All right. Good afternoon,
everyone. Good afternoon.
So we have a very technical
session coming up today.
And I would like to get
started where we
left off on Tuesday,
which is basically the setup
of the entry PGDR, right?
We basically went over
the way that the entry page
directory is being set up,
and we got to the
point of looking
at this code where
essentially we
are setting up the two elements
of the page directory,
the zeroth element and
the 512th element.
And we're basically performing
the following mapping.
We're mapping the
virtual frame numbers on
the left hand side to
the physical frame numbers
on the right hand side.
Okay? And this is
basically the code
in the X V six that you can
take a look at where
this mapping is actually
set up for entry PG DR.
So this is a recap
from the very,
very tail end of the
previous lecture.
And I'm going to go
fast today because we
have just an unbelievable
amount of technical content.
So this is kind of what it
looks like conceptually, okay.
And it was interesting to see
that for a lot of people,
this actually raises eyebrows.
Because for the first
time, what you are seeing
is at the very tail end of
the bootstrapping process,
we're setting up some
memory aliasing.
Okay? We are basically making
two virtual frames
or virtual pages on
the left hand side to point to
one physical frame on the
right hand side, okay?
And the two virtual frames
on the left hand side are
basically the four
megabyte large page at
the very bottom
of this memory of
the virtual memory
address space and
the very first four
megabyte chunk
starting at current base.
Okay. And we're
making it through
the setup of the entry PGDR
that we just went through,
we're making it point to
exactly the same physical frame
sitting in your DRM, okay?
So basically, that means
that you're able to
address some content
that sits in
this four megabyte physical
frame by either using
the low addresses
here or by using
the high addresses here with
the most significant
bits set to one.
After you've enabled
paging, okay?
So any questions about this?
So this is where we stopped
at the end of previous lecture.
And so some people
started asking
some very good questions
after the lecture.
One of those
questions was, well,
don't we map kind of
user space processes
into the low addresses,
and that is actually correct.
Though, basically,
after Kernel boots up,
it deletes the low
address entry,
okay, and it's going to
replace it with a bunch
of virtual frame number.
So a bunch of elements, page
directory entries that are
mapping user space
processes, okay?
Per process. And we're
going to get to that.
Okay, so what we
didn't get a chance to
cover, and very briefly,
let's go over this right now is
basically what we
already know kind of
what happens in the most
significant 20 bits of
our page directory entry
and page table entry.
We discussed that last time.
Okay?
The most significant 20 bits
are gonna give us what?
Yeah.
Yeah, they're going to give you
a physical page number for what?
So in case of PGE,
it's going to give you
a physical page number
for the next level
page table, right?
So it's a base address for
the next level page table.
And as we walk through
some of the code today,
this is I'm going to
make it very concrete.
So right now it may seem
a little bit conceptual,
even though it's quite concrete,
but we are going to
look at the code to
really drive this
home today, okay?
So the most significant
20 bits here are the
physical the page page table
physical frame number.
So the physical PFM for
the next level of
indirection, okay?
So what's happening in the least
significant 12
bits of our entry?
That's where a lot of very, very
useful mechanismic
stuff is happening.
For example, you have a very,
very important present bit.
We're going to in the
context of lab two,
you will figure out why
it's ultra important, okay?
It actually gives us the
ability to control things,
and it gives us
the ability to actually
implement copy and write.
Then we have the writable bit.
We have the user
versus super user bit.
One of the bits is
responsible for
basically specifying whether
or not the rights to
this particular address are
going to be right through
or they're going
to be right back.
One of the bits can
actually disable cache.
One of them keeps track
of whether or not the
page table entry,
for instance, is pointing to
an accessed frame, right?
One of them is keeping
track of the dirty state,
basically, whether or not we've
written to this frame already.
And that's super useful
information, right?
Because if we've written to it,
then maybe we need to do
something different when we are,
for example, performing a fork.
Okay. So then the important bit
is the page size bit, right,
because if it's zero,
it specifies that
the page table entry
the page directory entry is
pointing to a four
kilobyte page.
If page size, if
PS is set to one,
we know that we're actually
pointing to a four
megabyte page.
And we discussed
how we would set up
basically a single
level paging structure
where the frames that are
allocated to the
user space process
are four megabyte sized.
Going to recap that
really quickly.
Any questions about
the flag so far?
They're going to end up
being super useful and,
you know, you'll be
using, you know,
a good fraction of them
in the context of
the remaining labs,
like lab two and Lab three.
So it'll become very
concrete. Okay.
So, um, so one
of the things that I discussed
in previous lecture
is basically I
gave you sort of a canonical two
level paging mechanism
when you have
a page directory
and the PFNs and
the page directory are
pointing to the page table,
which is the second level
of indirection, right?
And the PfNs inside
the entries of the page
table are actually
pointing to the physical
address of the frame
that we are actually trying
to read and write, okay?
So that's one way of doing it.
What about why not
just use four kilobyte
single level paging?
So let's think about
that. So let's say
that we want to keep the offset,
at least significant
12 bits to still
indirect into a physical frame
of memory we're
reading and writing.
So we're allocating
four kilobyte
sized pages to the user
space address, okay?
And then instead of
having these two levels,
the page directory pointing
to page table page,
pointing to the physical
frame we're writing, right?
What if we were to combine the
most significant ten
plus ten and make it
20 bits to make that be a
single level of indirection.
What's the problem with that?
Yes.
Because then the page table will
be like a page
directory, I guess.
Page director, yeah. Big.
It'll be really big.
How big? Two through 20.
Times. Right, times the width,
right, that you're dealing with.
So the 20 bits,
remember, the 20 most
significant bits,
the way you should be
thinking about them is
that they give you the
index into the table.
So they index elements.
So it's element
granularity addressing.
Okay? So in order to get
the size of the page
directory, in this case,
you need to figure
out how many indices
you're able to
have in this case,
two to the 20th, that
is correct, right?
And then the size of each
element of the array.
And the size of each element
of the array is going to be
32 bits because we are
here talking about 32
bit operating system,
okay? And that's four bytes.
So the total size of
your page directory is
going to be four bytes,
4 megabytes, two to the 20th
times four, 4 megabytes.
Okay, well, that
doesn't seem too
bad or does it? What's
the problem with that?
Because remember, at the
I think two thirds into
the previous lecture,
we discussed the opposite
way of doing this.
We discussed having a very
small page directory,
like a four case sized
page directory by using
the most significant ten
bits to index into that.
And the remaining 22
bits we were using
for the frames we were allocating
to the process, right?
And we've already
discussed that.
Now I'm giving you a
different design option.
Third design option, in fact,
where we're doing
the opposite split
of the linear address.
We are combining the ten plus
ten most significant bits
to index into the
page directory,
and we're going to be
allocating four kilobyte
sized physical frames to
the user space process.
Okay? So Oh, yeah,
we're going to come back
to this when we sort
of summarize all of these
three different options.
So let's just focus
on this right now.
I think somebody
raised a hand, like,
what's the problem with the four
megabyte sized page director?
Yeah. The issue with
the page directory
itself takes up more than
a single frame in
physical memory?
Takes up more than what?
Single page frame
in physical memory.
Okay. Right. So basically,
the concern that you have
with this essentially is that
we're paying huge overhead
for page directory, right?
And how many page
directory pages
are we going to have in
the system at any
given point in time?
Can somebody give me sort
of an educated guess?
Yes. Exactly. The number
of processes, right?
That's another thing that came
up sort of at the
end of, I guess,
in the Q&A after the
previous lecture, right,
is that you need to
remember that we
need to maintain
this indirection.
We need to maintain these
pages per process, okay?
And if you have
thousand 24 processes
running in the system,
each of which at minimum needs
a single page directory,
a separate page
directory that is
not shared across them, okay?
And it's 4 megabytes sized.
You know, for thousand
24 processes,
how much memory
you're going to spend
just keeping track
of this metadata?
Just keeping track of
the page directories.
How much memory?
4 gigabytes, right?
So you have thousand
24 processes,
which is not a large
number at all, right?
And just to maintain, you know,
just to be able to
support this illusion of
isolation across processes in
the VMM component of the kernel,
you're paying four
gigabyte cost for that.
That's huge, right?
But did we take
care of the process
where we were splitting the
linear address as 20 and 12,
sorry, as ten and 22,
when we were
allocating 4 megabytes
sized page frames
to the process.
The problem there was
that we were actually
allocating the frames
were very large.
And even if the process
wasn't doing anything at all,
it was incurring quite a bit of
overhead and too much
memory was allocated,
too much memory was wasted.
Did we take care of that
use case with this design?
So same process, very
small process, right?
So it has just a little
bit of code and data,
a little bit of stack,
a little bit of heap.
Let's say one frame each.
You know, how much
memory is that process
using with this design?
Okay, one frame
for code and data,
one frame for stack,
one frame for heap.
With this design where
we're using, you know,
12 bits to index into
the page frames,
you know, how much memory is
that process going to use?
Not counting the
page tables, yes.
What's that? I was going
to give you a number.
I was going to say it's 101012.
No, no, it's going to
use three frames, right.
And each of the frames are
being indirected with the
12 least significant bits,
right, with the offset.
So they're four K sized.
So you have three frames,
times four K is 12 kilobytes.
Right? So you have taken
care of those processes.
You're not allocating
huge you're
not wasting memory
for small processes.
But you sort of pushed
the problem to a different
component of the system.
You pushed the
problem, the memory
overhead to the page
directories instead.
And so I wanted to emphasize
this because I think it's a
very cute little toy example.
It's extremely simple, okay?
But at the same
time, it actually
highlights what commonly happens
in the design of systems that's
called basically
Chasing the bottleneck.
Or Wakemo right?
Approach to system design.
You fix something for
a particular use case,
but you actually introduce
the problem somewhere else.
So you may think that
you've actually fixed
the problem for small processes,
and this may very
well be the case
if the number of processes
in the system is very small,
but you actually introduced
huge overhead on the
page directory size.
You guys see that? I hope
you appreciate that.
So we've thus far discussed like
three different ways
of splitting up
the linear address and
sort of the implications
associated with
each one of them.
Okay.
And so what would be the
advantages associated with that?
Well, given the virtual
address, the question is,
how many memory lookups does it
take to translate it to a
physical address, right?
So here we're sort of
doing a comparison to
a two level paging system and
a one level paging system.
So we've discussed this in
previous lecture, right?
You're here reducing the number
of memory lookups you have
to do in order to perform this
virtual to physical
address translation.
Okay? So there are advantages.
For any given design point,
you should be able to sort
of crystallize in your mind.
When you sort of go back to
the video recording,
go back to the slides,
you should be able to
crystallize in your mind,
kind of what the advantages
and disadvantages are. Okay?
All right, so did we do
this question, right?
How many memory operations
does it take to
translate a virtual address
to physical address in a
two level page table walk?
So what do you think would
be the answer to that?
Be bold, be proud.
Two, I hear twos, right?
So how many of you
think it's two?
Okay. Okay, good, good.
I think it's less than 50%,
but how many of you think
it's not two? Even fewer.
What is the rest doing? What
do you think it's zero?
Um, Okay, so actually,
it turns out that the answer
is indeed two, right,
because we have to perform
a memory read for the
page directory itself.
And then once we've accessed
the page directory,
we have to perform a memory read
for the page table, right?
And those are the
two memory reads
that are necessary in
order for us to get
a page table entry with
the PFN of the physical frame
that we are trying to access.
So if the question
is precisely stated,
how many memory accesses
are required in
this two level page table walk
for the purposes of
translating VA to PA,
the answer is two.
Okay?
You guys agree with that?
Okay. Nice. Now, here's
where I sort of
tried to put all of
these three different design
choices on a single slide.
We discussed three different
multi level paging
design choices.
The first one is
the one that you
might have learned
in 2,200, right?
It's the standard sort of
canonical two level paging,
where the split up of the
linear address is ten,
ten and 12, okay?
And everyone knows this.
Everyone is very, very
intimately familiar
with this two level
paging approach, right?
And what you may
not have thought
about up until this week,
right, is that you can also have
one level paging mechanisms.
And you can also do that
in two different ways.
Okay? Here, we're
splitting up ten and 22,
and you should immediately
tell me what is, you know,
what's the size of the page
directory in this case,
and what's the size
of the physical
frames we're allocating to use
the space process
just by looking at
this pair right off the bat,
it should just immediately
pop out in your head.
So how large is the physical
the page directory?
Was that?
Yeah, that's right.
Thousand 24 entries
were 32 bit system,
I must specify that.
So it's four K, right?
In this particular case, our
page directory is four K,
and the frames we're
allocating are how big?
Due to the power of 22,
which is 4 megabytes, right?
And so this is where
you start seeing sort
of heterogeneous frames
of memory being used.
In this case, normal size
frames and large large pages,
normal pages and large pages,
four K and four megabyte pages
being used at the same time.
And the use case
that we discussed
here is that what happens.
So once you look at a particular
design in the system,
try to come up with
corner cases or
the use cases that don't really
fit that design point very well.
We discussed small processes,
right with minimum memory
consumption, okay?
And I asked you, well,
if it has just a little bit of
activity in the code
and data segment,
a little bit of
activity on the stack,
and it allocates
something on the heap,
it uses approximately
two to three frames
of memory, right?
And memory is going
to be allocated to
the process at the
granularity of frames.
And so if it has any
minimum activity at all,
we're talking about allocating
two to three frames,
each of which is 4 megabytes.
And so we're going to allocate
huge amount of memory
eight to 12 megabytes,
minimum cost per process.
Wow, that's a lot. Is that okay?
Could be, if we don't
concern ourselves
with the number
of processes in the system.
Another way to split this up.
That's the third bullet
point right here, right,
is actually to have a
large page directory
and only use the 12
least significant bits
to indirect into your
physical frames.
Immediately, you
should be able to tell
me what is the size of
the page directory?
What is the size of
the physical frames
allocated to the process?
So page directory size.
Yes, yeah, don't
forget the times four.
This is one of the most common
mistakes that people make.
And I think I know why
that trips you up, okay?
Because when we look
at the 12 bits,
we say that the frame size
is two to the 12, right?
And the reason for that
is because this offset,
the 12 bits that are least
significant 12 bits,
are they are addressing
into the physical frame
at byte granularity.
They are counting bytes.
So every unique bit sequence
that is comprised
of those 12 bits
is counting a single byte.
That's why you have two
to the power of 12 bytes.
Now, when you're looking
at 20 right here,
okay, what is it counting?
Is it counting bytes?
Every unique bit
sequence consisting of
these 20 bits is
indexing into an array.
You're counting
elements of the array.
And so that's why you need to
also multiply by the size of
the element of the array to
actually get the
page directory size.
Does that click? Okay, good.
Because it's going
to be on the test.
Alright. And so we discuss
the overheads associated with
supporting the paging mechanism.
You know, let's pop up a
stack a little bit, right?
The paging mechanism is one of
the really cool mechanisms
that we discuss in
this class because it provides
us with very good example of
isolation and protection.
That's why we care
about paging mechanism.
We provide processes with
the illusion of running in
isolation in the system.
We provide all sorts
of great things
with paging mechanism,
including memory over
subscription, right?
Including isolation.
But it does come with overhead.
There are two different kinds of
overhead that we have
already discussed.
The first one is the memory
overhead because for
every single process,
you have to pay the cost of
all of the page table pages
that have been allocated to
maintain this V to P mapping.
Okay. And so we want to try
to minimize that somehow.
And that's what the
multi that's what
the multi level paging system
actually accomplishes
it accomplishes.
It actually accomplishes
the ability to
minimize this memory
overhead associated with
all the page table
pages combined that
participate collectively in the
virtual to physical
address translation.
Okay. So we discuss
the memory overhead.
There's also a latency overhead.
Basically, how many
steps does it take?
How much time does
it take for me to
actually take a linear address
or virtual address and translate
it to physical address.
And the reason we care about
this is because it's on
the critical path of
the memory operation we
are trying to perform.
As application
developers, all we care
about is performing a
read or write in address,
right, somewhere in memory.
But this goes through
this multi step
overhead associated with that
that we refer to as
the page table walk.
So we want to
minimize that, too.
And now you have sort of
a multi objective
optimization function
because simultaneously,
we're trying to
minimize the memory
overhead and at the same time,
minimize the latency overhead,
and they are at odds
with each other.
And that's what makes system
design really cool, okay?
Because you want to
make it fast and you
don't want to use
too much memory.
And they're actually at
odds with each other,
because the last bullet
point right here,
the way to accomplish this
is to reduce the number
of layers of indirection,
right, to go with a single
level paging system.
But it increases it balloons
the memory overhead.
Now, you try to hammer
the memory overhead,
and the way to do
that is increase
the number of levels
you have to go through.
So they're at odds with each
other. Does that make sense?
So, you know, as you
go into fourth year
courses and you'll
actually start
thinking more about
system design, you
know, things like this,
the trade offs associated with
Sim system design
is precisely what
creates elegant research and
elegant systems,
for that matter.
Okay.
Um, now, what about
X 86 64, right?
Nobody uses 32 bit
systems anymore.
What about X 86 64?
Well, how many of
you find this a little bit scary
just by looking at this diagram?
Something incomprehensible,
something hard.
So do not fear because
the principle is
exactly the same, okay?
You know, basically,
what I have to
tell you from the very
beginning is that we are
actually using only 48 bits
of the 64 linear address space,
and there's some way that
we have to split it up.
So if I give you some
arbitrary system,
I don't know, 36
bit address system.
I'm not going to
do that, probably.
But in this particular case,
not to confuse
you, we're working
with a 64 bit address system.
I have to specify how many bits
of that linear address actually
participate in
the virtual physical
address translation, okay?
Because it doesn't
have to be 64.
In this particular
case, it's only 48.
And then the next question
you want to ask is,
well, how do we
break it up, right?
And that depends on
a couple of things.
That depends, for example,
on what page sizes we are
actually natively
supporting in the system.
We're already used to the
page size of four K, right?
And indeed, if you look
at the last level
here on this slide,
you can see that the
least significant 12 bits
are used to offset,
right, into the physical frames
allocated to the process.
So we already know
what to do with
the 12 bits of the
Sonia address.
We should be feeling better now.
How many bits do we have left?
So 48 -12 is what?
Yeah, 36, right?
36. Okay, so what do we want
to do with those 36 bits?
And this is a very open
ended question, right?
So the way to think about
it is that you will
probably have some number
of page table pages, right?
You will probably
have some number
of these directories and
some fragments of
the linear address
indexing into them, right?
So the first question
that comes to mind is,
how big are those
page table pages?
Let's go with the
simplest design,
Let's try to use
the same size page
for everything, right?
So we want to use four
K for everything,
which is to do the power
of 12 bytes, right?
And so the question is,
how many elements were able to
fit into 4 kilobytes
in a 32 bit system?
How many elements we
were able to fit into
our four kilobyte page
directory in a 32 bit system.
1024, right?
Two to the power of ten.
Remember? So you had ten.
You had ten, and you had 12,
and we were using this to
index into our page directory.
This is our PGD.
So two to the power of ten.
This is ten bits right here.
To the power of ten
is 1024 elements,
each of which was four bytes
because we're in 32 bit system.
We are in a 64 bit system.
Now, we want to use the same
four kilobyte or two to
the power of 12 byte pages in
order to store our tables.
How many elements can we store?
Oh, God. Come on, people.
Wake up. Yes.
So why 1024? How did
you arrive at that?
If you have 1024,
each element is going
to be how many bytes?
My two bytes.
No, it's going to be
four bytes, right?
So if you divide that by 1024,
which is two to the
power of ten, right,
you're going to get
two to the power of
two bytes per element.
And this was the case for
a 32 bit system because
32 bits is four bytes.
Now, we're on a 64 bit system.
So on a 64 bit system,
the way to figure
out the number of
elements is to take
the page size,
due to the power of 12
byte page size that
we want to use to store
the page directory, okay?
And we divide that by what?
To the three.
Two to the power of three,
which is basically the eight
bytes that correspond to
64 bit wide elements
of the table.
Make sense? So two to
the power of three,
this is not a magic number.
It's just the number of bytes,
eight bytes that
corresponds to 64 bits.
And the table here is going
to consist of elements,
the size of which matches
whether or not we're
in a 32 bit system
or 64 bit system, right?
So we're dividing that
by two to the power
of three, and we get what?
Two to the power of nine,
which is 512, okay?
That's the 512 elements
that we can store on
a 64 bit system in 4
kilobytes sized table.
Okay, well, we've arrived
at something interesting.
512 bytes, which is two
to the power of nine.
How many bits do I need
to index into that table?
Nine. Interesting. And so we had
so let me we
had basically a total of
48 bits to work with.
48, and we decided
that we're going
to use the least significant
12 as the offset.
Okay? And we have
36 bits remaining,
and 36 magically divides
into nine to have four
chunks of nine bits.
Okay. So we have nine bits,
nine bits, nine bits,
nine, nine, nine,
and nine, totaling 48 bits,
each of which is
going to indirect or
index into the corresponding
page directory or page table.
So this is how we
actually arrive
at This is how we come on.
We actually arrive at
the four level paging
system on a X 86 64.
You have nine bits that are most
significant within
the 48 bit chunk.
They're not the
most significant.
They're the most significant
within the 48 bit chunk
that are going to
indirect into page,
our this thing right here.
PML four E. And then
the same thing happens.
We indirect into that, right,
by using essentially
the physical address
inside CR three as the base,
and then the most significant
nine bits as the index.
This gives us the
page table element,
which consists of a
physical frame number that
gives us the base address for
the next level for L two.
Okay. And then we use
the next nine bits of
the linear address to index
into that second level page,
the L two, right?
And this gives us
the page table entry
with a physical frame number of
the third level page table
that's called the
page table here,
right? And so on and so forth.
You have four levels
of indirection.
And finally, the four
is actually going
to have a page table entry
with a physical frame number
that gives us access to
the actual physical frame
in memory that we want
to perform an operation.
So instead of doing two
lookups for the page tables,
we do four lookups for
the page table plus
the additional read or
write operation that we
actually wanted to do
from the very beginning.
Five memory operations total to
perform a read or
write on an X 86 64.
Yes. Six.
Yeah, it can, right? And so
we need to concern ourselves
with this huge overhead.
It's exactly the same situation
as I described before.
Huge overheads associated
with memory, right?
And also huge overheads because
you're performing all of
these lookups on the critical
path of the VT P map.
And so we have certain things
that help us with that, right?
So remember, I mentioned
that there are overheads,
and we discussed this
very vigorously,
and I'm glad that
I'm recording this.
Please go back and
review the lecture.
Okay? So discuss that
very vigorously,
and I sort of motivated the
fact that there's a lot
of overhead on a critical path
on a memory read and write.
Now, what do we do about this?
Well, it turns out
that we actually have
some hardware support in
order to make this faster.
Memory management unit in
particular actually allows
us to speed things up,
and the TLB cache is actually
a huge part of that, right?
You know, when in doubt, try to
think about what can
we possibly hash.
And TLB cache actually
gives us the ability.
It's sort of um a multi
way associative cache
that actually gives
us the ability to
save VA to PA mapics
virtual address
or virtual frame number to
physical frame number mappings.
I have to be very careful here
because this is not
precisely correct.
What it actually gives us
the ability to save is
the virtual address to
page table entry mapping.
So that simultaneously
caches what
the physical frame number
should be associated
with this virtual address and
what the flags should be.
The permission flags
should be associated with
this virtual memory
address, okay?
All right.
Well, here's another
interesting twist.
Now, let's say that I mean,
this is a statement of fact
TOB is going to
be fixed in size.
There's going to be some
number of elements,
the VA to PA mappings
that it's going to be
able to have, right?
Let's say 128, okay?
Now, if you are thinking about
the choice of one
of those two single
level paging systems,
either the one with a
large page directory
or the one with a
small page directory,
which one would you choose to
maximize the hit ratio in TLB?
So that choice actually
has implications
on how often you're
going to hit or
how often you're going to
miss in TLB as a result.
How cool is that?
Right? It seems so trivial.
You know, Okay,
let's split it up
into four MEG and four K
or four K and four MEG,
but it actually
turns out to have
orders of magnitude
difference on the TLB hits.
And the reason for
this is because
the larger your last
level pages are,
let's say, 4 megabytes, right?
That means that you
understand that every
element of the TLB
actually is a virtual frame
number to a page table entry.
And page table entry,
the more memory it addresses,
let's say 4 megabytes, you know,
the more the entire TLB
is capable of addressing.
Right? So in this case,
128 times 4 megabytes.
If we're using a
small page door and
a large physical
frame. Makes sense?
If we flip that design,
then we actually have
exactly the same
number of elements,
but each element is
essentially addressing
4 kilobytes and three orders
of magnitude less memory.
And so that means that
with that kind of design,
you're going to be missing
in the TOB a lot more.
Make sense? Yes. Side TLB,
you're addressing a
large amount of space,
you need to have a
larger page table entry
in your TLB mapping.
Doesn't that mean
that you would spit
there less page table
mappings to your t?
Well, so so no,
because basically the size of
the TLB entry is
going to be entirely
dependent on the size
of the PT, right?
So in the 32 bit system,
it's going to be 32 bits because
the size of a PT is 32 bits.
So the size of the TLB
entry itself is going to be
governed by whether
or not you're on
a 32 bit system versus
64 bit system, right?
It's not going to be governed
by the choice of, like,
one or the other single level
paging system. Makes sense.
And so what's really tricky
here is that basically
thinking about how much
a single element of TLB
is able to address.
And the more it's
able to address,
the more you're going
to be hitting in TLB.
Statistically speaking, right?
If we just apply, like
a Monte Carlo simulation
approach to this,
you know, statistically
speaking,
the larger more bits,
the more least significant
bits you're using
to offset into your
physical frames of memory,
you know, the better your TOB
hit ratio is going to be. Okay?
So just remember that. So what's
interesting is that I really
spent a lot of time in
this lecture trying to sort
of motivate that there are
real and very
significant implications
with every single design choice,
even though those
design choices may
seem quite trivial to you and,
in fact, boring, right?
But what's not boring
is the trade off spaces
that they're inducing and
how to reason about that.
Okay. So there's
some optimizations
to TLB that also exist.
Like, for example, you can
have instruction only caches,
like ITLB you will always,
if you look at the
process of SPAC,
you will actually
figure out what
the sizes of those
different types of TLB are.
And there are actually
reasons for this.
Like, can somebody tell
me why you would want to
split up TLB into
ITOB and GTOB, right?
This is a class that's all
about thinking, right?
That's all about questioning
the design choices.
So why would I want to split
up TLB into ITOB and GTLB?
Can somebody venture a guess?
Just came up with
this right now.
Yes. Locality, you're going
to be going back,
say, you have a loop.
So in your set of instructions,
you might be going back
to the same instruction.
Mm hmm. Fine. Mm hm.
You're iterating, like,
the same star function
or something.
Like, you're gonna be
going back to the spot.
So much more temporal
locality with VA
to PA mappings for
instructions compared to data,
right? Okay. Anything else?
It has to do with,
um, let's say,
even if you have
the same temporal locality
between instructions and data,
it's still preferable
to split it up.
Yeah. But that's a good one.
On average, there are
much fewer instructions,
and there will be adated
macsre chamber on the memory.
So you would want to have
a smaller you want to have
a smaller ITOBm which
make it faster.
So your actual instruction
in your computer will be faster.
So you're saying that
basically this gives you
the ability to actually save
area on the chip, right?
Because you can make
the TOB itself.
The size of the TOB
itself smaller.
Is that what you're
saying? I think
it's smaller for the
sake of speeding
up access.
Okay. Okay.
Yeah, that's an
interesting point.
What I was trying to get to is
actually something that's
highly relevant to Lab two.
And it's the question of when
you want to flush the TLB.
Right? So with the data,
you have much higher
probability of
actually making
changes to the VA to
PA mappings and
actually allocating
pages and making changes
to the page table entries.
And the changes to the
page table entries,
they are going to
incur or trigger
TLB flashes a lot more
frequently compared
to the instructions.
So the instructions actually
read only the immutable, right?
So once you've loaded your set
of frames that are
responsible for the code,
you're not going to
change that, okay?
Well, I mean, in
most cases, you're not
going to change that.
You can, but you're not
Whereas with the data segment,
it's like, strictly
speaking writable, right?
You're you're going to be
doing a lot more writes,
and as a result of that,
you're actually going to be
messing with the VA to be
a mapping with much
higher probability
of data compared
to instructions.
Okay, let me leave
it at that. Okay.
And so, This is
where I would like to
switch to a different
set of slides.
So bear with me for 1 second.
Uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh,
uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh,
uh, uh, uh, uh,
uh, uh,
uh,
Okay.
I took a while. Okay, I'm
going to get to administration
if we have time.
Let's talk about the page walk.
So let's try to make it very
concrete with a walk through of
the actual code
written in XV six
that you should be able to
find and actually go
through it yourself.
This is a walk PG DR.
How many of you have gone
through this already?
So it takes on input
a virtual address
right here, VA, right?
And it also takes a pointer
to a page directory and
some parameter that basically
defines whether or not we
actually want to
allocate, right?
So it tries to output a
page table entry pointer.
That's the purpose
of Block page PGDR.
So it is responsible for
VA to PA translation.
Now, here's how this happens.
We take a virtual
address right here,
and we basically extract
the ten most significant bits
of that virtual address.
This is our page
directory index.
So the Pgx of
VA is basically the ten
most significant bits.
And then we use that
to actually index into
PGDR precisely as we
already explained, right?
And this gives us we take
the address of that.
So this gives us the pointer
to a page directory entry.
So PGE is a page
directory entry,
and we get a pointer to a page
directory entry by taking
a page DR index of the VA
and indexing into PGDR.
That seems pretty straightforward
so far, right? Okay.
And by the way, for those of
you who want a reference,
PDX is that code on
the right hand side,
because the way to extract
ten most significant bits is
you perform a right shift,
right to get rid
of everything to
the right of those ten
most significant bits,
and you're going to
basically end it with
a three FF which is the
ten bits set to one.
Very simple. Okay?
Everything really,
really makes sense here.
And so you get a page directory
entry, the page d entry.
Now, what do you do
with it? The next line
is very interesting right here.
So the If statement is checking
whether or not the
list whether or
not the present
bit is set, okay?
And that's going to be super
important for lab two.
We're checking whether or not
the page directory entry
is actually pointing
to what we discussed
so far is that it's
supposed to point to the next
level page table, right?
But it may or may not exist.
It may not have been allocated.
It may or may not be
present in memory.
So that's what
we're checking for
with this I condition, okay?
And let's say if
it's not present,
let's go to the
else clause, right?
And we're basically
just going to allocate.
We perform **** which
is going to give us
the page table frame
because by the end of
the return statement,
we need to have a
page table to index
into second ten bits
of the linear address.
So we need to have page
table coming from somewhere.
In the else clause,
we've essentially
allocated it and we
set it to zero. Okay?
And we want to make
sure that we set it to
zero because we want all of
those bits that I described
previously to be set
to zero by default,
including the present bit,
which is very important.
Okay? And then we update
the page directory entry,
which pointed us to the void in
the first place with
the address with
the physical address of the
page table that we have just
allocated or with
the present bit
and the right bit
and the user bit.
So that's what we're
writing back into
the page directory entry if
it was pointing into null.
Okay? Now, if it was
not pointing into null,
so in other words,
if the page table entry,
if the present bit was set,
we're right here in the if body.
Now, what's happening here?
Well, the first thing that we're
going to do is we're going to
extract that base address
that I was talking about, right?
It's the second level page
table page base address.
And it's a physical address
as we discussed, right?
It's the physical address of
the second level
page table page.
And then we're going to because
it's a physical address,
the next thing we're doing
is we're performing this
physical to virtual translation,
the p2v translation.
That's going to give
us a virtual address.
And we cast it, and
this is going to
become our pointer
stored in PG tab.
This is our page table pointer.
So now we have a
handle that points
at the second level
page table page.
And what do we want to
do with that handle?
We want to index into it,
right, and we want to
get a page table entry.
And that's exactly what
we're doing right here.
On the return line, we
basically take the PG tab,
take the virtual address,
extract the second most
significant ten bits.
That's what PTX
stands for, right?
It's the page table page index.
And of course, you
should be able to write
a macro for PTX already
by now in this class,
because all we have
to do is shift right,
get rid of the 12 bits that
we're using for offset,
right, and mask
the ten least significant
bits post shift.
Right? That makes sense?
Okay, and there is a
code for that, right?
Our PTX shift is the 12 bits.
So we take the VA, we get rid of
the 12 least significant bits
that are used for offset, right,
and we mask it with, again,
three FF, which is
ten bits set to one.
That's how we get the
page table index.
Page table index is a number.
It's an index into
the page table.
That's exactly what we're doing.
We're taking page
table right here and
indexing into it with
the number that we got.
Percent means we take
the address of that,
and that is a pointer to
a page table entry
we have just found.
Now, I got the page table entry.
Now, there's a bunch of
things I can do with that.
First of all, I want to put
it in the TOB cache because
now the VFN that I started with
the virtual frame number that
you can extract from VA.
Okay? The virtual
frame number you can
extract from VA is going to
point this page table entry.
I want to save that
mapping, right?
If it doesn't already exist.
And then I can also extract
the physical frame number for
the page that I'm actually
trying to write to.
Okay.
So, finally, I guess,
let's conclude this lecture
by recapping what was
happening with boot
allocation in entry dS.
Okay? This is the first kind of
entry point in the Elf binary
that you have just loaded
with your bootloader.
Okay? So you're starting with
a saving whatever you had
in CR four register in EIX.
You're basically oring that
with a page size
extension flag in order
to provide support for
those four megabyte
sized pages, right?
Because we're dealing
with four megabyte
sized pages at this
point in time,
we're moving sort of the
result back into CR four,
and then we're essentially
loading the entry PGDR into EIX.
And here, what
happens actually is
another evidence of
and the answer to
the question that
I posed earlier in
my previous lecture is that
this is a v2t mapping
right here, right?
A VTP mapping which implies
that we want to put
the physical address
associated with
entry PGDR into AX and then
subsequently into CR three.
CR three is loaded with
the physical address
of entropGDR.
So does R three take virtual
address or physical address?
We have evidence that it takes
physical address right
there in the code.
So I explained conceptually
why that should be the case,
and I also showed you the code,
why that is the case, right?
And here's the entrPGDR that
we've already discussed,
which sets up memory aliasing
for the first time in
the system by pointing
the Vafan of zero and Vafan of
512 to exactly the same
physical frame in memory.
Okay? Alright. And just
to illustrate what happens
here, this happens.
Both of these via fans
on the left hand side,
on the left hand
side, you have a view
of the virtual address space.
On the right hand side, you have
a view of the physical
address space.
They both point to
exactly the same
four megabyte physical frame.
Okay, so to conclude,
what's happening with XV
six versus other
operating systems?
What can you possibly expect
with your wonderful XV six,
which I love for the
purposes of teaching, right?
It currently has
no ability to have
multiple virtual pages
mapped to a single page,
which makes copy and
write impossible, right?
Because copy and
write implies that
you need to have the ability
to have many to one mappings.
And it also makes shared
memory also very difficult.
Someone asked me, I think,
a week ago after class,
Well, how do you make
shared memory work, right?
Well, the only way
to make it work to
share memory is you're
sharing a physical frame.
That means that the
VON of process one and
that separate VF fan of
process two need to have
a way of pointing to
the same PON to have
exactly the same mapping
to a physical frame
number, right?
So you cannot do that
in XV six right now,
the way it is on your
computer at this time, right?
And the reason for
that is because Xp six
expects the kernel to map
all of physical memory,
including all user programs.
And once the kernel and
a user program at most have a
mapping to a physical page,
the physical page can
have no more mappings.
Another way to say
this or to think
about it is that physical
page mapping is binary.
Given any physical frame,
it is either free
and you can use
it or it's used and you
cannot use it anymore,
it's used by exactly
one userspace address,
exactly one user space VfN.
However, we do know that
other operating systems may
have user programs map
virtual pages to the same
physical page, right?
Because we want to be able to
enable copy and write support.
We want to be able to load
shared libraries into
the separate virtual
address spaces but
only have one physical copy in
our memory for the
purposes of savings.
That's what Unix actually got
right back in the
70s and 80s, right?
And that means that we
need to do something with
those physical frame metadata.
We need to make sure that
we are keeping track of
how many virtual
frames are pointing to
the physical frame and take
care of that accounting, okay?
And this is where I'm
going to stop for today.
Thank you.