Okay.
I think we're ready to go and
we're ready to rock and roll.
This is probably one of the best
lectures of the whole course,
so I hope you guys are excited
for it as much as I am.
Today, this is a
third lecture in
the sequence of virtual memory
lectures that we
have in this class.
Third and second last, sadly.
The last lecture touching upon
virtual memory management
is going to be Thursday.
Let's go ahead and dive in.
Okay? A few points
of administratvi
a Lab zero has been graded
and grades have been posted.
You should be able to view
your scores on Canvas.
As far as the specifics
are concerned,
I'm sure you've all
noticed by now that
we're sort of using
this combination
of grade scope and Canvas.
So Canvas is going to
be the ground truth for
actual grade keeping
the grading.
And of course, Gradescope
is going to have
some more fine
grain information,
for example, some
point breakdown for
the specific parts of the
labs that you have submitted.
Hopefully, that's
visible. Okay, good.
So lab one was due on Friday.
And so the only reason I bring
this up is because I do see
150 submissions for lab
one, so that's awesome.
That's actually
more than the lab
zero submissions, my handful.
So I'm pretty happy about that.
People are engaging with
the class as you should be.
Another reason why
I'm mentioning
this is because this also marks
February 3 marks the late June.
My have noticed that
on grade scope.
It's basically when the maximum
allowable late days
allocated for a lab expire.
So that means that we are
now unblocked on grading.
We don't start grading until
the maximum allowable late dates
have expired for a given lab.
Alright, so lab two
was released on
Friday on January 3 first.
And I'll just reiterate since
I didn't get a chance to
do that at Thursday last week,
is that it's much more
involved than lab one.
You should not think
that, oh, you know,
I feel pretty comfortable
with lab one,
I should be okay for
the rest of the class.
I mean, possible
that's possible,
but definitely do not
treat Lab one as a proxy
for lab for subsequent
labs, okay?
And you may have noticed that
we do have three weeks
allocated for lab two,
and we do think that you
will have to use up all
of those three weeks.
The way to think about it, spend
ten to 15 hours per
week for this lab,
and then you should
be okay because it
does take anywhere 30-45
hours to complete.
Total, total. Not
per week, total.
So ten, 15 hours per week.
Let's say ten, 12
hours per week,
to feel good about it.
You know, try to aim to get
it done by the end of Week two,
take advantage of
the supervised labs
that are going to be
focusing on lab today's
Tuesday, right?
So tomorrow and the
week after tomorrow,
it's all going to
be about lab two,
copy and write and
things like that, okay?
So you'll get a lot
of help and support.
Through the execution
of lab two.
Lab two is, you
know, oftentimes,
it's sort of cited as one of
the most exciting labs in
this class, but
actually it varies.
Some people like lab
three more than Lab two.
It's going to be a
personal preference.
But it is when things get
super exciting as far
as the hands on component of
this class is concerned.
Any questions?
Okay.
So, I wanted to bring
up the lab partners.
I'm going to have to sync
up with the TAs because I
do see 24 of you
still unassigned.
Not exactly sure if
anybody having problems
with the group signup or
how it interacts with Gradescope
and your gradescope submissions?
A anybody having
difficulties with that?
If not, then this
is just a no up.
But I did notice that there
are 24 unassigned students.
You know, I urge you guys,
to make sure that you self
assign yourself to a group,
even if you're going solo.
On Lab two, okay?
And the release of the
lab was blocked on this.
We could have
released it earlier.
I was due last week, and
lab two is going to be all
about virtual memory management.
You've seen this pec by now,
the primary goal is
going to be to make things
more efficient in X V six.
We're going to talk about
what that means much more
precisely in this
class, in this lecture.
You're going to be exploring
two powerful techniques,
specifically copy and
write forking and
lazy versus eager
zero page allocation.
And, you know, those are
not just vocabulary words.
They're actually
technical terms.
The lazy and eager are
technical terms and systems.
There are a lot of, you know,
systems papers and
systems design decisions
that were made one way
versus the other way,
and there are advantages
and disadvantages of both.
So for example, if you're
doing something lazy,
that means you're deferring
decision making to
a later time or potentially
to the last possible time
when you can make a
control decision.
This comes up in
scheduling, for instance,
trying to pre allocate
all of the resources
ahead of time or defer
the actual allocation or spatio
temporal allocation of resources
to the process when you
actually have much
more information
and can take advantage of
a much more up to date
dynamic state knowledge
of the system, right?
And you'll see what that
means specifically in
the context of virtual
memory management this week.
Okay, so we've covered
the slides last lecture,
so I will skip through those.
And get to the point
where we stop.
So this is the slide
where we stopped.
I sort of wanted to
highlight this because
it sort of captures
simultaneously what
the limitations of
your XV six operating system
are and the opportunities
for improvement.
Anytime you see something
that is a limitation,
it also should ring a bell
that this is also
an opportunity for
improvement in any
system design.
So currently, the XV
six operating system
you're working with
has no ability to have
multiple virtual pages
mapped to a single page, right?
That's a severe limitation
because that makes Copy
and write impossible.
Because in order for
copy and write to work,
you do need to have many to
one mappings working, right?
It also makes shared
memory mapping
difficult because in order
for shared memory to work,
you need to have the
ability for one,
two, or a couple of
physical frames of
memory to be pointed
to from different disjoint
virtual address spaces.
Okay, so describing what the
limitations of XV six are.
And what specifically becomes
hard as a result of
those limitations.
XV six expects the kernel to
map all of physical
memory up to 2 gigabytes,
so any user program can map
virtual pages to
three physical pages.
And once the kernel and
a user program have a map
into a physical page,
that physical frame of memory
can have no more mappings.
So the implication of
that is that if you
look at any given physical
frame or physical page,
I use those terms
interchangeably.
If that's already been mapped,
then it can be in
one of two states.
Essentially the
mapping is binary.
Physical frame of memory is
either free or it's used.
Okay? But we know very
well by now that
operating systems do have
many user programs mapping
virtual pages to the
same physical page,
and that's essentially how copy
and write support
is enabled, right?
We also briefly
discussed as one of
the use cases of
taking advantage
of memory aliasing and multiple
VA to single PA mapping.
One of the use cases of that is
shared libraries,
because, you know,
do we want shared libraries
to sort of be replicated and
copy it into every single
virtual address space
for every single process?
Let's say every single process
largely or with very
few exceptions,
is going to use Lip C. Do we
want to make a copy of Lip C
for every single of
thousands and thousands
of processes, right?
That seems like an
unnecessary duplication.
So why don't we go ahead and
share that? Well, how
do we share that?
Well, we need to
have the ability
to have multiple VAs point to
the same PA. Let me know
if I'm going too fast.
A lot of that is
just kind of recap.
We're going to get
into the specifics
and the technicalities
of this in this.
In this lecture, the
lecture is super exciting.
And so I want to get to
that as soon as I can.
Okay. So now we have virtual
memory via paging, right?
We've discussed the basics of
virtual memory management.
We've discussed kind of
the mechanismic design
of virtual memory management,
of paging, right?
And I'm using those terms
very deliberately because
we also talked about
the advantages and
disadvantages of
the different mechanism designs
especially during the
previous lecture.
So paging is a mechanism
for memory isolation
and protection.
Paging itself, as we
have come to learn,
is actually a very
powerful primitive, right?
But what does it
actually let us do?
Why should we care as
application developers?
Let's say you don't care about
operating systems, right?
low level system design.
Why do I care about paging?
Can anyone think of a way to
describe the
mechanism of paging?
Like, what do we remember as
the benefits of heavy paging at
a high level from the
application developers
perspective? What can we do?
Yeah.
That thing to worry about.
Alasfting with
other applications.
Right, right. Okay, so
basically the answer there
was that we kind of remove
the cognitive burden from
the application developers
mind so that they don't have to
reason about physical
resource allocation, right?
So we're providing that illusion
that they are running in
their own virtual address space
so that they don't have to worry
about anybody else using
these physical resources
at the same time.
So you're again, kind
of talking about the
isolation here, right?
So that's removing
the cognitive burden
from the application
developers mind,
but also providing the
illusion of isolation.
Anything else we can do
with Page So many things.
The full slide of those
things coming up.
So we've covered standard
isolation, right?
What else can we do?
Any other guesses?
Yeah.
So permissions,
what specifically?
Permissions is a mechanism to
do something at a high level.
Page to read or write
it or write to it.
Okay, so yeah, you're basically
controlling the ability to read
or write to a page using
permission bits, right?
But think higher level.
If you were so
that's a mechanism.
That's like your hammer, right?
You don't say, Oh, I like
a hammer because I
can use it to hammer.
You can actually say, Oh, I
can build a house, right?
So what's the analogy of
building a house here?
Yeah.
Say. So shared memory, right?
Enabling shared memory.
Yeah, so paging now allows
us to enable shared memory.
In other words, the
super highest order bit
here is that we get
to lie and be lazy.
We constantly lie
to the processes,
and we'll see exactly
how that works.
And we can also allow ourselves
to be lazy by deferring some of
the heavyweight operations that
are quite costly to perform
if we were eager about
performing them.
Okay? So the line
here and the laziness
here is going to be precisely
defined over the course
of this lecture.
So in other words,
paging is actually paging
actually affords us a
level of interaction
which enables for us
to interpose on the control
path of the application.
And this is very powerful.
So basically, an application is
completely unaware of
the fact that there
exists an omniscient and
omnipotent observer
that is capable of
interposing on its
control path in
some specific scenarios
when it's trying to
access memory in
this case, okay?
And we also get the ability to
suspend the reality and
modify the behavior of the
underlying mechanisms.
So that seems very high level.
And the analogy, the
high level analogy,
I'll draw here is the deja
vu principle in the matrix.
Does anybody remember the
deja vu scene in the matrix?
Am I talking to the
wrong audience?
Have you seen the Matrix?
Yeah? This is, like,
quite simply the absolute
best Sci fi movie out there.
Okay, have you seen this? So
this is the deja vu scene,
basically when
there was a change
that was made in
the matrix code.
And Neil, basically the
protagonist of the story,
notices that, and somebody
explains to him that
whenever you see a dejavu,
somebody has changed
something under your feet.
So the illusion here is
this virtual world that they
are basically experiencing,
right, by being plugged
into the matrix.
And dejavu is when
somebody has changed
something under your feet.
So paging is precisely
something like this.
It gives us the ability to
suspend reality and make
changes under the feet
of the application
that's trying to run.
Okay.
So one of the first
things that we obviously
know are going to be enabled
by paging is copy
and write fork.
This is the main theme of
the lecture today, right?
In addition to this, we can
also perform demand paging.
We can also do lazy allocation.
So lazy allocation
refers to the fact
that let's say the application
has requested some
memory, right?
But we multiple
frames of memory,
but we're not going
to actually allocate
multiple frames of memory
at the time of the request.
We could allocate a single
frame of memory that's
a special physical frame and
point multiple VFNs
to a single PON,
right, and deal with that later,
kind of postpone dealing with
that lazy decision later
on if and only if the
application actually
tries to perform a in
those PFNs that were
allocated, right?
So that's lazy allocation.
We have on demand
zero filled pages
that are also enabled by paging.
We have the ability
to actually keep
track of 10 filled
page in the system.
This also enables
virtual allocation.
The shared memory, as
somebody pointed out,
is one of the bullet
points here, right?
We can map files to memory.
And we'll discuss
that next lecture,
so I'm not going to
dwell on this right now.
And we can also page to disk.
So this is basically
where one of the things
we're lying to the
process, right?
It goes back to what are we
lying to the process about is
how much physical memory
we actually have in
the system, right?
Because we're giving them a full
32 bit virtual address space
to work with, right?
And we don't want
them to think about
the physical memory
limitations unless,
of course, they start
worrying about performance.
But let's not talk
about that just yet.
We don't want them to worry
about that in principle.
And so in order to be
able to support it,
once we start running out of
physical frames that have
already been allocated
to the process,
we have no more physical
resources to give.
We got to do
something because we
keep lying to the
process that there is
no memory because there
is in their virtual
address space,
and they're calling
Malec. So what do you do?
Well, what do you do? Anyone?
Yeah. Print physical memory
with the page saved
in the disk of the
current application
that's calling Malec and then
perform the operation
and then swap back and
the other programs
its yeah, exactly.
So exactly what you said.
Basically, we can choose
some physical frames,
and that's a matter of
policy which physical frames
we're going to choose.
But the mechanism here is
the paging mechanism that's
invoked in order for us to
actually swap out
specific physical frames
to disk so that we can allocate
those physical frames for
mapping to the new via fence
that we're trying to map.
Okay. And we're going to discuss
this as well, not today.
But I just wanted to give
you a laundry list of all of
the things that we
can actually do with
just one hammer, paging.
And one more thing is
memory oversubscription.
As it's sort of related to
the previous bullet point,
you're able to
oversubscribe by allocating
more virtual memory than
the physical memory that you
actually have in the system,
and you would not be able
to do that without paging.
So it sounds like a very
powerful mechanism, right?
Probably one of the
most powerful and
the most elegant
mechanisms in the kernel.
Okay, so let's talk
about copy and write.
Copy and write fork
in particular.
So here's the
question number one,
do we need to copy
the entire virtual
address space on fork?
Because remember, during the set
of previous lectures
I told you, right,
and I clarified that
very explicitly
that we have to essentially
perform a copy of all
of the physical frames
allocated to a process because
they need to be unique.
They need to have their
own page directory,
they need to have their own
page set of page table pages.
And, of course,
they need to have
their own physical frames
that were allocated,
right, where they're performing
their reads and writes.
So logically,
they should be completely
separate and disjoint.
But if we're performing a fork,
first of all, does everybody
know what fork is, right?
First, table stakes first.
Does everybody know what for?
What is fork?
Anyone? Yes. It's a
new child process,
the same as a parent process.
So you're basically
cloning a parent process,
right, to create
the child process.
Yeah. Okay, so you're creating
a copy of a process, right?
You're creating a
copy of a process.
And the question is how?
Like in the process of
creating a copy of
a parent process,
you know, do we need to copy
the entire virtual
address space on fork?
In other words, here's what it
would sort of
logically look like.
A given parent process would
have its own page directory,
then next level
page table pages,
each of which, you know,
sort of pointing to some set of
physical frames that
were already pre
allocated for physical
for that process, okay?
So here's a question.
Do we want to
make a copy of that
whole thing? Yes or no?
So why not? Seems
like we need to,
right, in order to
provide isolation.
Whoever said no, so why not?
Yes. Repeating.
We don't need to we're not
changing the contents
but if we're writing,
then we need to copy
it over. So it's Ah.
Okay, so basically the
high level bit there
is that it depends,
right, on what we
are going to do.
If we are so I really like
somebody's Piazza post when
they said, I don't get it.
You know, we're making
this whole copy,
and then we perform an exact
only to replace all of this.
So this copy is
entirely unnecessary.
And my response was,
like, Hold that thought, right?
So this is the lecture, we're
going to talk about it.
So hopefully that person
held that thought and hopefully
that person was in my section.
So basically, here, it is
logically, we, of course,
want to provide this
we want to lie to
the process that the entirety of
their page table pages and
physical frames was copied,
but physically, we do not
necessarily have to do that.
Here's another way to think
about it, visualize this.
So on the left hand side,
on the left hand side, let
me see if I have a pointer.
I'm afraid to click on anything.
Okay. Okay, on the
left hand side,
you have a virtual
address space,
and on the right hand side, you
have a physical address space.
And you have a parent here at
the top and you have a
child here at the bottom.
Okay? And let's just
say that the parent has
three virtual pages
mapped to physical pages.
So they have some one
frame four kilobyte sized
virtual frame at
the very bottom of
the physical address probably
pertaining to code and data,
right, mapping to
zero X, cafe right?
And then they have
something at the top.
Let's say this red one, probably
referring to the stack,
mapping a physical frame on
the right hand side, 0507 FE.
That's the contents of that
physical frame, right?
And then we perform a fork.
So this is our fork. And
so the child is going
to basically if we do nothing,
what's going to happen
in XP six right now,
if we do absolutely nothing,
the child is going to
inherit basically all of
these mappings and all of
these physical frames
on the right hand side.
And so by doing this,
you're going to write
out you're going to run out
of memory really quickly.
So your ability to oversubscribe
physical resources
is non existent,
essentially, right?
Is it necessary?
I think we have established
that it depends.
It's not necessary if
the child is just going to
be reading or performing
read operations on those
virtual frames because
then it makes sense to just send
those reads to the original
physical frames anyway.
Make sense? Okay. But this
is exactly what XV
six does today.
And we want to be
able to fix that.
We want to be able to
dedupe because we do want
to preserve the state
when the fork is
invoked on the parent.
But the way it is done
right now is inefficient.
Now, what would
the efficient way
of preserving the
state look like?
The efficient way of preserving
state would look like this,
where we actually de
duplicated all of
the references to
physical frames
immediately after the fork.
So that's pretty
straightforward, right?
Just wanted to have that
illustration. You guys with me?
Okay, so now the fork happens
and the child process,
the virtual frame numbers
or virtual page numbers
on the left hand side
in the child VA space,
right, are pointing to
the same physical frames on
the right hand side
immediately after the fork.
That would be an efficient
way of preserving stay,
but we're deferring some
work that has to happen
if the child were to decide
to mutate that state.
So that's what you
will make XP six do.
Okay, fantastic.
So we got to the point
where we believe it is
unnecessary to copy
the actual physical
frames of memory, right?
And that's what I have
here on this slide.
You have process one, pointing
to its own page directory.
You have Process two pointing
Each of the page
directories, remember,
has a set of PDs
that are pointing to page
table pages at the next level.
We're assuming a two
level paging system here.
And then on the right hand side,
there's a shared set of
physical frames pointed
to by the page tables
of process one and page
tables of process two.
So we're now sharing them.
So we got to the point
where we agree that this
is a good thing to do.
But here's the
question. Do we even
need a page directory
per process?
I told you we need
it, but do we?
And what about the page tables?
Do we need them per process?
Do they need to be duplicated?
Because they are on this slide.
Yes. We still need
duplicate page directories
to Sorry, can you speak up?
We still need duplicate
page directories
to mutate a page.
If we mutate, right?
If there's some mutation
operation happening, right?
But if I were to tell you,
for example, on a test, right,
that you're cloning
a child and you're
guaranteed that
the statistics of
their memory interaction is such
that they have 0% rights.
Then what would be the
answer to that question?
It is not necessary because
no mutation of state
actually takes place, right?
This is the ultimate kind
of use case for which
you can actually save
quite a bit by not
performing any copy of
the page directories or page
table pages at all, right?
So you could get away with
something like this
where process one and
process two are
actually pointing to
the same page directory, okay?
Sharing the same page
directory and sharing
the same set of
page table pages,
and as we've already
established previously,
sharing the same set
of physical frames.
This is actually possible.
And when we get to it, I'll
actually point I'll
actually point you
to a paper that was
recently published in one
of my favorite conferences,
USS quite recently,
it's not an old paper,
only four years ago, 2021
that actually does
something like this.
So people are still
thinking about
these overheads and people
are still trying to
come up with different
design points where
they make decisions on
what to copy on fork.
You know, you think that
this is a solved problem,
and somebody like solved it,
I don't know, 20, 30 years ago,
but that is not
actually the case.
And we'll discuss why
it's well motivated to
revisit things like this
when we get to that slide.
Okay? So, but here's
the question.
Does this break isolation?
You know, let's quickly
recap, you know,
the key kind of
necessary conditions that we
depend on an
operating system for,
which is isolation and
protection, right?
So does this break
isolation if we do that?
Yes, it does, right?
Has the potential of
breaking isolation
if we just do that
and do nothing else.
So it requires some
additional work
for us to still
preserve isolation
while performing this kind of
performance optimization that
we are trying to achieve.
Okay? So what would
happen if process two
wrote to this page?
Let's say the science page
here on the right hand side.
Yes. Oh, we have to
duplicate the page rectory.
No. Basically, if we
do nothing at all,
what would happen?
I would change the state
that original page or process
one doesn't know that.
Yeah, so does
everybody see that?
I mean, that's the point
of departure for us?
That's the motivation for
all the complexity we're
going to talk about.
The motivation is that writing
to that shared physical frame,
colored cyan on the
right hand side,
is going to leak state
across two processes.
It's going to break isolation.
It's going to look obvious
on this slide, right?
But, trust me, as we
go through the slides,
it's going to become
less and less obvious.
But I want to make
sure that everyone
is on the same page
that if you allow
the right from process
two to happen to the
sien page right here,
this is going to
leak state between
processes one and two,
which is undesirable.
And the reason why
it's undesirable
is because we are trying
to offer the illusion of
isolation to the processes.
We are trying to tell them that
they are running by themselves.
So this state leakage is
a huge problem and
must never happen,
and it's a security
violation. Yes.
Process only doing
read operations,
then this is okay,
right? That's did.
But what if Because the work
is invoked by the parent.
Right. Okay, so then that
means that both the parent
and the child will only
be doing read Well,
no, we should still allow
the parent to perform rites.
That's my point then.
It's like if the
child's expecting to
only do read operation,
and the parent writes and
mutates something
on one of the pages
that not also change
the child's ad out.
Exactly. So basically the so
the mutation of the state
happening either from the parent
or from the child will
break that isolation.
And we want to be
able to prevent that.
We want to be able
to interpose on this
happening and prevent that
from happening entirely, okay?
Alright.
So, we should not allow iTu
to write as a result, right?
That's sort of the answer
to that bubble right there.
You know, we should not kind
of allow process to proceed
with the write without
some additional
logic that needs to happen.
Okay. And so what that
additional logic is,
as someone pointed
out, you know,
repeatedly, what
the hell is this?
Okay. Is that we need to
perform a copy of
that SIN page, right?
We need to make a copy.
So now the SIN page
has been copied into the
orange page right here.
The physical frame from process
one physical address
space was copied to
a process two physical
address space
when we sort of trapped
process two right.
Okay?
And so the way to
figure this out,
whether or not you need to make
this copy is to ask yourself,
you know, what points to
that vertex in
this graph, right?
The way to think about it at
a high level is that you're
dealing with a graph.
It's directed acyclic
graph. There are no cycles.
There are edges that
have a direction,
and it's a graph, right?
Directed a cyclgraph.
And the second dimension,
directed at cyclgraph,
have you taken design of
algorithms and data structures
or something like that?
Oh yeah, you've
taken that. So cool.
You know how to
represent graphs.
Let's say, as an
adjacency matrix, right?
So think of this in your
mind, sort of mentally,
think of this as actually
the adjacency matrix
where you have all
the vertices in
this graph horizontally and
vertically, vertically
and horizontally.
And there's kind of a non
zero in the cell of that matrix.
I ane I to J is an edge
that exists in this graph.
Okay. And this is actually
a very powerful construct
because once you've established
that this is a graph
that changes over time,
now it's fairly easy
to figure out whether
or not a particular vertex has
multiple processes
pointing to it.
In other words, there
exist where there exists
more than one unique path
from processes to the
vertex in question, right?
And the vertex in question is
the one you're trying to
write to perform a write on.
And so if the answer
to that question is,
yes, you actually have
to split the state.
You actually have to make a
copy of that physical frame.
Okay, so you've made a copy.
Are we done? Did we
take care of it?
Did we preserve isolation?
Yes. Well, would we
have to tell one
of the processes that
the physical address
has changed on that page?
Yes, exactly. Think about what
changed when you
performed that copy,
right? So what changed?
What changed is that
the virtual address
that is being accessed by
process too now has
a different physical
frame associated
with that because we've just
allocated and copied into it.
So the VA to PA
mapping has changed.
Now, if the mapping has changed
and we know what
carries that mapping.
That mapping is being carried by
the combination of page
directory and page
table pages, right?
In particular, in
this particular case,
you need to back propagate
this change through
this structure.
So the PT at
the last level page table page
has to change because you need
to update its
physical frame number
because the physical frame
number has changed. Right?
Oh, what does that mean?
That means that
you are trying to
mutate this, I guess, you know,
imagine that this
orange page table,
page table page
doesn't exist yet.
You're trying to mutate
this page table, right?
And if you're trying
to mutate that,
you need to ask yourself, how
many have access to
this page table?
Can you trace it back to
more than one process?
Right? And if the answer is yes,
then you need to
make a copy of this.
Okay, so what have
you accomplished?
You have accomplished
now creating
a new page table page,
which is a separate.
It has a separate, completely
distinct physical frame number.
At NT, that needs to back
propagate to the page directory.
So now you're updating
a PDE entry inside
page directory in
order to reflect that.
That means you're
mutating page directory.
And if you're mutating
page directory,
of course, you have to make a
copy of the page directory.
Okay, and that's
how this mutation
actually propagates, right?
So as I mentioned, there exists
a page table entry inside
this page table that actually
needs to be updated.
That means you're
trying to perform
a write into a last
level page table page.
And if you're
writing and there's
more than one process
that has access to
that page table page by
traversing the graph,
right, that means that you need
to copy the page and
create a new frame for it.
So we've done that, and
now we're able to perform
an update to a page
table entry here. Okay?
And because we've done that,
we need to back propagate that.
Oh, sorry, wrong direction to
a page directory entry
and update the page
directory entry,
which if you recall
from last week
holds the PFN for the next
level page table page.
What does that mean?
That means we're
performing a write in
the page directory.
That means that we
need to make a copy.
So that's how this
simple change, right,
simple write to one of
the physical frames that
shared between two processes
is going to backprop
through this whole graph
and cause actually
all this copy on writing for
the page table pages and the
page directory as a result.
And now, so let's revisit
this question, right?
What is the probability of us
to actually mutating PDEs,
page directory entries
for a process in general?
And I actually really like
this question because that
would force you to think.
But let me give you a hint.
Think about this. What is
the probability of a
process calling a function?
Is it high or is it low?
The probability of a process
calling a function is very high.
Now, when you call a
function, what happens?
Yes.
Yeah, something is
happening on the stack.
Are you writing to the stack?
Yeah, you're writing
to the stack.
Oh, my God, you're
writing to the stack.
And if that page
wasn't previously
allocated to the stack
or if it was cout,
so it was kind of just copied
from the parent, right?
And you're performing a write,
you know that it's
going to trigger
a change in one of
the page tables,
and you know that's going to
backprop into page directory.
So that means that
at the very least,
if you're calling just
a single function,
right, in your process,
you know that this is going to
backprop into a mutation
of page directory.
That's guaranteed. And so
the probability of page
directory mutation
is extremely high. Okay?
However, it's a
different question.
If you think about it
from the perspective of
what is the probability of
mutating the page tables,
that becomes a little bit dicey.
That really becomes a
property of the workload.
And that's what makes
it interesting.
So then that means that
in some you will probably
always want to create a
copy of the page directory.
Why? The overhead is pretty low.
You're just paying the cost
of a single page, right?
So you're not really saving
much by trying to
save on that copy,
and the probability
that you need to do it
anyway in a lazy fashion
is extremely high.
So just go ahead
and get it done.
Okay? However, with
the page table pages,
as was actually demonstrated
in this US's 2021 paper,
it's a completely
different story,
especially if for a specific set
of workloads that are
mostly read only,
right, maybe only
their stack changes,
but their code and data is
immutable, and, you know,
they are mapping a
lot of data into
their memory that
they're performing
read only operations on.
So most of the page tables are
actually going to stay
immutable, right,
while only a few page
table pages such as
the ones associated
with the stack are
going to be the ones
that are mutated, right?
So it's only a small handful
of those page table pages.
Maybe then it actually is
advantageous to save on that
copy. Do you guys see that?
So that sort of becomes a
property of the workload.
Okay. So how do we know
which parts to copy in
this particular case?
Can somebody answer
this question?
So given a particular vertex,
let's say you've
designed an algorithm
that handles this
and you're trying
to figure out if
you need or don't
need to make a copy of a
particular vertex in this graph,
how do you make that decision?
Yes.
So one of the
necessary conditions
is that you want to mutate it,
right? Is it sufficient?
Yes.
Yeah, there exists
more than one pathway
to that vertex, right?
So basically, you want
to copy something.
You want to copy a
vertex in this graph,
this graph of T is a
function of time, right?
If both of those hold true,
if you want to make
a change to it,
you want to mutate it, right,
as you pointed out,
and a logical,
if there exists more than
one pathway to that vertex,
that means that it's shared.
So you need to find a way
to actually keep track of
the sharing information for
every single vertex
in this graph. Yes.
Can you just keep track of
how many toes are
pointing to that vertex?
You absolutely can.
That is exactly right.
And that's called ref counting.
All right. And that's
what you're going to be
exploring in your lab two. Okay?
All right. So let's move on.
Lab two is not going to
require you to
implement copyright
for page tables and
page directory.
So all of this that I've
described with page table
and page directory is
something for you to keep in
mind because people do implement
such solutions in real systems
and they do publish
papers about this.
So it's very real. It's not
even an academic
thought exercise.
Okay? So people do that.
And I wanted to make sure that I
once again kind
of try to instill
in you that no single
design point is absolute.
It is a function of the
statistical properties
of the workload that
you're dealing with,
as well as a function of
the system that you
implement this on.
Yeah. In what sense?
But what about the
file system here?
It's used that some people
actually implement copy
and write pharkts?
Right, right. A difference
in file systems or Where
would you see that?
So let's take this
question off line.
But basically, what
I was saying is
that depending on what
your read and write accesses
are for the application,
and the workload if you
know those characteristics,
it can either motivate
or dissuade you from
performing a copy,
either lazy or eager copy
on the page directories
and page tables.
In most cases, you want
to copy page directory.
In some cases, you do not
want to copy page tables.
But I wanted to assure
you that in lab two,
you don't have to worry
about page director
and page table copy and
write implementation because
that is quite involved.
Okay? So the only thing that
you need to implement copy and
write for is for the last
level physical frames.
Okay. So do we
need to copy every map
physical page on fork,
right? The answer is no.
Do we need to make a page
table for each process, right?
The answer is no.
What do we need to
track in order to ensure
copy and write operations?
Working, you know, we sort
of discuss that as well.
We need to track, you know,
which vertices are
actually having
access to that particular vertex
that you're trying to mutate.
In other words, the
sharing information.
And that is going to be
the crux of lab two.
Now, what mechanisms do we
have to enable copy and write?
And this gets us back to
these permission bits that we
already talked about. Right?
It's part of our hammer.
And in particular,
oh, I don't have.
In particular, we care about
a couple of bits here.
The present bit, that's
the bit that says whether
or not we're pointing
into the void from a
page directory entry
or from the page table page,
or that next level
physical frame was
allocated and we can actually
proceed with our page
table walk, right?
And this write bit
is going to be
super important and
the reason for this is
because it gives us a physical
permission to perform a write to
the next level page table
page or physical frame.
Okay? So there's
a right bit here,
which means that can we perform
a write operation on
the page table page?
There's a right bit
here, and it refers to
whether or not we have
a physical permission
to write to the physical frame.
Okay? And we're going to use
this mechanism to
enable copy and write.
This actually gets
us to the discussion
of the two different kinds
of permissions, right?
There are two
separate permissions
that you need to keep in
mind the logical permission
and the physical permission.
And it's really important
because there can be a lot
of confusion about this.
Why? Well, because
logical permissions
kind of capture whether or not
it is legal to access a
particular memory address, right?
Is it legal for me to
access this memory?
But physical permission actually
deals with the question
of should the CPU
give me a trap for
accessing this page or am I
physically able to access
this particular memory?
And copy on write implementation
actually depends on
the combination of
capturing both the
logical and the physical
permissions, right?
So for instance, we just saw
a case where the data
is physically shared,
but logically, it's not shared.
So logically, process
one and process two,
they have write access to
a particular VFN in
their separate virtual
address spaces, right?
And they can both
proceed with issuing
those store or write operations
on that virtual address.
So they're logically
allowed to do that.
But we physically disallow them
to do that by setting
the right bit to zero.
Why? Because we want to
trap and interpose on
that control flow
operation so that
we perform the deja
vu trick, right?
So that we change something
under the hood in order to
ensure isolation
between those processes
and prevent the
leakage of state.
All right. Did that make sense?
So for example, if
physical mapping
is going to say that
our write bit is zero,
that means that we're
physically going to
be incapable to perform write,
okay, right after copy on write.
So this is going to
be much more clear
if we actually go through
a copy on write example.
Um, and how the permission bits,
our mechanismic permission bits
are going to be updated as we
step through the process of
performing a fork and
copy on write, okay?
But we are at 2:50 right now.
So I'm going to spend
our last lecture on
Thursday kind of
carefully walking through
this example and
making sure that
everybody understands
how we enact
logical and physical
permittans with
our permission bits in the
context of this example.
Thank you, and I'll
see you on serve base.