So
Okay.
Good afternoon, everybody.
We have such a limited amount of
time with you guys that
every minute counts.
Is there some sort of a
career fair happening
or there seems to be like,
quite a few seats
empty in the back.
Does anybody know what the
reason for that might be?
Surely it's not me, right?
Especially for this
lecture because this
is the last lecture on
virtual memory management,
out of the four lectures
over the past two weeks.
And this is going to be
hopefully a slam dunk.
We're going to be
kind of covering
what we finished off with.
During the last lecture, we're
going to be finishing up
our discussion of virtual memory
management tips
and tricks, okay?
So let's go ahead
and get started.
I'm not even going to bore
you guys with administrativa.
We'll jump right in, okay.
Last time we discussed
copy on right fork, right?
As a recap, we discussed
whether or not it even
makes sense for us
to actually perform the copy of
the entire virtual address
space on fork, right?
And you have to remember
what that means.
Every single word here has a
precise definition, right?
The virtual memory to physical
memory address is
sort of propped up by
the whole paging
mechanism that we
already discussed
extensively, right,
which consists of a set
of page table pages,
one of which is a
page directory,
and then the last level
of page table pages,
mapping all of the
physical frames
that were allocated
to the process,
right, to be used.
Um, then so the question that I
raised during the
previous lecture
is whether or not
it makes sense to
actually make a copy
of that, right?
And we've sort of established
that, no, I don't think so.
You know, it's quite a
lot of stuff to copy,
especially for
stateful applications.
In some cases, it makes sense.
In some cases, it might not.
We discussed the
mechanisms that will
allow us to actually get
rid of that copy
altogether, right?
And so I also very briefly
kind of showed you
this illustration of
what that means from
the application
perspective because
previous slide was
sort of mechanismic.
This slide this slide is
actually much more from the
application perspective.
So on the left hand side,
on the left hand side,
you have your virtual address
space and two processes,
a parent and the
child at the bottom.
On the right hand side, you
have a physical
address space, right?
So I draw memory like this.
And then in the
parent address space
in the parent virtual
address space,
you have, let's
say, three frames,
four kilobyte size each.
Right. And these
three frames mapped
to some physical frames
underpinning those
virtual frames, okay?
And when we perform
a copy, sorry,
when we perform a
fork, you know,
the default of what's
happening in Expix right now
is actually a full copy of
all of the physical frames,
the blue frame at the bottom,
the green frame in the middle,
and the red frame at the top.
Of the virtual address space.
The physical frames underpinning
those are going to
be copied, right?
And the reason for
this, as we discussed,
is also quite important.
The reason for this is
that's the simplest way of
enabling something
that we really want
the operating system to
provide, which is what?
Isolation. Thank you.
Right. But is it
necessary, right?
We want this to be
much more performant.
And we discussed that.
No, it turns out, oh,
well, one more thing.
What is the complexity
of this kind of fork?
If I were to ask you, basically,
with vanilla X V six with
no modification whatsoever,
what is the complexity of fork
as a function of the
number of physical frames?
You guys have taken Okay,
you have, OVN, right?
So the complexity of this is ON.
So what that means is that if
you actually time the fork,
if you actually run
the experiments,
right, you'll get
different numbers
where the latency of the fork,
the micro benchmark that
actually tries to
figure out, you know,
how long the fork takes is
going to be a function of
how many pages you run,
how many pages you're
dealing with, right?
And hopefully if we get time,
we'll circle back to
this observation at the
very end of this lecture,
and this is something that
was sort of directly fed into
the motivation of the Euross
2021 paper that I
mentioned previously.
Okay? Okay, but we
don't want to do that.
It's a lot of copying, right?
Let's try to save on copying.
Let's try to dedupe,
especially since in many cases,
we actually don't need all
of this state to carry
forward to carry over,
rather, from the
parent address space
to the child address
space, right?
So what if we did
something like this?
So a parent forks
a child, right?
That's a fork. And
a child instead
of performing a copy of all of
the physical frames
allocated to the parent
to the child to
preserve isolation,
right, we actually just
pointing all the VONs from
the child address space to
the same PONs from
the physical address
space of the parent.
What is the complexity of that?
Yes.
Of one. Okay? So I want
to make that clear
because we're not
just shaving off
a few milliseconds
here and there.
This is actually the complexity
itself has improved, right?
Even if you actually introduce
some additional overhead of sort
of keeping track
of some metadata,
you know, the reference
counts and whatnot,
the logical and physical
permissions and whatnot, right?
You've actually improved
the complexity to off one,
and this is
sort of the best possible
complexity you can have.
Can the complexity be
better than off one?
But you're going to pay
the cost for that
later on, right?
And that cost is
basically what we were
referring to as the lazy
allocation of physical frames.
You have to pay the cost
later on if the child
actually starts writing to
its virtual address
space, right?
And this is what you're going
to have to do in lab two.
You already know
that. It's a recap.
So now the child tries to write.
And I also gave you a very
simple example of the
very obvious that you
would most often expect
the child to perform.
And it's currently
signified with
this arrow right there on the
slide. What is that right?
Ta ta, ta, ta, ta, ta. Yes.
A what? No, no,
the fork has already happened.
Yeah, the fork has
already happened and we
did due the physical
frames. Yes.
What? Sorry? No, yes.
Stack, right? When there's
a specific reason why
each of those colored
rectangles are there.
The blue rectangle is
actually very low in
the address space,
and that's typically where
your code and data are
for your ELF binary.
Okay? That's where you map
your elf binaries, usually.
The red one is closer to
the middle right where your most
significant bit flips 0-1,
which, of course, means
that the very top
of that address space is
kernel address space, right?
And then right
before it flips 0-1,
or somewhere very high in
the in the virtual
address space,
you have a red frame,
and the red frame is usually
where your stack is, right?
And somewhere in the middle
is where your heap space is.
So the green one usually
corresponds to the heap. Okay?
So this write
actually means that
the child is actually trying
to write to the stack.
Now, should we allow for
this to happen, right?
We've deduped we
improve the complexity.
Should we allow for
this write to happen?
Does the child have a logical
permission to write to
its own stack?
Absolutely, right?
How can you run your
programs otherwise?
But should the child
have a physical
permission to write to
its own stack at this
point in time, no.
And what do we use?
Which mechanism do
we use in order to prevent
this from happening?
Yeah, copy on write.
That's sort of a catch all.
And there's a specific
permission bit
that we use for that.
Yes.
Page table entry.
Yeah, the PTE that's
actually mapping that
stack frame, right?
The VFN corresponding
to a stack frame,
the page table entry is going
to have its right
bit set to zero.
And we're going to go
through an example step
by step so that you can
actually appreciate how you
need to set those
permission bits in order to
actually disentangle
the logical permissions
from the physical
permissions and therefore
enable the entirety of the
copy on write mechanism.
Alright, so the right
wants to right there.
We've established that
we don't want to do
that because it's
going to leak state.
It's a security violation.
It's going to get rid of
the isolation that we really
want the operating
system to provide.
Not going to happen.
What we do instead
is we perform a copy of
the physical frame. Okay?
And watch this. If you haven't
seen, watch this, right?
Nice. We're moving VFN.
We're moving a VFN arrow
to point to a new
physical frame.
And we're going to see
an example of that.
Now the write can proceed.
Now, the logical and
the physical permissions for
the child to write
are going to align.
And we've now changed the state.
We've now actually
mutated the state of
that physical frame after it
was copied and
after we've updated
the VTP mapping for
the child process.
Okay. So this is
a good foray and sort of
review of the logical and
physical permissions, right?
We separate permissions into
two types, logical and physical.
Logical is basically, is
it legal for a process
to address to access
or write to the memory that
it's currently writing?
And physical is
basically whether
or not this is physically going
to be allowed to proceed,
or if we actually need
to have mechanisms
to stop that from
happening so that gives us
an opportunity to actually
do the dejavu trick, right?
To actually suspend reality
for the process attempting
this operation and make
some changes that
actually make it okay.
Which is a technical term.
Okay, so now we've got to
the point where we
believe it's unnecessary
to copy the actual physical
frames of memory, right?
We want to keep them the
same across the fork,
from a parent to
a child process.
So you have your
physical frames on
the right hand side
in this diagram.
And again, this is a
recap, so I'm going fast.
It's a recap from the
previous lecture.
And now you have
a page directory,
which is basically mapping
all of the page tables,
and the process
one is pointing to
its page directory through
the contents of this
here three register.
Okay, so process two
comes along, right?
It's a fork of process one.
And instead of just telling
you what should happen,
you know, the way
you should think
about this is as follows.
You need to have some
sort of mechanism that
maps V virtual address to
physical address space, right?
So what do you get on
input from process two?
You have just forked.
The moment you have just forked,
everything in the
virtual address space
of the child is going to
be the same or different from
the virtual address
space of the parent.
Same. Is the stack at the
same location, right?
You depend on that, in fact,
because if you actually performs
a bunch of nested
codes for a function,
you actually expect the child to
actually stay in that
activation frame
when the child forks, right?
You depend on that. The heap
allocated data
structures, right?
Are they in the same location
on the heap after the fork?
You're still able to interact
with them after the fork.
They're still there, right?
The pointer that was saved
on stack that actually saved
the memory address of
your mallet data structure on
the heap remains
exactly the same.
All of the virtual addresses
have remained the
same after the fork.
So the input to this black box
that we're trying to
figure out is the same.
Is the output the same?
We've decided we're going
to make it the same, right?
Because we want to dedupe
the physical frames.
Okay, so input is the same.
The output is the same.
What does that tell you
about the black box?
The black box the purpose of
the black box is to carry
the mapping of the
input to the output.
And if the input is the same
and the output is the same,
like copying a C plus
plus hash map, right?
So if the hash map keys
and the values are
exactly the same,
is that going to be
the same hash map?
Yeah, the mapping is going to
be exactly the same, right?
So you will end up with
the same contents
that you're going to
put in the black box regardless
of how it's actually
implemented,
you know, two
level, three level,
five level, whatever, right?
The important thing here
is that it's going to
have exactly the same contents
as the pairing, right?
And this is what I
want to, you know,
get through to you on
this slide right here.
So the contents of
the black box at
the top actually equal
to the contents of the
black box at the bottom.
And that's why it
raised the question
of whether or not we could
dedupe them as well.
Right?
So that's what we
discussed last time.
Any questions about this so far?
Six, don't we don't
like process to
point to the same page
dactor same page tables?
We do not, no, no.
XP six, you will
only have to concern
yourself with deduping
the physical frames.
Yeah. Okay.
And so, you know, here we
are just going through
this process to
demonstrate that we
can make additional
optimizations,
such as deduping the page tables
and the page directory by
making process 2.2 exactly
the same set of mappings,
the VTP mappings, right?
Um Okay,
so this is just another
slide demonstrating that,
but we can't just get away
with doing this because we
need to do something
when the child process
actually attempts
to write, right?
When the child process
attempts to write,
we need to have the mechanism
to trap that right.
And once we've
trapped that right,
we have the color
information, right?
We have the color context,
in this case, process too,
and we know where the where
which physical frame the
write is attempted on.
Now we need to figure out
what to do with
this information.
And we discussed last time that
the number one thing you should
be asking yourself, right,
whether or not to
permit this right
is whether or not this page
or this physical frame
is or is it accessible by
more than one process?
If it is accessible by
more than one process,
should we allow the
right to happen?
No. So it must be
accessible by at most,
how many processes?
One, how do we figure that out?
Sure. Ref count is a way of
implementing sort
of the conceptual
approach to this, right?
And here on this slide,
how do we figure that out?
We see how many kind of
references there are
or how many vertices in
this particular graph
directed basically graph,
point to the vertex that we're
trying to mutate, right?
So let's start back propping.
How many page table pages
have a reference to
this physical frame?
Just one, right? Hmm.
We're still good so far.
Haven't encountered a reason
to copy the frame, right?
Okay, let's keep going.
How many page directories
are referencing the page table?
One, okay? Still haven't
encountered the reason for us
to make a copy of the
physical frame. Dang it.
Okay. Well, how many
process vertices
are actually referenced
in the page directory?
Two, now we've encountered the
reason to actually go back
and perform a copy
on the physical frame that
we're trying to mutate, okay?
In other words, as I mentioned
during the previous class,
and I don't know how many of you
actually picked up
on that, right?
There is a way to actually
represent this as a
directed basically graph.
One of the simplest kind of
data structures to do this is
the adjacency matrix where you
have vertices horizontally
and vertically,
and the element is non zero.
If and all, there exists
an edge from element
I to element J.
Okay? And so it is actually
possible to use
this data structure
at least as a mental model.
I'm not saying you should
do that in your lab, right?
I'm not saying that. But what
I'm saying is that you
should keep that as
a mental model because if you
transpose that adjacency.
Okay, this is a bit of an
aside. 1 minute, I promise.
If you transpose this adjacency
matrix, what do you get?
It's an interview
question. Very common.
Yes. Reverse.
Yeah, it's the reverse graph.
You reverse all the edges
in this adjacency graph,
once you've reversed that
and you still have a hold,
a handle on your physical
frame, you're mutating, right?
That gives you the ability
to perform path finding to
figure out how many unique paths
through the graph you
are able to get, right?
And if it's more than one, then
that means that you need
to mutate the frame.
You need to copy the
frame and then mutate.
Make sense? Yes.
Process.
Speech process needs
to tell page table.
Wouldn't there only be one?
Even though both processes
referenced the same
page directory,
wouldn't it only be
possible to actually get to
that page only from the process
that initially refused?
Because to get to that page,
you would have had to go to
process the page table first.
Okay, so there are answer
there are two
answers in my mind.
One of them is sort of more
directly related to your lab,
and one of them is more directly
related to the lecture.
So, so first of all,
even if you assume that
the processes are going to
be addressing their own
separate page directory, right,
we've already discussed
that you're going
to maintain the same mapping
to the physical frames.
And so there will
be page tables,
even if a set of page tables
is separate from the processes,
you can still have
physical frames pointed
to by more than one
page table page.
That's why you need to
do this calculus, right?
Okay. Okay, so this
is what it's going to
look like after you
actually have back
propagated all the mutations
that you need to perform, right?
So you need to perform
a copy on write for
the sim physical
frame that you have
attempted to write
that pay process
two has attempted to write to,
and you got the orange physical
frame, right, right here.
Is the orange physical
frame that you received.
Okay. And now, for every
single step kind of think,
what precisely happened
in your universe?
What happened in your universe?
You've attempted to mutate
a particular address
in the VFN, right?
And the PFN associated
with that has changed.
So that means that the
mapping has changed, right?
The VFN to PFN
mapping has changed.
We need to propagate
that mapping back
to the last level page
table page because that's
where that mapping is
captured, right? Makes sense?
That's where that
mapping is captured.
So in other words, the last
level page table page carries
a PT which encodes two things.
One of them is the
physical frame number of
the physical frame
you're accessing and
the other one is a set of
permission bits, right?
And that PTE is going to change,
which implies that there
must be a right to
the page table page in
order to update that PTE.
So now we're at a
different point in now
a graph that we've captured,
and we are attempting to
mutate a different
vertex in that graph.
And same logic applies.
Can I mutate it? Yes or
no? How can we tell?
Exactly the same logic, yes.
You can check the write
bit on the page table?
No, no, no, no, no, no,
no, exactly the same
algorithm applies.
You need to figure out
how many references
there are to this page table
that you're trying
to access, right?
Is it possible for
more than one process
to access this page table?
If there is,
attempting a write in
a shared vertex in this graph
is going to leak state, okay?
And we must never prevent
that from happening.
So we're in the
kernel right now.
We're in the kernel right
now and we're trying to
sort of correct the
situation of leaking
state because of all the
performance optimizations
that we are trying to implement.
Okay? So the rules are
a little bit different.
You need to think
more carefully.
You cannot just rely on
those right bits
because you are God.
You are the one that's actually
controlling those bits.
You are omniscient and
omnipotent observer
that's interposing on the
reality of those processes.
Okay, so do not
rely on those bits.
You're the one setting them.
So we've decided that the
page table itself needs to
be copied in order
for us to perform a
mutation on the PTE, right?
And once we've copied that,
we know that there's a
page directory entry
that used to reference
that page table,
and that mapping has changed,
which means that
we need to update
the PDE in order to
reflect that mapping.
Oh. So what does that tell
us about the page directory?
Can we perform the update
on a PDE inside the
page directory?
Yes. Until we make a copy?
No, not until we make a
copy because it's shared.
It's more than one process
accessing that
vertex in the graph.
So essentially, what
I have done is I have
given you a conceptual
algorithm that you can
sort of recursively
invoke regardless of
where in the graph
the mutation is trying
to be performed.
Okay. And you can see that
conceptual this mindset,
this conceptual approach can
actually give you a very,
very powerful approach
to keep track of which
physical frames of
memory actually
need are allowed to be
mutated and which
need to be copied,
regardless of what's
happening in terms
of parent, children,
grandchildren,
grand grand grandchildren,
and allowing
the rights across this
entire family hierarchy.
Okay? Because that graph
is all you have to
worry about is,
how do you update this graph as
a function of time
and then identify
which vertex of that graph you
are performing a write on
and figure out whether
or not the write should proceed
or figure out whether or not you
need to perform a copy and back
propagate the
results of the copy,
the implications of that
copy, I should say.
Okay.
I'm having entirely too
much fun with this.
But this is so powerful,
because, you know,
this is a simple example of
just a parent and the
child process, right?
But then you can ask, what
if the parent forked
another child?
Are you going to have to worry
about that in your lab, too?
What if the child forked
another child, right?
What if the child
forked another child?
So a grandchild, but
the child exited,
then what happens, right?
So all of these
cornea cases will
have to be covered
by your lab, too.
And this sort of gives you
a conceptual framework to reason
about what changes to
the graph so that you
maintain correctness.
Okay.
So, let's recap on
this. Let's see.
So basically, what
happens now if
parent wants to update
or mutate the sien page,
the original science page,
should this be
allowed to proceed?
That's the same exact
kind of question.
Think about the vertex,
think about the graph, think
about the sharing information.
So update or any kind of
mutation operation
on a SIN page,
this one right here, right?
Should we allow for
this to proceed?
How many processes
are pointing to that?
One, right? And
it's right there.
So the process one is still able
to reference the original page
that process two
attempted to write to,
and there exists exactly one
path through this graph.
And so that process
one write should be
allowed to proceed.
And that should trigger
something in your mind, okay?
I'm not going to say what
it is, but there are
implications associated
with that, right?
So do we need to copy every
mapped physical page on fork?
No. Do we even
need to make a page
table for each process?
No. What do we need to
track to ensure copy and
write operations correctness,
sharing information?
Yes. So is this sharing
information is it
stored processes like kernel
memory, that makes sense?
Or is it shared,
I'm just confused,
this information where do
you store that adjacent?
Yeah, so that's part of
what you have to figure out
in the context of Lab two,
where that information
is going to be stored.
Okay. So how do we do this
protection mechanisms.
The write bits that actually
give us the hammers
to enable, right?
And we already discussed
what they are.
We talked about what
the present bit means,
and the write bits
are they exist
both in the page directory entry
and the page table entry.
They basically mean
whether or not the write
to the next level is
allowed to proceed, right?
In both cases, the semantic
meaning is exactly the same.
So for the page directory
entry, we bit set to one,
that means that the
PTE page table entry
at the next level
that means that
you should be
allowed to write to
the page table page
at the next level
that this PG is pointing to.
You only have to
concern yourself with
PTE, page table entries.
If the right bit is set to one,
that means that you're
allowed to mutate
the physical frame of memory
that's being accessed, okay?
Alright, so let's walk
through a copy on
write example and
actually figure out exactly
how we use these
mechanismic bits.
I'm referring to
them as mechanismic
because they enable
something, right?
And how these permission bits
are going to be updated.
We start with process one.
It has a PD one page directory,
which has two page tables,
right, roughly speaking,
and it has three
physical frames of
memory allocated in the
physical address space.
So each page directory, sorry,
each page table is an
array, okay? It's a table.
Of a bunch of PTEsPage
table elements, right?
W that carry the information
about the physical frame of
the physical frame number
and the permission bits.
So let's examine what
our permission bits in each
case have to be, okay?
So let's specifically talk
about what the page table
one contents are and
what the page table
two contents are.
So we have three
physical frames,
how many PTs we need
to worry about.
The physical frames, on
the right hand side that we need
to provide the mapping for.
How many PTs we need to
worry about? Three, right?
Because there's one PT
per physical frame
that we're mapping.
Okay? So what should the bits?
Actually, the starting condition
here is that we're just
going to enable everything.
So I'm just going to
give you that, right?
This is the starting condition.
We're able to write to P one.
We're able to write to P two,
and we're able to
write to P three.
Okay, we fork the process too.
So what should happen to the PTs
in page table one and PT
is in page table two.
What should happen?
Yes.
Yes. Exactly. So specifically,
the question reduces down to
what should happen to
those permission bits,
those mechanismic
permission bits
that are at our
disposal in the kernel.
And as you correctly
pointed out,
we need to turn them off, right?
We need to set the
right bits to zero.
And the reason for this is
because for every single
one of the leaf
vertices in this dag,
okay, every single one of
your physical frames,
they are shared.
They are shared and accessible
by more than one process.
So we should not allow
the write to proceed.
The way we enable that is
by setting the
right bit to zero.
That should be pretty
straightforward, right?
Okay, so now process two
wants to perform a write.
Specifically, it wants to
perform a write to P one.
So first of all,
we've already established,
I'm not going to
go over it again.
We've already established that
we need to trap that, right?
And now we are in
the handler code.
We're inside the handler code.
So what needs to happen,
so the first thing that
needs to happen as we've
already discussed is we need to
make a copy to P
one to P one prime.
So that's this copy right here.
P one to P one prime
has been copied.
Page table one to page table
one prime has been copied,
page directory one to page
directory prime has been copied.
So we've already gone over
that and the reasons for this.
And the process to
is now pointing to
its own separate page
directory table, okay?
Okay, so that's what we
are handling right here.
And the question is, you
have to answer the
following question.
What the page table entries
look like for PT one prime?
And what page table entries
look like for PG two.
So let's start
with a simple one.
PG two. There's a
page table element
that's handling physical
frame three, P three.
What should be the
permissions be right here?
Yes.
Okay.
What's that?
Should be on and
write should be off.
And how can we tell that
write should be off?
If you reverse the
pads for P three,
you'll see that PT
two refering to
PD one and PD one
process process.
Exactly. So if you
trace it back, right,
you will eventually
find that PD one and
PD one prime actually
point to P three, right?
And so that means
that permission bid,
the right permission bit
should still be zero
because we should still continue
to disallow rights to P three.
We should still trap any
possible writes to P three
in the future, right?
Okay. Now, what about the PTs
that are mapping P
two and P one prime?
So let's maybe
start with a P two.
That's the easy case, right?
What should the right
bit be for P two?
In other words, right here,
is it a zero or a one?
It's a zero. Why is that?
Two. For the same reason
why the right bit for P
three is zero, right?
It is possible for
you to actually
access this from more
than one process, right?
You can find paths back
to P one and process one,
Proc one and process two.
Oh, here we go. Bunch of
stuff starts happening.
Okay. And finally, what
should be the P one prime?
Basically, what permission
bits should be set for
the PTE mapping our
P one prime frame?
One. And what's the
reason for that?
There's only one path
through the graph that
actually leads us to
P one prime, okay?
And that's how you can tell.
Does that example make sense?
There are questions, yes.
Let's say process two
allocates a new page.
We have to update
the page dt and
the page table process
two Yeah, exactly.
Yeah. Basically, if
you're if you're not
referencing the state that you
inherited from the parent,
you're just doing
an S break, right,
and allocating new
physical frames of memory,
you still have to update the
last level page table pages
in order to insert the PTs that
map that new physical frames,
those new physical frames.
So even though, let's say
process reallocates a
new page called P four,
which is outside the
scope of process one.
Okay. Yeah. So P four, right?
Then why do we have
to update the page wrapping
page table in that case?
Like Well, the
reason for this is
because there's a
new v2p mapping
that you need to keep
track of, right?
That didn't previously exist.
So now there's an additional
VT P mapping that
you're trying to
capture and save somehow
using this mechanism, right?
And if it's a brand
new physical frame
allocated to a brand
new VFN, right,
you need to reflect that in
the PTE and because
you're updating the PTE,
you need to if the PTE is
actually inserted into
a page table page that
previously existed,
nothing should happen in
page directory, right?
If, however, the PTE needs to be
inserted into a page table
page that did not exist,
you need to allocate
that and update
the page directory
entry to point to
a newly allocated
page table page.
Then in that case,
you need to copy.
Yes. Yeah. Yeah,
good question. Yes.
In what case? Yeah.
Yeah, because that's purely
and entirely kind of in
the V to P mapping space
of a separate process,
that does not concern any
other process, right?
Yes. I the original P one. Yes.
Yeah, so that's a really
good question, right?
I hinted that something needs to
happen to the P
one, and actually,
let me sort of answer
that question in the context
of the next few slides.
So then I'll take
more questions closer towards
the end of the class.
Okay? So here's a question
that's going to ultimately
give the answer to you.
How many TOB page invalidates
do we need to make
on a right to P one?
Is it 01 or a quintessential 42.
So in other words,
process two is a
child of process one.
Process two has attempted
to write P one,
right? It's right here.
I know it's hard to track,
but we attempted
to write to P one.
Then we made a copy of P
one to P one prime, right?
So something happened
there, okay?
And the question asks,
how many TOB patient validates
do we need to perform
as a result of this?
So first of all, does anybody
think that it's zero?
No. Does anybody think it's 42?
No. So it must be 1-2,
right? How do we know that?
Well, let's look at this
figure again, okay?
So we know that we've
changed the permission and
the physical address for the
P one prime frame, right?
So that right there means that
there exists a VTP
mapping that has changed.
And do you remember what
TLB is responsible for?
COB is responsible
for caching VM to
PT mappings is responsible for
caching virtual frame
numbers to PT mappings.
PTE consists, as I
mentioned, from two things.
One of them is What
are the two high
level things that
a patient hold information for?
The address and flags.
The address and
the flags, right?
Has the address changed?
The physical frame
number, has it changed?
Yeah, it has changed, right?
So the VFN that
process to the child
process has attempted to
write on now has
a different PFN that
it's writing into, okay?
So that right there should
trigger an invalidate.
Is that the only
invalidate Is that
the only thing that has
changed that I need
to ask yourself?
Is that the only thing that
has changed in the system,
or is that the only thing that
should change in the system?
And back to your
question, what if process
one now wants to write to P one?
In this figure right here,
do the mental
gymnastics to figure
out how many processes
are pointing to P one.
How many?
One, right? But what
was its permission bit?
Zero. And so what
happens if process
one writes to P one with
a zero permission bit?
Yeah, it's going to give
you a page fall, right?
Do we want that page
fault to happen?
No, there's no reason for
that page fault
to happen, right?
So that means that we
probably should have updated
the permissions on the
physical frame P one.
Uh huh. So now that means that
it's not just one thing that
has changed in our universe.
It's two things. One of them
is associated with the new frame
P one prime that
we've just allocated.
That one is the easy one.
So we know and invalidate
happened there.
And the other one is
that we need to change
the permission bits on
physical frame one so that we
don't unnecessarily
trap the parent
on the frame that is
no longer shared.
Two things have changed.
More specifically,
things have changed to
two different via fans.
Now, how many of you think
that this is going to
require two invalidates because
of this, two TLB invalidates.
Okay, how many of
you think that it's
going to require one invalidate?
Okay, why do you think
that it's going to be one?
You, for example.
P one prime was
never in until he got
created brand new.
So you wouldn't necessarily be
invalidating as much as
adding a new entry to.
So when you're
doing invalidating
the original P one red obscure.
Right. And so let me just
paraphrase that a little bit
for everybody's benefit, right?
So what happens is that
who is the color that
initiated a right to P one
that became a right to P one
prime in the first place?
The color is process two.
Okay? So the context
that's currently loaded in
the kernel is the
process to context.
Okay. So anything that
pertains to the process
to context, you know,
is in all the mappings
that are in the TLB that
pertain to the
process to context.
If we attempt to make changes to
VA to PTE mappings for
any other process,
this is not in the TOB
that we have right now.
And as a matter of fact, we need
to just update the
data structure,
and next time we switch
contacts back to process one,
the contact switch itself
is going to take
care of that flush
because we will be writing
the page directory of
process one into CR three,
which triggers a TLB flush.
Okay? So that means once
again that the answer is one.
We only need to perform
a TLB and validate
for the single update
that we're making for
the P one frame
because that's what's in the
context of the kernel right now.
So that's a bit of
a trick question,
right? But it's fun
to think about.
Does that answer your question?
And that answers his question.
Okay? The answer
is one. All right.
So we got through
this example and
we still have some
time. That's awesome.
So basically, what do we track?
Think about per physical page
versus per virtual page data.
How do I know when I
need to copy a page?
We have already discussed that.
I sort of gave you my mental
model about how to
think about it.
How do I know when P one
prime has been freed?
You know? What about P two?
So you have to think about
corner cases because it's not
just going to be a simple
parent and child relationship.
It could be grandchildren,
grand grandgrandchildren.
It could be somebody dying
in the process, right?
It could be someone who is
being orphaned in the process.
So how do I handle cases like
this and how do I handle
out of memory instances?
Um, so basically, the
way to think about
this is when you really dig
in your lab to, you know,
try to go back to this
deck of slides and
possibly this video as
well and sort of ask
yourself to think about this
conceptually as a graph
that's sort of
being mutated over
time and think like a vertex,
you know, because there's so
much stuff happening
around this,
but we were able to kind
of reduce it down to
the narrow waste interface of
thinking about it as a
graph data structure.
That's a function
of time and being
able to mutate the vertices
along the way, as
well as the graph.
As a result of all of this,
it gives us the ability to
perform copy on write fork,
extensive discussion, okay,
demand paging or
lazy allocation,
so we can defer
allocation later on.
We can have on demand
zero filled pages because
zero filling is actually
an expensive operation
if you perform this on
a critical path of a
malloc or a calloc,
I guess, right? Or an break.
We can have a 10 field
page in our system.
And as a matter of fact,
when I was working on
the Snowflok research project
back at the University
of Toronto, basically,
I needed to worry about kind of
carrying over the zero
field page from the guest
Linux kernel and
across the fork to
the rest of the virtual machines
that were forked from
the original parent.
It enables virtual allocation.
It enables virtual
shared memory.
Hopefully, we'll get
to that example.
We can also map files.
So instead of doing file IO,
we can actually
perform memory reason
writes as soon as our files
were mapped into memory,
which is a very
powerful construct,
and databases use it
all the time, okay?
They map a bunch of files that
actually represent the
data on disk, right?
And you can actually
with high efficiency
and high throughput,
perform your database operations
on memory mapped data.
You can also basically
page frames to disc,
and this is a necessary
condition for us to even
have memory oversubscription
in the first case, okay?
Because if you ran out
of physical frames,
if you ran out of physical
resources that you have to give,
and you want to prop
up this illusion of
infinite memory to
every single process,
you have to do something
under the hood.
And that something is paging
frames to disk, okay?
So maybe let's talk
about lazy allocation.
If we assign a process
virtual memory space,
do we need to populate
it with physical memory?
Well, the answer is now
obviously no, right?
Can we assign more virtual
memory than physical memory?
Yes, of course, that's
called oversubscription.
There are trade offs
associated with that.
Always think about
trade offs, okay?
Always think about trade offs,
as I myself aspire to do,
and I try to sort of instill
that on you as well.
Lazy zeroing. So, specifically,
I think we're going
to discuss this
in the context of an break.
So pages from the
kernel that are
allocated from the kernel
are zero by default.
Why? Well, if you
didn't do that,
you could have received a
physical frame from
someone that might
have stored your private SSH key
in that physical frame, right?
So that would be a
huge security leak,
you know, very easy,
low hanging fruit
kind of stuff for
the hackers to take
advantage of, right?
So, you know, by default,
you really want your
kernel pages to be free.
Um so do we need to zero
them on allocation?
As I mentioned, that's
hard because it's hold on.
hard because it's
an expensive kind of
MM set on 4,096 bytes,
which actually takes
quite a bit of
time and it's non
trivial overhead that you
want to be able to avoid.
So do all of these mappings
need to different
physical pages?
Of course, the answer is no.
Let's walk through an example.
On the left hand side, you have
virtual address space and you
have your process kind of
trying to allocate
additional memory,
o and they do that
by calling break.
Okay? So they call as break to
allocate two times page
size worth of memory.
So that means that this
is going to create
two additional V ofens
and the question is,
what physical frames
they're going to map two.
And on the right hand side,
you have your physical
memory, so you have space.
So you could have allocated
a Pfen five to VfN
four and Pfen six
to VfN five, right? You
could have done that.
But are we going
to do that? Is it
necessary for us to do that?
It's not necessary, right?
What could we do instead?
Yes. You can point them
both at the same
page and then zero
that one singular page and
then worry about remapping when
you actually make a write
to one of your VFN pages.
Exactly, right? We've already
extensively discussed the
whole copy on write stuff,
right, and on demand paging.
What we could do is basically
just take one physical frame,
MM set it to zero, right,
and point both of
those VfNs to that PFN
and worry about copy
on write later,
just like we've done
already in this class.
And so that saves memory,
which means that now you have
more virtual frames that
are that the processes and
the applications in general
believe to be in existence,
right, then there
are physical frames.
So that's the mechanism that
actually allows us over
subscription, right?
And so this is a read
only mapping, of course.
So that means that
when we do that,
of course, we do have to set
our we bit to zero, right,
so that we can take
that trap so that we
can do all of that magic that
we've already discussed,
right, to perform
a copy on write.
We can also do shared memory.
Does every virtual page need to
map to a unique
physical webpage?
I mean, that's obvious that
the answer to that is no, right?
What are some of the examples
of useful shared
memory mappings?
Do you guys know? Give me
some good examples of
shared memory mappings.
Yeah, Libraries, right?
Libraries. Exactly. And UNIX
sort of became really popular.
I don't know. 40 years ago,
something like this, right?
Because it actually saved
quite a bit of memory.
It was ultra efficient at
the time when the amount
of memory you had,
you know, was orders of
magnitude less, right,
by allowing these
shared object files,
the data so files
to be loaded into
multiple address spaces of
multiple processes and using
only a small number
of physical frames.
So it was a huge
saving exercise, okay?
And so you can actually
play around with
this and take a look
at it yourself, right?
So here, I did a
very simple thing.
I started two sleep
processes, right,
sleep 100 seconds or
sleep 200 seconds.
And I looked at their maps,
which are located
on the Slash PC
PID slash MAPS, okay?
And actually, it looks
nauseating, right?
It's so much information here,
but there's actually
quite a bit of
very useful and interesting
information here.
For instance, right?
Let's take a look at
this Lip C shared
object file that was
loaded at exactly
the same address
for both of these processes.
And the physical frames that are
occupied by the Lips library
are exactly the same,
and they are mapped into two
processes at the same time.
But without paying the cost
without paying the
double cost for them.
Okay? So that's an easy one,
but there's so much more
information out there.
So, for example, let's
take a look at this
mapping right here.
Do you see my cursor? Okay, so
this mapping is so first of all,
the three least significant
hexadecimal digits,
notice that all of the mappings,
they have three
least significant
hexadecimal digits
to being zero.
Why is that the case? Yeah, the
page what's the page size
in this system? You think?
What?
Yeah, two to the
power of 12, right?
And the 12 bits are basically
three hexadecimal digits.
So all of these mappings
are page aligned.
That's observation simple
observation number one, right?
What are some additional
observations?
Well, let's look at
this region right here.
So now shift right by
three hexadecimal digits.
So disregard them because
they're all page aligned,
and you will be
dealing with VfNs.
Okay? So this particular
mapping is from
c00 VfN to D eight A VN.
And it's readable
and executable.
What do you think that is?
For lip C. Yeah, huh?
It's a code segment
for lip C, right?
Exactly. You don't
want to write to it,
but you want to read it and
you want to execute it.
And how many virtual
frames or actually,
how many physical frames does
it take in order
for us to actually
maintain this specific mapping
for the code segment of lip C?
If I were to ask
you this question,
how many physical frames
do I need in order
to support a ip
Cde code segment?
And the answer can
be in hexodecimal.
I don't want you to do
the decimal math here.
What's the answer
in hexodecimal?
18 A. It's D eight A give
me my cursor. 1 second.
Maybe if I switch it to
a laser pointer, it
would be better.
It's D eight A right here
minus c00 right
here. You get 18 A.
18 a VM the PfN mappings,
how many PTs does that take
to maintain this mapping?
18 A. Now, so
that means that we need
at least 18 A mappings
in order to map Lip C
in this case, right?
So how many page
table pages does it
take in order to
maintain 18 A PTs?
Only one because how many
elements can we fit?
One page table page.
So this is a bit of a
tricky 64 bit system.
But let's forget about
the fact that it's
a 64 bit system.
We can treat it as
a 32 bit system
for the purposes
of this question.
In a 32 bit system,
the breakdown of linear
address is 101012, okay?
The second most
significant ten digits
is an index into a last level
page table page, right?
So that means that there
are 1024 elements,
due to the power of ten elements
that you can store in a
single page table page.
What is 1024 in hex?
What?
It's 400. It's going
to be less than sorry,
it's going to be
greater than 18 A.
So the answer that you only need
a single page table page here in
order to map 18 A
PTs is correct.
Okay? So you only got away with
a single last level
page table page to
map the entirety of
the Lipsey code.
Just one page table page.
Okay, so there's so much
information in these things.
For a 64 bit system,
just for the purposes
of completion,
we're now dealing with
a 48 bit address space,
and the last level
page table page
has nine bits
indexing into that.
Remember? You guys
remember that?
Because this is the last
lecture we're discussing this.
Okay, so with nine bits,
how many elements is that?
Yes, 512 in decimal,
200 in hexadecimal.
So that's still going to
be greater than 18 A.
Okay? So even in
the 64 bit system,
you're able to get away with
a single page table page in
order to map the lips code.
Okay? So is that fun or what?
Just by looking at
this information,
you can already ask
some really cool questions
and ask yourself, well,
what is the overhead
associated with me,
maintaining these
shared mappings across
the processes for a
shared object file. Okay?
So this is a laundry list of
everything we're able
to support, right?
We're going to talk about
swapping on Tuesday.
And I just wanted to end
on a research perspective.
This Eurosis 2000
sorry, where is it?
The On Demand fork,
the 2021 paper.
It's going to be in the slides
and the slides have
already been shared.
I encourage you to
take a look at that.
And the reason why this was
a really cool paper is
because it's the paper
that made the right call
of performing copy on write on
the last level page table pages
for stateful read
only applications.
Okay, so the motivation was that
the applications have
large memory footprints.
That means that
they have lots of
PTEs to map a large
memory space,
which does not change.
So that's hundreds of megabytes.
There are lots of PTPs to copy,
lots of page table
pages to copy.
So is it possible?
Well, we don't have time to
consider other alternatives.
The proposed solution was
that there is a drop in
replacement for fork.
They literally implemented
their own fork
that performs page table
page copy on write.
And, of course, they
evaluated this with
applications that allocate
1 gigabyte of memory.
And now, do the
mental gymnastics to
figure out if you're mapping
1 gigabyte of memory,
how many PTPs do we
need for this?o?
Does anybody want to do that?
I'll leave it as a
thought exercise,
but there's a very
precise answer to this.
1 gigabyte is due
to the power of 30,
and that's your
starting point, okay?
So that's a lot of PTPs.
And if you're not
making any changes
to the PTEs of those PTPs,
you might as well not
copy them on a fork.
As a result, the micro benchmark
demonstrated that they
were able to save 99%
of latency on fork.
Okay? So that's basically,
let's say, 100 to one.
It's almost 100 X improvement
as far as the micro
benchmark is concerned.
But then the question
is, does it help when
the applications are
really running and
really executing in production.
That's called a macro benchmark.
So the macro benchmark here
demonstrated that the
execution throughput
itself was showing
improvements anywhere 59-226%.
Okay? And that's
really it for today.
I encourage you to go
back to this lecture.
Thankfully, it's recorded.