Okay.
It
No
that's
no and
No
We
one? I'm My Stator.
I to my best experience in fact.
I'm not, in fact, a TA
or graduate student.
I get that every meeting,
so let's clarify that.
Welcome to Lecture
Dere on security.
I was asked. I'm actually in
a security and privacy
department at SEP and SES.
I was asked to come
and guest lecture.
I'm incredibly excited
means I get ref
live scream so I
sort of began my most
recent career as
a PhD student in ECS and MIT,
graduated a while ago.
I then went to Google,
where I worked on Android
Security and Privacy team
as a senior research scientist.
I'm actually still
affiliated with them,
part time, when I left.
They very emphatically said,
Hear God, please about
the projects around up.
And now I'm here. I
moved to Atlanta.
I'm a professor, incredibly
excited to talk.
The things that I tend
to hack on personally,
is that I build and break
systems that are
relevant to society.
So I have this sort of
intersectional belief
in looking at economics,
law, public policy, and
then building systems
that are related to that.
As a result, I've
actually done some
interesting research.
One study that we did actually
found security flaws in
every Internet voting
system used to
US federal election
thing that I can
talk about the nice
lecture a little bit.
I've written Amicus support by
electronic Meer Foundation
Society organization
that deals with policy logy.
I've also done a bunch of crypto
research including stuff that
resulted in legislation not
being passed in Congress.
We know that because they read
our report to pressional freer,
so it's part of history now.
The thing that I've been
focusing on recently is
ten encryption and re
decentralization of social media.
This is the thing that I'm
incredibly talking about.
We're also looking into things
related to location privacy,
things like air tags,
and things like that.
So, in general, this has
led to a bunch of really,
really interesting and sort
of attractive security research.
So that's part of the
reason why I'm here
today sort of evangelize
folks getting
involved in security
and security research
to tell you why
I'm excited by it.
So I'm going to
start with probably a
really basic question
because every lecture like
this is to start with
a weird rhetorical question
that might actually
have answers.
What actually is
computer security?
The actual real
question, not a real.
You want to raise
your race holes.
Yes. I would say something
like ensuring that
users actually
using your computer
are not able to do things that.
Keeping running.
Ask any other Intra
malicious actors
can hack Auto acc introduced
a new term malicious actor.
So someone writing malware
someone who's trying
to do something bad,
maybe a presence of
an adversary one.
I start coclling.
Maybe there might be a
policy you can put it,
stress, make a system adhere to.
One, someone who is not
authorized to get access
to something access.
Yeah, computer security is
actually ill defined
as a discipline.
The best that I could
come up with was
sort of these two definitions,
one of which is
useful free today.
One is security
assistance design,
which you can sort of put
in as something
akin to medicine.
Right? You have a system and
you're going to introduce
some properties to it,
and you're going to understand
what those properties do.
The second is security is
ecosystem analysis,
akin to public health.
So how well the
security properties
at work in real real well.
So when you study security,
you might be doing one
of these two things.
And what's really relevant to
you for this class
and I'm going to
focus on in this
class is this idea
of security systems design.
Okay. I'm going to
be a little bit more
specific about what
I mean by that
here. What does
that actually mean?
Security to abstract
really far out,
it's just the design
of systems to achieve
some property that
you're going to
define against an
act of adversary.
Somebody trying to
push your system over.
The general process for
this is you first
define your system,
you provide a set
of security goals,
and then you provide
some sort of
proof that your system
actually follows these goals.
This is incredibly high level,
and we're going to delve
a little bit more
into all of them.
But I first want to illustrate
the sort of difference between
what you might have been
doing recently and security.
And I think it's summed
up in these two gifts.
What is the difference
between these two scenarios?
Sure. Actually, you have.
Maybe a point of failure.
Yes, there's a point of failure,
but both systems failed.
Perhaps one of the lowered
dramatically or the other.
This bridge actually did
fall down eventually.
So how it call.
Yeah, there's an adversary,
Bestrs being destroyed by
Sensi agglomeration things.
This is just bad
design. So for example,
a bridge might never fall down,
but someone bombing said bridges
a different set of
design constraints.
It's a different set
design interests.
There's an active
adversary that might
know how the bridge
was actually constructed,
for example.
Okay. I don't cool.
All right. So there
are two large components when
you're actually designing
a system like this.
The first is a series
of goals, right?
And you've already dealt
with some of this, right?
A separate user on a same
computer shouldn't be,
for example, DA goal.
No process or being able to read
another process is memory unless
explicitly set up a debugger GE
or something like this, right?
I can also be categories,
called the CA thread. Does
anyone know what that is?
CAA. So that's the
organization. A, go forward.
Confident it's
confidentiality, integrity,
and veteran availability is DA.
These might be a series of
goals that you might
have for a system,
very important, for example,
for a time server to
always have integrity,
you don't want someone
mucking at the
time and be very available,
but you don't really care
if it's confidential.
So this is just a really
high level framework
that people use
categories of goals.
And then you have this thing
called a threat bottle
the threat bottle is
actually somewhat nuanced.
And really, at the
end of the day,
it's set of assumptions
about what attacker
can and cannot do.
Defining this is actually
really important.
For example, are we assuming
that two processes are
running on the same machine?
Are we assuming if I'm a
user that someone that can
get physics aviceF example,
these assumptions
actually really
determine the actual outcome
of the system that you're using.
We can disuss a
little bit about a
bit of examples in the future.
Another example might be can
someone guess passwords.
How often they can I
guess they're dliftd.
In general, front model will
specify what's in
and out of scope,
and the goal is to find
what you actually
want to achieve.
I'm going to illustrate
a little bit,
why this is actually
hard in a little bit.
But the components of
actually how you do this,
the implementation
falls into two pockets,
this is generally how you
actually achieve your goals.
The first is policy,
which is a set of rules.
Now, it's like technical policy,
I don't mean, what they do in
DC unless you're like
Amazon voting in DC.
But I mean things that
are file permissions,
requiring passwords of
two backations policy.
There's a mechanism, right?
This is just hardware
and software
that actually sort
of force your goals.
So for example, a lot of
you don't know if gotten
to this point yet.
You've written virtual
memory, right?
Written You have this ability
to separate processes so they
can fit each other's memory.
Yeah. That same mechanism.
Another example might be
user accounts, right?
I think set UID is another thing
that you guys
implemented this Boss.
Have you gotten there
yet? About four.
Okay. Sorry, I'm telegraphing
things an issue.
But this will be important.
Encryption might be
another thing,
another mechanism.
All right, so let's
talk about an example.
Your TA controls Canvas,
which ultimately controls your
grade of this boss, right?
The policy here is
that only your TA
should be able to change
grades in Canvas.
Let's say you guys don't
like these labs
that you're doing.
How do you choose GE?
What might you do?
Please don't in into
things. Pay off the TA.
Bride a TA.
Sure. Go to office hours,
wait for the TA to leave
their laptop and then
do it from there.
I was just exactly what you.
If you're using the TA,
that might be a. I'm sorry.
Any others?
I can yeah, you might
break into Canvas servers.
You might do all
sorts of things.
You might skill your
computer, break
into UTAs tech account.
I might break into Canvas
or bribe an ad in there.
I might also go after
your professor's account.
Suggestion you might bribe,
which normally you don't get,
but it's interesting that this
is the first thing that was
actually chosen out of this.
The point here is
that there's actually
a ton of attacks and
they're fun to think about.
Security is actually
a negative goal.
You're proving the
absence of something,
the absence of the ability
to actually execute
the soil. That's
actually kind of hard.
There's a bunch of ways in
which failure to occur,
and only one of them is
really necessary in order
for someone to
change their grade.
Of course, in
practice, our diligent
professor staring
daggers at me right now.
We'll immediately notice an
attempt and you will fail,
which itself is kind of
a security guarantee
that's interesting, right?
Be the sort of expected value of
changing your grade
might actually be quite
different if you actually
attempt to do so.
So one of the things
that I really like
about security is
that you get to ask
this question a lot,
and some of those scenarios
are very entertaining.
And generally, they sort of
fit in these categories.
So, for example, you
might just have bad
policies or goals.
You might have a bad threat.
Like your assumptis
about what your
adversary can be wrong,
and you might have just
bad mechanisms, right?
So like bugs in your mechanism.
We're going to talk about OPs.
Let's talk about incorrect
goals and or policies.
I want to give you an
illustrated example
and see if you can
figure out how it works.
This is a real thing
that happened.
Please don't go into this
until I'm done, so I sit on.
In Fairfax County, Virginia,
a 9-year-old boy was caught
accessing a gray
management account
owned by the superintendent.
So clearly something
has gone wrong here,
but this is a thing.
The question is, how?
I'm going to give you
the system's policies,
and I want someone
to raise their hand and tell
me exactly what happened.
And the policies are student can
access only their own files.
The superintendent has
access to everyone's grades,
files, et cetera, because
they're superintendent.
Teachers can add new
students to their class.
Teachers can change the password
of any student in their class,
and the student got access to
everybody as the superintendent.
So what actually happened here?
One hand up. Did the teacher
add the superintendent as
a student and then
change their password?
Yeah, what happened
here is hilarious,
is the question you
might want to ask,
what's the worst thing
can have a student
gets access to the
teacher's password.
Is the student adds
a superintendent to
a compromise teacher's class
and changes their password.
Right? Because they can
just do that, right,
any user is someone who
can connect to a class.
And then logs in as a
superintendent docks solidles.
So this is kind of sad.
And the point here
is that the policy
actually amounts to teachers do
anything clearly got
the intended goal of
the system, right?
This is a policy that led to
a particularly bad failure.
Then we get this kind
of a hilarious example.
Policies typically go wrong in
the management or
maintenance cases, right?
So for example, who can change
permissions or passwords
on a computer?
Who can get access
to audit logs,
and what might be storing
those autologs including
errors that include said
passwords and things like this.
Who can get access to backups.
Who can upgrade software
change configuration
of the device, right?
Who can manage servers
and who revokes privileges
of former ABIs.
These are all sort of
relevant questions
you might want to ask
yourself in your Pat system.
What policies might be involved.
So let's talk about
threat models.
Getting a threat model right
might be incredibly subtle.
I'm going to provide a
few examples of this.
So talk about bad throw models.
I think my favorite
example of this are folks
that just believe that because
their system is quite esoteric,
they might actually know
how my system works,
and therefore I am secure.
I compile it myself. I
run entu because I'm,
you know, masochist
or something.
I take x26, I compile it
and I run it on my own.
Therefore, no one's going to
know how my system works.
There's this thing if you take
nothing else from this lectures,
please remember this principle
called Karkovs principle,
which states that the
system is always secure.
The adversary knows everything
about the system, and
it is still secure.
In other words, the
enemy knows the system.
So for a long time, for
example, cryptography,
we just kept crypto
secret with the assumption
that if the enemy knew
how ictography worked,
they would be able to break it.
And that's really not a
good design principle.
And the inverse of this is
security through
security, right?
Sort of hide. I think a
fantastic example of this
typing
a fantastic example
of this is something
called the Clipper Chip.
Anyone have heard of
this? A couple of knots.
What was the Clipper
hip? Clipper chip
was a government
mandated back door
to certain encryption
Levi's encryption chips
on the processing board
of certain computers.
Yeah, this was an
NSA designed chip
that way back in the day
it was sort of a arguable,
people were arguing
as to whether or
not crytography should be
available to the general masses.
The US government came
up with this middle
ground where they said,
Okay, the NSA is going
to create this chip.
Only US person should
be able to get
access to the cryptography
that is done on
this chip, right?
Only US law enforcement,
for example, can actually break
the cryptography on this chip.
Uh, and then be able to see
your group communications.
It was actually done
on phones back in
the day, flaneline wired phones.
What was interesting
about this is
that design of it was
completely secret.
And this very irascible
now professor,
formerly a research
scientist at Bell Labs,
A Blaze, got off and broke it.
And the design was known
bad. It was clearly bad.
The only reason they believe
they were going to get
away with this is because
no same person would sit
there for hours decapping
the ship and understanding
how it works.
And it turns out that,
computer science
professors are not safe.
In this. That's why we research.
So this is just like a
fantastic example of this.
Have you ever seen, like,
what was the Alan
Turing documentary
ntationGame, you go into this.
It's a really fantastic.
Other bad models examples.
How many people here
from a Stuxnet?
What was sucks that?
Basically, the government
snuck a bunch of
software to destroy or it was
targeting the PLCs for
nuclear centrifuges, I think.
It's been just a
little bit too fast,
they would break over time, and
I had to get through
the air gap because
those weren't connected.
Yeah, these were air gaps.
This was an attack that
happened on air gap systems,
particularly Iranian nuclear
facilities center beaches.
The assumption, the
security assumption here
is that one could not
jump the Air GAP.
And what was used to
get on these systems
was just a zero day and how
Windows processes USB
media on the USB stay.
Jump their gaps assumption
didn't work out, right?
Then there's
computational assumpions.
This happens a lot
in phytography.
You might make an
assumption that
a cryptographic primitive
is always going to be fine.
S is really great example
of this dates back again
to the original
proporsscpton, where, hey,
there was an algorithm
that was known broken,
but computationally would be
feasible for anyone but the
NSA to be able to break,
of course, computers
got really fast and
you can break this
now on your laptop.
So this is actually a
real thing that was used,
encrypted communication
between you and your bank,
for example, back in the day.
It's not using Bolin.
And of course, there's
quantum computers now.
Well, ish Shor's algorithm
breaks a well known graphic RSA.
So prime factorization,
which is what
RSA sort of depends on,
no longer going to work.
Another example,
trust your hardware.
I think this is seems
like a bats fining movie,
but I'm telling you, it's true.
There's this thing called
the Farewell Dossier.
And during the Cold War, Soviets
tried to steal US plans in
tact they often lack the
ability to generate their own.
The problem is that US actually
had defector in the sort
of intelligence group that
was doing this called
the classified farewell.
And this guy named Gus Weiss,
who is the National
Security Council
in group in the White House,
Director of
International Economics,
later would describe
what happened here.
They generated contrived
computer chips which
found their way into
Soviet military equipment.
Flawed turbines
were installed on
a gas pipeline and
defective plant,
output of chemical plants
in a tractor facility.
Pentagon introduced
misleading information
pertinent to sell aircraft,
space events, and
tactical aircraft.
The Soviet space shuttle
was a rejected NASA design.
So they used this,
you know,
just trusting the sort of
pipeline that they had,
trusting the hardware,
where they got it from.
Turns out not to
necessarily be accurate,
especially when you get
the deletion states.
This is, again, a very
entertaining example
of this kind of break.
Another great example is
just trusting your software.
So in 2015, Chinese
IOS developers,
turned out that Apple
didn't have Akamai did have
three place servers in other
countries for a long time.
So if you try to
download Xcode would
take hour or
something like this.
So a bunch of people
in China were
just hosting Xcode locally.
Uh, in some of
these years that we're
posting Eco actually just
had Malware amended.
As a result, it actually
injected Malware
into compiled apps.
This is a thing
called Xcode host.
This was in hundreds if
not thousands of apps
in the app store.
We're all just like, you know,
doing basically
controlled as Bontthing.
There's a really
famous essay on this
by Ken Thompson. You
guys know who he is?
If you were not assigned
K&R credit Well,
Yeah, so he's a to award winner.
He wrote this fantastic lecture.
It's two pages long,
called reflections
and Trusting Trust,
which discusses this concept
of backroom thing, right?
Bro this is a known bug.
There's really no good way of
solving this other than
reading and compiling
code itself or trusting
the folks who are actually
developing for in
kids like this.
So again, this is a very
interesting example.
Another example might
just cross media updates.
A good example, this
is Apple, the FBI.
Everybody remember the
Sandord video thing?
Basically, the law enforcement
tried to order Apple to create
a It update to
their device that had been
found to break a window
that was used device.
It's interesting, maybe
we shouldn't just
trust that an update comes
from the right place.
Now we have UK who's trying
to do something very similar.
Is anyone familiar
with Left PAD?
So NPM NPM is the cop
script framework that has
a centralized code repository
that you include by
reference the same
way that you do with
G. So you might have a URL,
and a bunch of
people were depend
on this library called left pad,
which literally would
left pad things
like zero pad left. Okay.
It's not that hard.
Someone bought paid off
MBM package repository and got
that namespace replacing
the old library,
and a bunch of people
downloaded and compiled
their apps had this
malicious left pad in it.
It was just supposed
to pad things
left and arbitrary
code execution.
Croma said she was actually
bought by Mauer authors.
Here's a link to
that. I don't need to
go into this, but basically,
people were thinking they
were installing ad blockers
and said they were
installing Mauer.
This seems to be a group.
But what else can you go?
You might have bad mechanisms.
So a rule thumb
here any bug that you find
could be actually segregation.
Examples of this include buffer
overflows, use after free,
code injection failures,
just even straight crashes
might be indicative of a.
There's a bunch of
examples of things that
people did not think were
going to be issues that turned
out to be really big ones.
Timing attacks is
a great example.
It takes you longer to do one
thing versus another thing,
and that leaks information to
me that might disclose
useful information.
People have used that to
a filtrate, for example,
for dots is why
people tell you not to
throw your own for dot.
It's a really good example.
It's especially bad
when attacker allows
an attacker to
cross what's called
a trust boundary and
elevate privileges.
And what we mean by
this is, for example,
I might trust remote
attacker supplying
a value to my function cannot
control the entirety
of my program,
but gave the attacker access
to the entire
program or control.
I was trusting a thing as a
developer, as a designer,
and it turned out that
assumption was false or
falsified using some
mechanism failure.
Another example
might be attacker
finds a flaw in a program,
more really just do something.
I think a really good example is
straight up memory safety.
I have this function here.
You might be able to tell
which one has the problem.
Made it quite easy. Can someone
tell me what's wrong
with this Quit.
That's it.
So what
the flaw or just like what
it does, you call it?
What's the flaw?
What's the issue here?
So the input if
the input size is
greater than the buffer,
then you have a buffer overflow,
so you can like malicious code.
Yeah. The as they have.
The formula might be
that you're not checking
the bounds of what is input
into Mulable function.
You have a buffer that's
definitionally size
ten here and you're
copying arbitrary input
into it that might be
longer than the amount
that you've allocated.
I'm going to try to illustrate
exactly what happens here.
Let's just say that
the input is one
through through ten or one
through zero in this case.
I want you to think
through you guys
the sack and how
that outing else.
You might save onto the
stack base pointer,
you might save onto the
stack return address.
Do you use 64 bit or 32 bits?
32.
So these makes us
that at this point,
and you're going to allocate
this ten size buffer
onto the stack,
which in this case is
allocated to zero,
and that might actually not be
true in certain circumstances,
let's assume that that
is actually true.
Then it's going to fill it with
one through a null terminator.
And then continue
on. This is fine.
Nothing bad happened
here in this example.
But let's say, we
actually instead of saying
one through through zero,
I see characters
one through zero.
We now say eight times 100.
We're definitionally going
to do something on here.
What happens?
Someone who did not.
Since you might
start to overwrite
other stack frames that
are if you allocate
something that's
only ten and then you put 100,
you're going to
probably overrate the
previous stack
frames that are on
top of the current stack
that you calculus function.
You're going to
overrate, something
called before you're going
to overrate stack frames.
What else can you overrate?
In particular is
the scary thing?
Varies. Like what's the side
of the sectrum you worried
about the most? Yeah.
What would you be most
concerned about already?
Probably the return of.
Yes. So you're worried
about the returns?
Exactly. Uh, so what's
going to go on here,
you're going to end your not it,
the same thing that happened
before except now
you're going to
overwrite IP with
ASA's 41 per 41.
And this is going to jump
when you return into Narnia,
because that's not
a address, right?
But you can then
change that address.
In fact, you have control over
the stack so you can jump
into the stack because the
stack here is executable.
So you can set it to the getting
of this just time
to start executing.
IP, once you control it, you
actually have control
over the entire program.
Is makes sense to everybody.
So people decide if that's okay.
All right. Yeah, once
I control the IP,
they're dead, right?
I can return to code
that I wrote the stack.
I can also return to
known functions, right?
For example, known things
that exist in LBC.
I can set up a stack,
and then I can call in
LC arbitrary input into it.
And yeah, the game here is
generally the adversary ones.
There's a bunch of
examples knows.
Buffer overflow is one example
of a larger thing
called memory cction.
This includes over weeds.
Actually, I can do an
information display here.
So how many people
here are heartbleed?
So heartbleed was
this vulnerability
of a program poops L,
which is everywhere on
the Internet, everybody
runs this thing.
It turns out had a
buffer over read,
so you could actually read
arbitrary values
from the server.
This was sort of a world
ending bug that required
a major coordinated effort
to go off and sold.
Use after free is another
thing where if you
free something,
then it's used again, that
might result in a vulnerability.
And these kind of
things happen on both
the stack and the heap.
You've probably become
inti bit familiar with.
For more and a really
fantastic history on
this, read this paper,
external war met ray goes over
a large history of
superbugs that are
found time and other examples.
Something that might be relevant
to you all carnal developers.
You've all written a
big pile of C recently.
Are you sure that it's
free of these issues?
There are 456 cis calls in.
There's a fantastic thing here
see if I can actually
show you this.
It's fantastic website
illustrates all.
There's all these cis
calls. I have it's lovely.
Loux Kernel has roughly
40 million lines of code.
Device drivers,
particular painfuid are
written by OEMs people
who manufacture
the devices and they tend
not to necessarily care about
the security price
properties in the system.
So very often,
there's whats there.
The result of
something like this,
there's a system
called Cis Color,
which is the thing that I
worked on a Google for a bit
that will fuzzing send
arbitrary data from space
in kernel space a VM,
much like you're
using for this class.
We'll fuzz various calls the
find bugs, find vbilties.
If you go to this website,
it's colspo.com slash OStrem.
This will actually
show you all of
the known these are things
that this thing has found,
S music bugs that this thing has
found that are still
not fixed in is Curl.
It's on the Internet.
Terrifying, right? I think
this is very entertaining stuff.
But yeah, like it turns out that
writing a large pile of Cs
are really hard to is here.
The solutions that
people have come up with
here straightforward things
like proving your code correct,
using bounce
checking, making sure
that you actually check the
inputs and things like this.
There's a series
of things that are
compiler optimizations
or compiler,
things that compiler can
do like ASLR, depth,
and various other things like
those KasNs like this
that will either cause
your computer default
if the program will
crash and in the case of
hurdle fault and crash,
the entire operations crash,
one of these issues and
there are some other primitives
that might be helpful,
which we'll discuss
the next sub here.
But the real solution
here is very
often is to use a
memory safe language.
Linux does have Rust and
the kernel moving forward,
which is really exciting.
This is somewhat of an
ideological thing that,
you know, you've gone for.
And by the way, I'm not the
only one who's saying this.
In fact, the White House issued
a press release stating
that the future of coach
should be memory safe.
So the White House has
gotten on board with this.
This is the previous
White House not hard.
I'm not entirely sure what
one's policies are to this.
Yeah, so this is
super interesting.
All right. Let me give you
another example, passwords.
How would you use the
word password honest?
So when you're logging in, how
does your operating
system actually
handle the log in process?
I don't think it's a thing
they've done yet, right?
Yes, b. The one who
hasn't answered.
Yes. Well you like to
hash the password?
Yes. You might hash it.
You definitely shouldn't leave
it in plain text, right?
This is a naive solution.
Well if you go wrong. What
assumptions am I making sides?
Why would I not do this?
To say. Yes. Because if someone
knows where you start
a password memory,
they can access that.
If I take the hard drive out of
your machine and then
start forensically imaging
it or looking at it,
I'm going to see your
password in latex.
I would be sad. If I got route
on your computer somehow,
I might through some others,
I might know the password is.
That seems unfortunate as well.
All right. Solution two,
let's talk about hashes.
Hash in a very broad sense,
this is the thing that takes
an arbitrary size straight
and reduces it to
a string of size D. It
has these other goals?
It's efficient, it's
terministic, it's random,
it's public, the outrms
being used here.
Everyone knows and
is repeatable.
And importantly, you're
not able to go back.
Examples, people probably
heard of MD five.
They probably heard Sha 56, yes.
There are other
versions as well.
Shah three, which is
kind of interesting.
The whole Shah three family
is a super cool thing.
In particular, has a
variable length digest.
Variable length.
It's kind of cool.
So you can specify how long
you want your hash to be?
Others include things like
collision resistance,
which states that
given some value X,
you can't find X prime such
that the hash two
of them are equal,
assuming, X and X prime
are not the same thing.
You can't collide them, you
can't find two
different values of
the same thing and
one wynus which just says that
basically given the result
of a hash in this case,
I can't can't get
the hashba out.
It's just interesting.
These are important properties.
This actually solves
your password
issue, you're hashing something.
I can't get the
original text back out.
I can't find another password.
Well let me get into the system.
Math at you and last general
Does this all makes sense?
I'm not going to tell
you how these are made
because that's beyond
the scope of the class,
but assume lluciate with
me that these things
actually exist.
How many people did I just lose?
All right. Cool. All right.
I just store the hash with
the password on this.
That is our new strategy?
I'm going to ask
a common question
here, what can go for it on.
Yes. They could figure out what
the hash is and then
they could store.
Yeah, I just said I can't
go backward though.
Right? So you can't take
the hash or something and they
get the actual thing back out.
Carl, you can rootworm
and store it.
So if I say,
take the English dictionary
and dump it through
a hash and they pair
it with the passwords,
I might get some
passwords back out.
Yeah.
Each. Fantastic, yes.
I just carry this database
of likely passwords,
and then I calculate
the hashes to them all.
Then now you can recover
the ones that are most
likely to exist, Password
one, two, three,
four happens an upsetting number
of times because
humans are humans,
we don't memorize things.
I'm not going to go
why this is true,
but it actually works even if
the password space
that you're doing
is prohibitively super large.
This works through something
called rainbow tables,
which is a beautiful
hack that exploits
the time space trade off that
limits the size of
your password list.
What's fun here is this has
actually happened, right?
Adobe actually lost 2.9
million customers passwords,
and somehow over 150 million
of those actually
wound up online.
Those are actually sort
of cash passwords, if is.
And as a result of this, this
150 million user emails,
encrypted passwords,
and password hints
being leaked was kind
of entertaining.
But they used this sort of
incorrect encryption incorrect
mode for doing this.
And the result was this
kind of laeous idea.
Where you can create this giant
Crossword plus a lot of filming
because you have
the hints and they
have a bunch of them
are all identical.
So you can actually
guess, you know, Oh,
you know, one person same
says name plus Jersey,
another one says, you know,
John plus Jersey and,
you know who's what the
actual password was.
And by the way, this is
actually a real thing.
You can go to this
website and play
this game as the
passers from this game.
This is pretty entertaining.
You've seen how to not do this.
How should you actually do this?
The real solution
here is that you
hash and you add
something called assault.
You're going to add
naught to the password.
You generate this random number
and you're going to store
the hash instead of
just a hash the
password or the hash
the password concatenated
with this random value.
That way you can't
precompute anything.
It's not breaking T thing
is actually equivalent to
actually the hash of
yourself an inordinate
amount of time.
This is the real
method to do it.
Modern techniques actually use
intentionally slow
hash functions,
things that would take
far longer for you
to get here to here.
This is one of the reasons
why they try to log
in your laptop and mess
up a couple of times,
but it's slow.
It's like slow process down to.
It's intentional. That's
a security goal, right?
They're trying to
invade it, so it's not
possible to have
this time of time.
All right. So I am
43 minutes past,
which means 7 minutes
early. I have a question.
So let's say if you
go back to the app,
you compute R, then how do
you get into the system?
So when you log in,
it takes a hash and knows R,
that's on this reads R,
it takes a hash of the
password that you entered,
concatenated with R and just
compares that with
what's actually on disk.
Well, what if someone knows
the R you have in your system?
Oh, it doesn't matter, right?
So it's a good question.
Because Mike, you're
telling me that R is
on disk and people can know so
the important thing here
is to keep in mind,
what attack you're trying
to prevent against.
R does not prevent
somebody from trying to
enforce your password, right?
So this is a really good point.
If you have a very
likely password,
they can sit there
and enforce it.
But they can't use the sort of
approach that were discussing
before because you can
use R. That's the thing
that you're trying
to provide against.
So you're making it so they
have to do this large thing,
this provi large dataset.
Are Rabo tables just like a
list of really popular words?
Rambo table was a list of
really popular passwords with
some magic that I'm
not going to explain
here because it's beyond
the scope of the class and
it far too long
for me to explain
that actually allows
you to do this for
billions of billions
of ten passwords.
It turns out this not possible.
Are there any other questions?
I didn't mean to speed through.
I just get nervous
in a glass because we
have 5 minutes left.
I wanted to make sure
I got through. Cool.
This time, we talked
about finding security.
We talked about the goals and
threat models that
you might have.
We talked about how you
might implement this,
in particular, we talked about
policies and mechanisms.
We gave you a bunch of
examples of how things
can go horribly wrong.
I gave you an
intuition behind them.
And we talked a little bit
about mechanism failures
and and how things go.
Next time, I think
I've depressed you
all with all these
horrible things
that can go horribly wrong.
And I promise you that there are
good things that
we can do to make
at least systems more
resilient in the presence
of these kind of failures.
We're going to talk a
little bit more about
operating systems for security.
In particular, I'm going to
talk to you about
isolation containers,
fuzzing and a few other
things that are common
here that solve many
of these problems or
at least make it more
that I aggregate.
I'm incredibly excited
and I'll see you,
I guess in a week two weeks?
How long is it? Next
week, Thursday.
Next week, Thursday. Swear
before spring break.
All right.
Are there any other questions?
Yes, good question.
Way back when we were
talking about string copy,
how is the other
version of it that
takes into account the
size of memory buffer?
Yeah. Why does the C standard
even still include the
one that doesn't do that?
It is a fantastic question.
Why we even allow book guide?
The answer to that is that
not all languages do, right?
If you have C is a
very old language that
has tons and tons of Google
develop software for it,
and if you get rid
of an API for it.
You've just destroyed a
ton of legacy software.
So this is a very good point,
why are we allowing users
in language design,
maybe shouldn't allow computers.
That's basically what
things like Ross are doing.
They're saying, you're
going to fight with
ix and is best,
and we'll stop you
from doing things like
unbounded checking
like this, unbounded.
But even in those, it turns
out that you actually need
sometimes do unsafe things.
For example, EMA,
memory access require an
initial life is somewhere,
and Russ has no good
answers to this right now.
They just let you
break out of it using.
There's a fun examples
of things like this.
It's all very long
wood way of saying,
why doesn't the language
actually help you here?
In some cases, they do in.
It's a very good question.
Officers hurt anything
else. Anything else?
Okay. Well, it was
fantastic at Electric.
I was you all in
I