You yes
Friday Friday
Saturday
What's up with the weather.
I got here and I'm
basically drenching
in this in whatever it is
that's happening outside.
It's not really a rain,
it's not really a fog.
It's something that's
sort of precipitating
as you walk through it, right?
Okay, so we're done
with our VMM lectures,
and today we're
planning to start
our interrupts and
concurrency lecture sequence.
So this is interrupts and
concurrency part one.
I did want to do a bit of
a wrap up on swapping
because we touched upon
the virtual memory management
tips and tricks at
the end of the last
lecture last week.
And swapping was actually
something that's fairly
important to talk about.
Okay?
So to get you guys warmed up,
I'm sure all of you know
by now that lab two is
due two weeks is
due on February 21.
Uh, I don't know.
It's one week from this Friday,
not two weeks from this Friday.
So it's due on February 21.
I do recommend submitting you
assignments towards
the end of this week,
which is Valentine's Day.
You know, what
better way to spend
your Valentine's Day than
submit your lab, too, right?
I'm sure many of
you will relate.
Um, and.
And the reason for this
is because it's going to
take some time to debug, okay?
So you may actually feel
quite confident with
your algorithm.
You may feel quite confident
with your grasp of
the conceptual
stuff that sort of
goes into figuring
things out in lab two.
Many cases that you may
not have thought about,
and this is quite normal.
This is expected. That's what
the test cases are there for.
And do make sure that you leave
a week to go through
them because it's
highly unlikely that
you'll get all of
your 100% of your score,
you know, the first time
you submit or even the
second time you submit.
Okay? I mentioned
declaring teams.
This is the boring stuff.
I just want to make
it official, right?
And I want to get
through it fast.
So bear with me. There were
still 22 students unassigned,
and so just sort of
declaratively specifying that
those teams are going to
be treated as single
student group.
So at the start of the lecture,
I checked, there's some students
that were not assigned
to any group.
That means that you're
in a group by yourself.
Okay? Welcome. Join.
Okay. And grade
scope, furthermore,
I've been told by the TA
that grade scope
is going to throw
an error if the team
member is not specified.
So make sure that you do
specify a team member
on every single
decision to ensure
appropriate accounting
for the number
of the times you have
submitted as a team.
Any questions so far?
Okay. Now, here's a slightly
more interesting slide.
Okay, so first of all,
we have identified
a handful of people
who perhaps accidentally
left their code public.
And I just want to, again,
as a matter of politic clarity
was specified that this
puts these people in
the gray area of
academic dishonesty.
Um, most cases are just
simple and honest mistakes.
And so this slide
is to disambiguate
how you should collaborate on
your Github repositories
in a private fashion
that doesn't get you into
the gray area of
academic dishonesty.
Make sure you initialize
the private repository that
is only visible to
you and your partner.
Then you perform
a local clone of
the XV six public
repository that we
provided to you as the
teaching staff of CS 3210.
You check out the branch. Okay.
Then remote you add a remote
for the private repository
that you have just
created, okay?
And there's a command for that.
Git remote ad that
adds a remote.
Then just verify that
your private repository
has been added
and is now listed as one of
the remotes for your
local repository,
X V six repository,
and you do that with Git
remote V. And finally push.
To your private remote.
I'm calling it lab two, private.
It's your private remote.
The branch name lab two.
Any questions about that?
How many of you are
unaware that if you
fork a public repository,
it stays public.
People were unaware.
Okay, so now you're aware.
We are going to be actively
looking for these cases.
Please do not make this mistake.
And this is sort of
a recipe for you
to avoid this
situation altogether.
Any questions?
Okay. Quick question for you.
How many of you actually
covered disk swapping in 2,200?
Is that most of you?
The majority of you covered
the disk swapping
algorithm, 2,200, right?
And so are you familiar
with the concept of
pushing a physical frame
to the disk, you know,
setting the appropriate bits in
the page table entry to
reflect that, right?
You're comfortable
with this? Sort of.
How far back was it?
Was it like last semester?
Was it a year ago,
two years ago?
So that means long time ago.
Okay. Okay, good. Thank you.
Yeah, I like that
kind of feedback.
So again, as I mentioned a few
times over the course of
this semester is that
sometimes we'll be coming back
to the algorithms
that are sort of
very familiar to you from
prior semesters, right?
But then we'll sort of start
asking philosophical
questions about it.
Like, why does this
happen the way it does?
You know, what sort of is
there a way to
conceptualize this?
You know, now that you've
learned some skills,
you actually have a
pretty heavy sort of
toolbox hanging
off to your side,
you know, attached
to your jeans.
And now you start asking
questions about tools.
Well, why should I use
this tool over that one?
And why is this tool shaped
this particular fashion, right?
And so let's try to do
that for the disc swapping
algorithm as well.
So let's see.
What's a good way to
start this? Oh, yeah.
And in the context
of this algorithm,
what's called the
clock algorithm,
we're also going to sort
of talk about those
two different things.
What are the mechanisms
that sort of enable
the clock algorithm to even
happen to be feasible,
to be possible, right?
And once you have this
set of mechanisms,
they're sort of your
hammers, right?
And then the question is, how do
you apply these mechanisms?
How do you enact a policy
is sort of an
orthogonal question.
Um because there's
a whole sequence,
a whole set of policies that you
can support and enable
with a set of mechanisms
that you provide.
So I will do my best sort
of in the context of
multiple places in this
course to actually
bring this to your attention
that there's this separation.
And that's fairly
important if you actually
decide to proceed with
doing systems research
in the future.
Okay. So let's see.
So one of, of course,
policy questions here, and
that's a policy question is,
how do we choose which
pages to evict, right?
You have a whole bunch
of physical frames.
These physical frames
are being occupied.
They're currently, you
know, holding some content,
and you need to
make up make space.
You know, what do you do? So one
of those frames needs to go.
What's the best way for us to
decide kind of which
page needs to go?
And we're going to discuss
sort of the best case and the
worst case of this, right?
I'm sure if well,
let me ask this as a question.
Which page do we need to
evict? How do you decide?
You've taken this
algorithm before, yes.
Fist What's Ahead
of the free list.
Okay. Anybody else? Yeah, yeah,
so it's something basically
by associative
thinking, you know,
almost like a large
language model, you know,
it sort of maps with a
very high probability
to this least recently
used keyword, right?
So you must have learned
at least recently used,
it's sort of a really
good heuristic
for you to deal
with that, right?
But then, you know, is it
the best possible policy, right?
And how far away from the
best possible policy?
What is the complexity
of this policy?
What are the overheads,
the memory overhead
associated with this policy?
The time compute overhead
associated with this policy.
Does anybody know Yeah,
so let's see if we can
get through this, right?
And of course, before we
get started with that,
just a reminder
from the last week
is our physical memory
limited by our RAM?
Well, it's not, right?
Because we talked about
oversubscription,
and we talked about the
ability to allocate
a lot more virtual memory
than physical memory.
And we also talked about
having the ability to map
other things into memory
than just your DRAM, right?
Files are very good
example of that, right?
So you can actually
have a portion of
your virtual memory where
you're mapping files.
And those files don't have
any physical frames
associated with that,
or do not necessarily have to
have physical frames
associated with that, right?
So the concept of swapping
is when you have to
save memory to disk
when we round out of
physical frames of memory.
So in other words,
you're basically
picking and choosing some tiles,
so to speak, behind
this memory mapped file
and swap them to disc.
In order to make space
for somebody else
who needs physical
frames right now.
And memory mapping is another
example, as I mentioned,
where we map file information
into the virtual address space,
and we basically anytime we
perform an IO
operation on sorry,
a memory read or write on
the virtual addresses to
which the file was mapped,
then these memory reads
and writes are going to
translate into writes
back to the file, okay?
They're not going
to translate into
writes to the physical
frames of memory,
they will translate
into file IO.
Make sense? Okay.
So how do we choose which
pages to evict to disc, right?
We're facing this necessity.
We need to make this decision.
Well, what is the ideal
page to evict to this?
So let's start thinking
about best case scenario.
If you sort of have
infinite resources
or you have infinite
amount of knowledge,
you know, would you proceed with
randomly choosing
physical frames to evict?
You know, would you like to
do it in a random fashion?
No, why not?
So if I were to
ask you literally,
I'm going to give you a
random eviction policy.
Like, how do you know
it's a bad design choice?
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly. So
there's actually
a an application is
accessing memory in a
specific pattern, right?
And there's a lot
of papers out there that
even try to learn what
this pattern is and even train
machine learning models in order
to identify the optimal
page eviction algorithm,
even use reinforcement learning
to come up with the policies for
page eviction as a function
of the memory access pattern.
The keyword here, all of
that is advanced stuff,
but the keyword here is
apparently memory
access pattern matters.
Thank you, right? Memory
So, great. Now that
we've established that,
you know, what sort
of an optimal space?
What sort of an
optimal scenario?
The best case, case is
that we actually know.
You have oracular knowledge of
what that access
pattern is, right?
And once you know
that, and you're
faced with the necessity
to evict a page,
which page would you evict
at a specific point in time?
Yeah. Is the longest
period of time.
Exactly. Basically,
you would have
the regular knowledge of
which pages are going
to be accessed, right?
And then given this information,
you will pick the page with
the least probability of
access in the near future,
which is the one that's furthest
away, there's actually a name.
It's actually an algorithm,
and there's a name
for this algorithm.
For anyone from
computer architecture,
you may recognize this as it?
At is algorithm, right?
So ultimately, and
the key here is
that you want to think
about trying to evict
pages that will be least useful
or the way to conceptualize
this is sort of
associating some sort of
utility with the page
and trying to evict
pages with the smallest
amount of utility.
And everything else sort of
becomes a detail, right?
Becomes a policy choice.
Well, how do we know
which pages are more
or less useful, right?
Well, one way to say
is that it's furthest
away from us if we
have that information.
Another way to tell is that, oh,
maybe it's the least
recently used,
and that becomes a
probabilistic decision, right?
It becomes a
probabilistic decision.
In this particular case,
though, it's Belts algorithm.
So, of course, we don't
know what the axis
pattern is going to be.
So what's commonly used is
the least recently
used approximation
or a heuristic in order
to approximate this,
in order to sort of
with high probability,
identify the physical frames
that are going to
be least useful.
But for those of you who
are thinkers, you know,
the second I said,
least useful, you know,
you can think of all sorts of
other ways to reason
about the utility of
using a particular frame,
like the arithmetic intensity or
the extent to which that
frame is going to be used.
Are we going to do only a
single read or
write to that page?
Is it a read or write, right?
Or are we going to hammer
it 1,000 times, right?
So that can also feed utility,
and you can all of a
sudden come up with a sort
of a very exponential
policy design space,
which makes it interesting.
But I don't want
to digress there.
Now, least recently used, fine.
Let's talk about
least recently used.
It's very expensive
to track, right?
So what do you
need in principle,
in order to be
able to enact the least
recently used policy?
What do we need
for that? What is
the necessary condition and
the information you need?
Yeah. The ordering
of the pages and
when they were access
like when they were used.
The ordering of
the pages, right.
So actually,
that's interesting that
you mentioned ordering.
Usually people say something
that's closely related to that,
but it's actually
semantically different.
Let's make it a little
bit more simple.
You probably want to know
the timestamp, right?
You want to know when it was
accessed in order to be
able to give you
this information.
But it's strictly more
expressive than the ordering.
And that's the
difference between
cardinal and ordinal ordering
because cardinal carries
more information.
But anyway, that's a nuance.
So ordering is actually
what you want.
But how do you even for
the purposes of order,
though, or timestamp,
it doesn't matter.
You need to somehow capture
this information on
every single access,
read or write, right?
So what's the problem with that?
Are we feeling good
about capturing
this information on every
single read or write?
So I once had a project
and it was a project on
a Mince CPU that
consisted of an eight by eight
mesh interconnect, right?
And I was hacking on the kernel,
and what I wanted it had
four memory controllers
along the perimeter,
and I wanted to figure out
what's the optimal
placement of a thread.
And the way I wanted to
figure this out is basically
which memory controller is
drawing its physical
frames from.
Where what is it
accessing in some sense?
And the reason for this is
because the way it was accessing
memory is actually by traversing
this mesh interconnect.
And so what mattered is
the Euclidean distance.
Sorry, is the
Manhattan distance.
Okay. And so, of course,
the first thing that comes
to mind is I started
trapping every single access
to the memory controller,
and it was not
a very performance system
as a result of that,
but it gave me the statistics.
So is that what we want to do?
Gave me the algorithm.
I published that paper,
but the system was unusable.
Why? Come on, guys. Yeah.
Yeah, too much overhead, right?
Like every single time,
even on a read, you actually
have to perform a write.
So every single access,
including reads,
turns into a write.
A write of the
metadata to capture,
this timestamp or ordering
information or a virtual
clock information,
right? That's super expensive.
We don't want to pay
that cost, right?
So what do we do instead, right?
Well, instead, we have to come
up with a different mechanism.
So here's an example.
Let's say we
have four frames of
memory top to bottom.
So the four different
color rectangles
are actually physical
frames of memory, okay?
And, and the number
written inside the rectangle is
actually essentially
the timestamp,
right, or the timestamp when
that page was last accessed.
So we have four physical
frames that were
already touched.
So we have one,
two, three, four,
and we have a current
access counter that's
standing at five.
You know, we can
think of it as a
virtual lampard clock, right.
And now we are sort of
accessing this page
right here and notice
how its access counter was
updated 3-5. Did you see that?
Okay, so we are updating it 3-5.
And we advanced the
access counter to six.
Okay, now we are
accessing the top frame,
and so we're going to update
its access counter or
timestamp point it was
accessed 2-6, right?
And the global access counter
is going to advance to seven.
And now the time comes to
evict and we know
exactly what to do.
We are going to evict
the least recently accessed
page in this particular case,
page with the access
counter one, right?
Pretty straightforward.
But as we mentioned,
there's a significant amount of
overhead to actually keep
track of this information.
And so, um
So basically doing this is
going to be a very bad thing.
The system becomes,
strictly speaking,
unusable. Can we do better?
You know, can we actually
think of the properties of
the least recently used
algorithm and come up
with a heuristic that
actually has much
better performance?
Because what's the worst
case performance here?
Paying for every
single access, right?
So basically your trap Well,
the worst case performance
here is with respect
to how many expensive operations
you need to perform, right?
I need to specify that.
And that is a trap.
How many traps are we paying
for actually enacting
this policy?
We are paying one
trap per axis, right?
You guys with me?
Okay, the question
is can we do it better, right?
You can improve the
algorithmic complexity.
Actually, the data structure
complexity that keeps track of
that from AN to
log end to A one,
but the overhead of actual
traps is not going to go away.
And that's a problem. So
instead, let's do this.
Let's try to approximate LRU
by essentially arranging
our physical frames
into a circular buffer.
So now our physical
frames are in a circle,
a clockwise circle, right?
And the numbers inside
those things actually
correspond to the frame number.
So let's see if I
get a pointer here.
Okay.
All right. So basically,
this is frame number one,
this is frame two, this is
frame three, this is frame four.
And we're going to have
sort of an axis bit
that will be sort of arbitrarily
set for each of those frames,
either to one or zero.
And this algorithm sort
of comes to life at
the time when we need
to perform an eviction.
So that means that we
need to frame five here,
and we need to place
it in lieu of one of
those four that you currently
see in the circular
buffer, okay?
So how do we do that?
Well, we start with
a pointer somewhere.
Now, the pointer, the
big arrow right here,
the big arrow is essentially
a version of our clock.
And as we rotate the arrow,
this is analogous to
monotonically increasing
the Lamport clock, okay?
Now, what are we doing
with the axis bit?
So we're checking
the current vertex
where the arrow is pointing,
and if A equals to one,
basically, we don't
touch that vertex.
We set A to zero,
and we proceed to point to
the next vertex in
the circular buffer.
In this particular case,
the axis bit is set to zero,
and that is going to
allow us to replace
two with the frame five and
evict frame number two.
And we're going to
set the axis bit to
one because remember that
this algorithm is actually
on acess to frame five that we
needed to swap in in order
to complete that
access operation.
And so by the time we are done,
we want our axis bit set to one.
Makes sense? Okay, so we've
completed the eviction.
We now evicted two,
and we replaced five.
And at this point
in time, you know,
it doesn't really
matter if we advance
the clock or we don't
advance the clock because we
know that the very beginning
of this algorithm is
checking for the axis
being one or zero, right?
So did that make sense?
Are you sure? No. Okay.
Do you have any questions?
So one question you might have
is how to make sure
that our access bit
is set to one when
we read a page
or write a page? Because
that's what we want.
Remember that the problem
we've identified is
that we pay too much
overhead on every single
access to memory.
We trap on every single access
to memory in the previous kind
of let's call it
naive implementation
of the algorithm, right?
In this algorithm, we
want to avoid that,
and we'll avoid
that if a read or
write is hitting a frame
with axis bit set to one.
So when that happens,
no trap takes place,
and the read or write operation
actually proceeds, okay?
So that's the way
to think about it.
So what we want to
accomplish is the common
case being simple,
the common case
being performant.
And the common case here is
basically when the axis
bit is set to one,
the page is sort of
frequently being used,
and it hasn't been
reset to zero,
back to zero by the
clock algorithm.
So given this clock algorithm,
the question then becomes,
precisely when do we trap?
And what's the
mechanism for us to
actually enable this
trap to make this trap
happen that actually resets
the clock resets it
from one back to zero.
When do I need to be
notified that a process
has access to page?
Right. We need to make sure
that we think through this,
like, is it every
single read or right?
That's the first thing to
get out of your way, right?
We've already established that
the answer to this is no.
And so we could
think about it from
the perspective of the
finite state automaton.
Basically, our aces bit can
be in two possible states.
Either it's in state zero or
it's in state one, right?
Okay, so now that we established
those two states in which
the access bit can be,
let's decompose
this step by step.
When the axis bit
is already set to
one on a read and write,
do we need to do anything?
The axis bit is
set to one, right?
The read or write can proceed.
This is essentially
this edge right here.
This is the state
transition edge 1-1.
So no trap should happen here.
Everybody agrees with
me. So axis bit is
one reading or writing
is going to stay one.
So that's the transition
edge to itself.
Okay? Now, there are two more
kind of transitions here.
What are those two more
transitions that are interesting?
State transition edges in
this two vertex graph.
Anyone? Yes.
One to zero and zero to one.
Yeah, 1-0 and 0-1, right?
Okay. And so let's talk
about one to zero.
So one to zero, when
does that happen?
It's this one right here.
I've just animated it.
This state transition 1-0.
When does that happen?
We saw it on the
previous slide. Yeah.
Yeah, it happens inside
the algorithm which
is running in your trap
handler already, right?
And so clearly, that's not
our mechanism to force
the trap to happen because
we're already inside
the trap handler.
So something else
must have caused it,
right? Well, what is it?
Well, the only
possible explanation
is this transition right here,
basically, the transition
from state zero to state one.
So that means that anytime
the axis bit is zero,
we want to design an algorithm
that sort of shadows
the axis bit zero and
forces our paging system
to give us a trap.
So that we get the opportunity
to set this axis bid
back to one and complete
the zero to one
state transition.
I don't know about you, but
I find this really exciting.
I sort of it really explains
what happens under the hood.
It explains precisely how to
design these mechanisms
that actually give you
the ability to interpose
on control flow
so that you can
actually implement
these mechanisms yourself.
Okay. And I just
walked you through
this thought process from
first principles
from ground zero,
how to come up with
this understanding
of what it means for us to
design this mechanism
to give us a trap.
Well, so what we've established
so far is that we need to have
a mechanism that gives a trap
on a state transition 0-1.
So what does that imply?
That implies and what are
our mechanismic bits?
We just have some
bits to deal with.
In this particular case,
we can use the present
bit and we can
make it shadow the
axis bit, okay?
Because the axis bit
is the logical bit.
But in order for us to enact
the physical permissions,
as we discussed during
the last lecture,
we need to use one of those bits
in the page table
entry itself, right?
So let's use the present
bit or PTE underscore P
to sort of shadow whatever
the axis bit is
currently set to.
So that means that if
the axis bit is zero,
we want to set the PTEP to zero.
And of course, if PTP is zero,
when we try to access the
frame that it's pointing to,
we're going to get
a trap, right?
So that's the mechanism
that we've just designed.
We can use PTEP to
shadow or whatever the
state of the axis bit is.
If it's zero, we set it to zero,
if it's one, we set
it to one, right?
And upon setting PTP to zero,
we're going to basically
get into the situation
where we're getting
a trap that gives
us the opportunity
to complete the state
transition 0-1.
By the clock algorithm.
Okay. And our invariant
here is, again,
by the time we are done
with the read right,
we want the axis bit to be one,
and we've accomplished that
with this mechanism as well.
It's sort of a
necessary condition
check mark that we need to have.
And it must be true for
this LRU approximation,
heuristic to work.
Okay. Let's see.
So here's a quick
complexity question.
Now, what have we done with
the worst case performance
of this clock algorithm?
So it used to be that we were
trapping on every single axis.
Now, what's the worst case?
How frequently can
we possibly trap?
And let's go back to
this so that you have
a visualization
that can help you
understand the worst case
performance of this algorithm.
And it's with respect with
the most expensive operation,
which is taking a trap.
Anyone? Yes. We're only chopping
when we get to evic
instead of every.
But let's say kind of a
little bit, you're right,
but a little bit more formally
kind of with respect to
either a number of axises or
the number of frames or
something like that.
It's order one.
It's sort of order N.
It's order something.
Oh, sorry, I didn't
see you, yeah. Zero.
Yeah, yeah. So is there
a possibility for
them all to be zero?
Is it possible?
I guess it would
be very unlikely,
but maybe potentially possible.
I guess you have to have
at least one or two frames
in memory, right?
Yeah, so it is, in
fact, possible,
and in the absolute worst case,
your clock algorithm is going to
cycle through the
entire buffer, right?
And so in this particular case,
the worst case is
that you're going
to be taking a trap on
every physical frame for
which the axis bit is
set to zero, right?
Because remember, our PTP
is shadowing aces bit.
And this is significantly
better than dealing with
the worst case that
we discussed for
the naive implementation where
it's every single
read or write, okay?
Okay. Um, yeah, I'm not
sure why I have it again.
So basically, I
think I demonstrated
here how the worst
case can happen.
Yeah, there we go.
Here's an illustration
of how the worst
case can happen.
So this is the initial state,
and it is possible, sort of as
a function of the
memory access patterns,
as you pointed out, right,
that our application is sort
of very memory intensive.
You know, it has
actually, you know,
performed a walk through all of
its physical frames or
the virtual memory that's
allocated to that
address, right?
And so all of our access
bits are set to one.
This is the worst possible
case that can happen, right?
And so now we start
looking for that page.
You know, we've run out of
memory. So this is set to one.
We must advance the clock.
This is set to one.
We set it to zero
advance the clock.
This is set to one, we set it
to zero advance the clock.
This is set to one. We set it
We're back to the beginning
and now we can evict.
So that's the worst
possible case.
Okay? So that just
animates this,
and then we finally
perform the eviction.
We put the physical frame
five instead of one
right here, right?
And we set the axis bit to one.
Right. And so one
additional thing
to mention here and it's
a little bit nuanced.
I'm going to try to sort of
go through this quickly.
This will only happen on
eviction. That's number one.
And number two, it's also
a combination of both
the memory pressure,
right, and the memory access
pattern of the application.
So if you were to actually
take the conditional
probability,
something like this is
highly unlikely to happen.
In other words,
it's unlikely for
all frames to actually
be marked as accessed in
the beginning and you being
in the eviction situation
at that point in time.
Okay. And so this seems like
a very worthwhile heuristic.
It seems like it
performs quite well.
So how do we choose
which pages to evict?
We've discussed the
clock algorithm.
We put pages in a circular list,
we mark them as access.
We have this logical access bit.
Anytime it's being
accessed, read or written.
And on evict the clock
iterates pages in the queue.
So our pointer is
essentially our monotonically
increasing virtual clock.
And if the page is accessed,
we mark it clean or
unaccessed by setting
the access bit to zero.
And if the page is
unaccessed we evict.
So that's sort of the
rundown or the summary
of the algorithm that we
just came to learn about.
Any questions about
the algorithm?
Okay, so let's talk
about concurrency.
The first question
to start with is,
you know, or interrupts
and concurrency, right?
How do we handle
unexpected events?
How do I get notified that
something new just
happened in my system?
Because remember that in our
on Neumann architecture,
you sort of have a flow
of instructions, right?
And if nothing happens,
nothing unexpected happens,
that flow of instruction
can just proceed as
scheduled, right?
And so what could
possibly happen that
actually interrupts those
that flow of instructions?
One example is
right there, right?
You start interacting keyboard
with keyboard, right?
You start getting
network packets.
Those are unexpected
events that cannot
be programmatically expected
by your program, right?
The fact that a
network arrived is
sort of completely unexpected
asynchronous event,
and you need to have mechanisms
to handle those events.
What is that mechanism?
The only way we have to deal
with something like that,
something that we didn't expect
is the interrupt mechanism.
Okay?
Now, what types of things
do we need interrupts for?
You know, what are some
of the use cases, right?
We already talked about
a couple of them, right?
We talked about
keyboard interrupts.
We talked about network data.
So I'm just going
to go through this
really quickly and then
we'll try to sort of categorize
this into a taxonomy, okay?
And so we've already
talked about paging,
in order for paging
mechanism to Would
paging mechanism work if
we didn't have interrupts?
Would it work? Can
we make it work?
No, right? We've been
talking about these
traps, you know,
as a mechanism for us to
actually interpose on
the control flow of
the application.
It would not work, right?
And so we are actually
depending on this mechanism of
exceptions in order to
implement the entire
paging system.
So interrupts are actually so
fundamental to everything we've
been talking about
up to this point.
As a matter of fact,
would scheduling
work if we didn't
have interrupts?
Are you even able to
switch between processes?
Right?
So we're talking about
timer interrupts, right?
And those are
hardware interrupts.
What happens if you have
a buffer overflow actually on
one of your device buffers?
If we didn't have interrupts,
would we be able to sort
of even assure the
correctness of
the applications that don't
give us an interrupt on
buffer overflows, right?
Debugging, right? When you're
interacting with the GDB,
you set a breakpoint somewhere,
and I don't know if you sort
of realize this or not,
but the reason why
the program actually
stops where you set
a breakpoint has
something to do with
receiving an interrupt, okay?
And so even though interrupts
may seem boring on the surface,
like, oh, it's just
an interrupt, right?
They're actually very,
very fundamental
mechanismic things that you
absolutely have to have in
the design of your system.
Communication and
interprocess interrupts.
In order for process A
to talk to process B,
you can send it interrupt
and actually deliver
a message that way.
Like in some sense,
you can think of sort of
the old school USPS, right,
where you raise a flag
when the mail arrived,
and I'm not even
going to mention
AOL because that's
even before my time.
But it had a similar kind of
icon where the mail
arrives and your red
flag goes up, right?
It's sort of an interrupt,
which serves as a
notification that
an unexpected asynchronous event
has occurred that
demands your attention.
And actually, that's
precisely captured, right?
An interrupt is an unexpected
asynchronous event
that occurred demands
your attention.
That's sort of almost by
definition what an interrupt is.
And it also gives us ability
to implement control features
like setting up watchdogs
in our system, right?
And to handle
catastrophic scenarios.
Like, for example, if, you
know, we're all human,
we make mistakes, even if
we are kernel developers,
we can make mistakes
in the kernel, right?
And when we make
mistakes in the kernel,
the kernel can get
into very, very,
very weird states
that are very, very,
very hard to debug, very
hard to get out of.
I'm sure some of you
may have noticed
that already, right?
If not, you absolutely will,
by the time you
get to Lab three,
which is all about
interrupts and concurrence.
And so you need to
have interrupts
that actually get you
out of that state.
And those are the non
maskable interrupts,
like basically pressing
the power button
that actually gives
you the ability
to essentially gracefully sat
down the system without
causing damage.
And this is a set of interrupts
that the kernel is
not allowed to mask,
is not allowed to disable,
not allowed to ignore.
Okay?
All right, so I mean,
I don't know if we have time
for thought experiment,
but for what it's worth,
can you imagine building
a keyboard driver
without interrupts?
So I just told you that
we need interrupts in
order to process keystrokes,
right? Is that true?
Can you interact with
the keyboard and your
operating system
still being able to I'm trying
to be very careful here,
receive the input you
have provided to the system
by using a keyboard.
Yeah, let me put it that way.
Yes. Could constantly
pull the keyboard
to see if there are new
keys yeah, exactly.
So this is a pull
versus push kind of a design
pattern in systems, right?
It's going to come up in
other places as well,
so you might I might as well
mention this now, right?
We rely on interrupts
in order for us to
sort of implement a push
based notification system.
So we use interrupts to push
a notification to
the operating system
to the kernel that,
Hey, I pressed, A,
pay attention to me, right?
Or we could pull
for this information from
an operating system.
I've got time right
now on my hands.
I'm going to see if anything
happened on my
device right there.
So let me look at it now.
Okay? So it is
actually possible,
but it's called polling,
and you would have
to keep checking
for the events that
happened, right?
In other words, you're not going
to handle them asynchronously.
You're going to actively
monitor those events
and potentially blocking for
them to actually arrive.
So what are the disadvantages
associated with that?
Why is it not something that
we actually do very quickly?
Yeah, you got to
keep checking even though
there might not be
something there.
Yeah, you don't know if there's
something there, right?
And so in a situation where
the interrupts or the exceptions
are actually infrequent,
you actually imposing
a lot of overhead,
as you correctly pointed out,
in order to keep checking for
something that
statistically may not be
there like 99 out of 100
times that you check, right?
So that's pretty
wasteful, right?
Um, and there are some
other disadvantages,
especially when
you think about it
as a mechanism for
handling device drivers.
So, you know, for
the sake for the sake of
this example, you know,
imagine you have
limited buffers on
the device driver and
you keep pressing
the strokes, right,
and the buffer starts
to fill up and you
no longer have space
to actually store
this information that
you're trying to provide
through the device driver.
Through the device, right?
And so what happens as
a result of this if you don't
have interrupts enabled,
is that the key strokes
may actually start to
disappear because
there's no more space
to put the keystrokes, right?
And so that's another
disadvantage.
One of the disadvantages at
a high level is a
performance disadvantage,
lots of overhead,
unnecessary overhead.
Another one is a
correctness disadvantage.
Performance correctness,
high level.
Okay. So every exception
interrupt is actually
assigned a vector.
So in XV six,
vector 14 is a
page fold handler,
and this is something
that you might have
seen in lab two.
Vector 32, this is going to be
famous in Lab three
because we need it for
scheduling implementation.
This is basically
our clock handler,
and of course, the
clock handler,
it gives us an ability to
actually contact switch
between processes,
and that's why it's super
important for the scheduler.
Okay? And when an
interrupt occurs,
the vector determines
what is the code for an
interrupt and it invokes
the handler in order to
handle the interrupt.
Here's my very brief taxonomy.
So you have interrupts,
and there's two different
kinds hardware and
software interrupts.
And for the software
interrupt that
usually corresponds to that
corresponds not usually,
that corresponds
to an instruction.
So those are also known
as internal interrupts,
something that only
the software sees
and they're not
generated by hardware.
Okay. And for example,
cis calls I implemented
using an inter structure.
And we have hardware interrupts
that also are of two types.
Some of them you
can ignore, some
of them you cannot ignore.
The ones that you cannot ignore,
I already mentioned are called
non maskba interrupts or Nimis.
And the maskb
interrupts are sort
of given to the system
using the INTR instruction.
So those are the ones
that come from hardware,
but we have the ability
to sort of enable or
disable receiving
those interrupts by setting
the IF bit in the
E flex register.
Okay.
So this sort of is
just a summary slide of
what I just said, okay?
Non mascub they
never get ignored.
You know, they're useful for
power failure, memory
corruption, error.
XV six actually has it.
You know, it has a way of hand.
It has an implementation of
non mascubin interrupts.
And this is basically,
if we get a non
mascub interrupt,
we give the kernel an
opportunity to gracefully die.
So actually vector two in X 86.
INTR corresponds to
mascuba interrupts,
and this is basically
when you can
ignore them by setting the
IF bit and Efflex to zero.
Okay.
And the enabling disabling
actually happens with
those instructions.
The assembly
instructions basically
set interrupt and clear.
So the STI sets the IF flag,
CLI clears the IF flag.
So that's basically
how you can ignore
interrupts that are maskable
inside your handler,
for instance.
Okay. Another question
is basically we have
this programmable
interrupt controller.
It looks like this.
It's a pretty outdated picture,
but nevertheless, it's a
variant of something like this.
The question is, how many pins
do we need to
allocate on a piece
of hardware that actually
gives us hardware
interrupts to the CPU?
Is it 16? Is it 32?
Is it 64? Is it 128?
Can we change it after
we ship the motherboard?
It's pretty hard
to change, right?
And so associating a
hardware interrupt with
every single one
of those pins is
probably not a very
good design decision.
Because if we want to
implement a new interrupt,
we sort of don't have
the capacity to do it.
You need to redesign a new pick.
You know, you need to
ship a new motherboard.
It's a pretty stupid
thing to do, right?
And so what do we do instead?
Instead, what we do is we take
a single pin on this programmable
interrupt controller,
and we sort of multiplex
all hardware interrupts
through a single pin.
So in other words, if
you receive, let's say,
a network Ethernet frame,
right, or any other kind
of hardware interrupt,
it's not going to go
directly to your CPU.
It first goes through
your programmable
interrupt controller.
Your PIC is the one that sort
of interposes on that first.
It detects that activity.
It recognizes the type
of a hardware interrupt
it has just trapped,
right, or it has just noticed.
And then it sends this interrupt
through one of the pins,
and I think it's
this pin right here,
pin number 17 called INT.
Two hour X 86 CPU,
as you can see in the bottom
right hand side of this slide.
Okay. And it delivers
both non mascubll interrupts and
maskeb hardware interrupts
in this fashion.
So clearly, this gives us
the ability to support
an arbitrary number of
hardware interrupts
without having to modify
the programmable
interrupt controller.
Okay? Okay, yeah.
And here I have basically
showing that the
17th pin here kind
of is the mechanism
that gets used
for us to deliver hardware
interrupts to Xe six CPU.
And then when it gets
to Xeight six CPU,
it gives us the ability
to handle that interrupt.
Okay, and how do we
handle those interrupts.
Software interrupts or
basically interrupts that
are kind of triggered
in software.
So this is not initiating
from any hardware in the system.
This is a piece of software that
explicitly decided to
raise the red light,
decided to raise the
exception in some sense,
the intentional interrupts
to the control tool.
Actually, it provides
the interstruption
for this purpose,
and it can invoke the interrupt
handler for the vector.
Vector is anywhere 0-5.
For example, for Titmva and it,
you have interrupt a number 64
or zero x 40 in order to
implement system calls.
That's the one
you're going to be
familiar with the
most in this class.
They have to be very careful how
you enter and leave
the interrupt and
the reason for this is
because it's a
privileged instruction.
Typically, I would leave
that the question.
Should we allow a user
space application to
just arbitrarily
issue interrupts
into our interact vector table.
Should should everything in
the interrupt vector table
be accessible for the
application to invoke?
Of course, the
answer is no. So how
do we prevent that
from happening?
Well, so we prevent that from
happening in a number of ways.
One of them is actually
detecting whether or not
the current privileged
privilege level matches
the descriptor
privilege level for
the descriptor in the
interrupt vector table.
Okay? And there's
actually a code in
XV six where the
interrupt vector table,
the IVT is set up,
and there's a macro that sets
up the descriptors in IVT,
and one of the flags
in that vector
is the GPL, descriptor
privilege level.
And basically, we check for
the GPL to make sure if we
should allow or disallow the
trap to actually preceed.
In addition to this,
we also need to
save some state in order for
us to actually again,
I could also phrase
it as a question.
Do we want to handle the
interrupt on the user's stack?
So remember that we
took an interrupt.
You have some state. This state
is captured by a
set of registers.
There's no magic here,
or rather it is magic,
but the magic is captured by
the set of registers, right?
And one of those
registers is ESP,
our stack pointer, another
register is SS, right?
Our stack segment register.
And we've just captured
an interrupt and they are
set to the user space
kernel context.
Do we want to proceed
with handling
this interrupt on
the user stack?
The answer is no, right?
So we don't want to do that.
We actually want to swap out
the user's stack or move
away rather from user stack
into the kernel stack,
save all of that state, and come
back to that state on the RT.
So the implementation of IRT is
basically it basically involves
restoring all of the
user space state that
we had when we received an
interrupt in the first place.
So let me see if Oh,
it's actually in
the next slide.
Perfect. Right here.
As long as it takes.
I can get through this now
or you can go through
this on your own.
But basically, it captures
in its entirety what
happens when you receive an
instruction in the kernel.
It has the following steps.
You decide the vector number
because that gives you
essentially an index
into IVT, okay?
As part of for example,
in a zero x 40 zerox
40 instruction
with zero x 40, that
would be the number.
Then you fetch the
interrupt descriptor from
IVT for this vector
number, right?
IGT stands for Interrupt
descriptor table.
How do I remember this?
The CPU finds it by taking
the eight byte entry,
starting at the
physical address that
the IDTRCPURgister points to.
Then what I mentioned is
that you got to make sure
that you check that your
current privilege level,
remember those rings
of protection, right?
They come in and
play here again.
It's a very concrete use case
for using the rings
of protection.
You check that your
current privilege level is
less than equal to
the descriptor
privilege level in
the descriptor that you've
just fetched from IDT, right?
Then you save the
stack pointer and
the stack segment in a
CPU internal register,
and then you load this point,
the new stack pointer and
the stack segment from TSS,
which is a special
table where you save
this kernel stack information.
Okay? So now you are no longer
on user space on user stack,
you are now on Kernel stack.
And then you push the
user stack information,
which is the SS and ESP,
you push the E flag which is
your control flag register,
and you push CS and EIP, right?
You basically push the
state for the user,
you clear some EFLx
because now you're in
kernel space and right before
you get into the handler.
And finally, how do you
get to the handler?
You set the CS and EIP that are
stored in the interrupt
descriptor table,
descriptor, okay?
You now set the CSE
and EIP and you jump,
and now you're in
the handler code.
So it seems quite involved,
but at a high level, you know,
if you didn't follow
that, that's okay, okay?
Because here's the high level.
The high level is this.
You figure out, what
is the interrupt number
that I'm getting.
Then you check. Is it okay
for me to run this interrupt?
Then you switch stacks.
So all of these pushes
and yada, yada,
you know, this is all about
switching stacks, okay?
And because you don't want
to perform handling
on the user stack.
Then you set up
registers by saving them
and making changes
to the E flex bits,
and then you finally jump to
the kernel handler by setting
the CSIP because CSIP is
a code segment,
instruction pointer,
pair that controls
which instruction
is going to be executed next,
and you get the CSIP pair
from the IDT descriptor,
from interrupt descriptor
table descriptor.
And that is how you get
into the handler code.
Okay? So this is the trap frame.
I already showed you
this slide before.
Basically this is how we define
interrupts for cis calls.
Okay? It's a macro that's
defined and uses DRS.
And yeah, here's where the
interrupt is actually
being invoked.
It's being invoked with
a T on the score ciscol
which is the zero x 40 that
I keep talking about, right?
Okay. And IRT is what
you call when you try to
return from the handler,
and that attempts to restore
the user space stack
before it hands
control back to the
user space process.
Okay.
And yeah, we can stop here.
This is basically how the
IDT is set up on TV Nt.
And you can see that the
only place where the user
can actually access the handler
is for
A
Okay.