Yeah.
I have no idea
um, All right.
Let's go ahead and get started.
We have a ton of material
to blast through.
So today we're supposed to be
talking about user
and kernel threads.
And basically, how do
you create, organize,
and manage userspace threads,
and we have different design
choices, Associated with that.
Before I get into the
user and kernel threads,
I wanted to finish something
from the previous lecture,
we're going to get to
that right after going
through a couple of
slides of administratvia.
Okay? So first and foremost,
lab three has now been released.
So, believe it or not, you guys
are you're done with lab two.
You only have two
labs remaining.
This lab is the biggest
lab, however, right?
So please do start early.
I wanted to say a few things
about the timeline
associated with this lab.
This lab is going to
consist of multiple parts.
It's a multi part lab.
The first part is on scheduling,
and then the rest
of it kind of has
to do with the threading
library implementation,
which we're also going to
talk about in this lecture.
This is not a coincidence, okay?
Okay, so the timeline
is that you do have
five weeks allocated for
lab three, calendar weeks.
So if you look at the schedule,
you will see that you
can count to five.
There are five weeks indeed
allocated to lab three,
it may seem like
quite a bit of time.
However, one of those
weeks is a spring break.
And, you know, we want
to make sure we do
not impose on your
spring break too much.
Of course, it's
entirely your choice
what you do with your
spring break, right?
But we wanted to make sure that
we don't count that one week
into the amount of
time we think you
have for the purposes of
completing your lab three.
So you now have four.
Okay? Another week, we also
have a midterm between now and
the time lab three is due,
so you need to have some
time to prepare for that.
I'm saying one week
of midterm prep.
Having said that, I do encourage
you to actually start
early and start
even as early as
this week and get
through the slides, get
through the videos.
There's a lot of video material
out there on the media gallery.
And so that you're well prepared
for the kinds of
midterm exam questions
we're going to ask.
They are going to be quite
different from your labs.
So the questions we're
going to ask will
be primarily conceptual
slash design,
slash system
architecture questions,
the thinking kinds of questions,
where we'll be asking you about
trade offs associated with
various design choices,
as we have been doing over
the course of all of
these lectures that
you guys went to.
So I just wanted to be
explicit about this
that it will be
different from the lab
assignments you've done, okay?
And so it does take
some time to do
some midterm preparation in
addition to the time you're
investing in your labs.
So that leaves us with
three weeks, right?
And that's the same amount
of time you had
for your lab two.
How well did your lab two go
if you didn't start
early, right?
Well, was there an answer?
How did it go? Yeah.
I mean, I literally
spoke with a handful of
students who didn't start
until three days
before the deadline,
and this has multiple
implications.
It's going to create a
lot of stress on you,
it's going to also
create a lot of
stress on the TAs,
but especially you,
and you may end
up in a situation
where you're so
stressed that you
make decisions you would
not have made otherwise.
And we do watch out for
those things, right?
So please make sure
this doesn't happen.
The best way to
proactively avoid all of
these stressful situations is if
you start early enough set.
We're trying to help you
as much as possible.
One of the ways we're
trying to help you with
Lab three is we
created a midpoint,
I guess, a halfway
checkpoint, okay?
And what is this
halfway checkpoint?
It's due on March 14, yes.
This is Pi day,
so easy to remember.
March 14 is basically
what we're looking
for is for you to get through
parts one and two of the lab.
And this will correspond
to the first 21 tests.
And so, basically,
what's going to
happen is that we're
going to give you six
bonus points, right?
This is going to
count as a bonus on
top of your lab
three assignment.
And we will weigh these six
points by the fraction of
the tests one through
21 that you have completed
by the deadline,
by the checkpoint deadline.
Does that make sense? So
it's not an all or nothing.
You can get partial
bonus credit,
and that's going to depend
on how many tests you've
completed in this range, okay?
And I can guarantee you that
people will be saying, Oh,
I actually completed more
tests in this range. Okay?
So if you complete
seven tests out of
this range, it's
seven out of 21.
One third times six
is how many points?
Two points, okay?
Even if you completed the
rest of the tests after 21,
you're more than
welcome to do that,
but that's not going
to count towards
your checkpoint
bonus points, right?
So that's kind of how we
are structurally trying
to help you get
through this lab.
And the checkpoint,
not coincidentally,
is going to be due Friday
before your spring break.
So just for all
practical purposes,
aim for that checkpoint as
your lab deadline,
and you will be fine.
Okay. So this year is different.
We actually changed
the auto grader to
calculate the score for you
so that there's no confusion,
right, and there's no manual
calculation involved.
The autograder is going to
calculate the checkpoint
score for you,
and it will be logged as part
of every submission
that you make.
Okay? Then we're going to
extract this information,
and we're going to port
it over to Canvas as
your checkpoint score.
Does that make sense?
Alright, I do want to go
quickly through this.
Oh, I forgot.
This is not the only bonus that
you get on lab three, right?
There's also a custom
schedule design question.
How could we not have
a custom scheduling design
question in this class, right?
Try to outperform
the stock schedulers
that you will be implementing
as part of the lab.
And if you're successful
at doing that,
refer for details to the SPAC.
You're also going to get
an additional bonus opportunity
with the custom
scheduler design write.
It's not due for the checkpoint.
You can do that later.
You can submit it
at the very end of
your lab because we don't
want to spend your time on
the bonus before you've
completed the entire lab.
Does that make sense?
Alright. Exam, people
have started asking for an exam.
I think of it as a good sign.
So for this section,
my section, Section C,
we are going to have
an exam on Tuesday,
March 11 at this time
in this location.
Is that clear? If you're
going to show up somewhere
else, please do not blame me.
This section,
Section C, Tuesday,
March 11 2250 in this
location at this time.
It will be an in class exam.
It will be administered
on Canvas.
It will be proctored. Please
bring your bus cards.
They will be checked
because we don't
want people from another
section to show up.
Okay? So go to the
section that you're in.
Even if you're collaborating
with a partner from
another section for the purposes
of your labs, that
doesn't matter.
You're registered
for the section,
you show up for this
section to take an exam.
I think I've belabored
that point quite a bit.
Topic coverage, everything
up to and excluding
security is going to be up
for grabs for Exam one.
This includes, but
is not limited
to I'm trying to be
legal here because I know that
someone is going to pick it up.
Isolation and protection,
kernel organization,
virtual memory management,
interrupts and concurrency
and scheduling.
We just went over that over
the course of the
past week, right?
User and kernel threading,
we're covering that today,
and OS and networking,
we're planning to cover
that on Thursday.
And what we will be testing,
again, is not your
lab knowledge.
What we will be testing is
the lecture material and
the content that
we will be asking
thinking design
questions on the exam.
The best way to
prepare for that is to
go back and study the
lecture material.
Okay. And so now before we
start talking about threading,
I want to go back and
give me a second.
I want to go back
and finish something
that we discussed during
the previous lecture
because this actually sets
up the context really nicely
for this lecture today.
Okay? So remember this?
This is where we
ended up. We sort of
went through where you
want to place your signal.
We established how
this combination of
signal and weight happens
actually creates and
reinforces a happens before
relationship between
the producer
and the consumer,
which is what we want.
That's where we stop. Okay?
Now, the next thing that
I wanted to talk about
is what is the mechanism for
waiting in the first place?
So we've established that
we want to be able to wait.
Wait is a nice primitive
to have, okay?
But then how do we wait?
What's the mechanism
for waiting?
And maybe let's start
asking some questions.
Well, do you expect the
user space application
or the kernel to
switch the processes?
So who's going to
switch the processes,
the user space or the kernel?
Yes. The kernel.
And why is that?
Access to everything.
Because this is something
that you think is
going to require some
privileged tactics, right?
Okay. And so how
do we handle the switches
within the kernel, right?
And more generally, how do
we put processes to sleep?
So you may find it
counterintuitive,
and at least I did when
I was first going
through this material.
But it's interesting
to note that
a process cannot actually
put itself to sleep.
Like, you think that this is
a very trivial operation.
You just call sleep, right?
You know, What's the problem.
But the user space
application actually is
completely unable to go to
sleep without Kernel's help.
It's a very, very simple
primitive, sleep, right?
You cannot do that without
the kernel. Very
interesting, right?
And then once we'll get to that.
And then once we
talk about this,
how do we wake up the
sleeping process is?
Sort of what's the
mechanism for that, right?
So one way to sort of
implement sleeping is Sorry,
hold on. What happens?
Yeah, what happens? We will
also talk about what happens on
the CPU when the process
waits for another.
And can we use the CPU more
productively in the meantime?
Because the simplest
possible thing to
do when you're
waiting in a sleep is
to basically just sleep
and maintain the context
that you've established,
maintain all the data
locality, the entire context.
I'm just going to be very
general here instead
of swapping out the context
and switching to another
threat of execution, right?
But is this the efficient way
of using the CPU when
you're sleeping?
In the interest of
time, you know,
normally I would give
you an opportunity to
give me the obvious answers
to the obvious questions, right?
But in the interest
of time, clearly,
this is not a very
productive way
of using the CPU, right?
We probably want to do
something else, right?
We probably want to switch
the control and the residency
of the CPU to another
running process
while the previous
process sleeps, right?
So that means it
seems obvious, right?
Of course, you want
to do that, right?
But did you think about
the implications of this?
There's even such a
minor thing like this,
whether or not we're sleeping on
a CPU and occupying
the CPU while
we sleep or we switch to
another process actually
creates a trade off.
What is the trade off?
Yeah. Headed, switching
to another process.
Yeah, there's some overhead
associated with the operation
of switching itself, right?
You need to save the context
of the process you're switching
from and restore the context
of the process you're
switching to, right?
And that overhead
is non negligible.
And there are some
additional latent issues
associated with
switching between
the processes. What are they?
Let's just recall what they are.
Because these are the kinds of
questions that you guys are
going to be getting on the test.
So I'm trying to
really get you into
this mind set of
thinking about things a little
bit more philosophical,
a little bit more conceptual.
So other than the
contact switch,
what else what else are
we paying for this?
We need to when the process
that we put to sleep
wakes back up,
then either it has to
wait for the process
that's currently on
the CBU to exit or we have
to preempt that process,
which adds more complexity
to our implementation.
Now, when we're in the
sleep Cisco, basically,
we're putting the
proc one to sleep,
and so we don't have
to go back to that.
But what I'm trying to
get to here, right?
Was there another
somewhere here?
There was another cost, yes.
Yeah, basically, you're going
to lose all the caches, right?
And the TLB flush,
you're going to load the entire
virtual memory address space
for the destination process
you're switching to, right?
Flushing the TLB and the
data locality and so forth.
All of that is going
out of the window.
So now that I've spoken
through all of this,
do we really want to
switch between processes,
right? In the kernel?
Or do we want to
try to avoid that?
And we're going to be talking
about this and how we actually
achieve hopefully the best
of both worlds by the
end of this lecture.
And God help me. We
have so little time.
And I should mention
one thing, okay?
You guys may be unaware of this,
but this is the first
time where this class
was switched to a 50
minute time slot,
and it's crazy because
the amount of material I
have was even more than an hour
and 15 minutes I had earlier.
And so I'm trying to go through
this material as fast as I
can, but at the same time,
I don't want to give up on
the quality of teaching,
and I want to engage
you in the process
interactively as we kind
of go through these
concepts together.
And so it's a very,
very challenging
kind of semester for
the instructors.
Okay, so we need to figure
out what needs to be saved
when we are sleeping, right?
So let's just go through that.
We need to save the
user address space
because as we
previously mentioned,
and I think you mentioned
here on the right hand side,
right, we're switching
address spaces.
We need to save user context.
What am I referring to?
What is our mechanism
for actually
capturing the context of
the processes universe?
It's the set of
registers, right?
We have this nice mechanism
of the set of registers
that captures that.
Then we also need to save
the kernel address space and
the kernel context
in addition to
that. How do we save them?
Well, let's go through
this very simple example
of a shell, calling
another process.
Let's say cat, right?
So we have a shell right
here in user space,
and we have a cat right
here in user space.
The red line is the user
space kernel space divide,
and let's see what's
happening in the kernel.
Boom, the first thing that
happens is that you need
to save user context.
That's when you're calling
into the kernel context
associated with
the process shell.
That's the first
user context save.
What happens after that
is so now we're in
the kernel context associated
with the process shell.
We're calling a switch function,
which is responsible for
saving the kernel context for
shell before we get
into the kernel context
for the scheduler.
That's another context switch.
Now we are on the
scheduler stack
inside the kernel. Okay.
We're on the scheduler
stack inside the kernel.
I'm being very deliberate
with my words.
Okay. After that, the switch
is going to be called
again when the scheduler
decides to run the next
process in the runable Q.
Let's just say that
the next process
in the runable Q is
the CAT process.
So what it's going to do
on switch is it's going to
load the kernel context for
the destination process,
in this case, CAT.
It's not switching right away.
Once it's done
that, we are still
inside the kernel on
the CAT's kernel stack.
And finally, we're going to load
the user contacts before we
hand the control to
the CAT process.
How many contact
switches have we made?
Yeah.
Four. Okay. Can you
enumerate them?
First is from user space to
kernel space when we go from
Shell to its kernel staff.
Sorry, can you speak up.
The first is from user space to
kernel space move to
its kernel stack.
The next is when you switch to
the kernel stack of the
scheduler. Right. That's two.
When you switch to
the kernel stack of
CAT the last one
is when you switch back
to the user stack?
Yeah, four contact switches,
right? That's insane.
You thought there was
only one. There are
actually four contact
switches here.
Now, granted, they're
actually fairly
lightweight, but
still, nevertheless,
four contact switches is
a lot and there are
some additional latent,
as we mentioned, disadvantages
associated with the contact
switch every single time.
Right? So what do we need to
save when we're sleeping?
As I mentioned, address space?
That's saved in the Px
page directory, right?
That's going to
be taken care of.
Now, user context,
that's going to be saved
on a call to the kernel.
So as we saw on the
previous slide, right here,
the user context is
going to be saved as we
are calling into the kernel
from the user space, okay?
It's going to be saved
there. The kernel context
is the one that's tricky.
The kernel context
right here is going to
have to be switched
saved explicitly.
Right? When we're going
from one kernel stack to
another kernel stack,
we have to make sure that we are
switching those kernel
contexts explicitly.
And I will show you how
elegant the mechanism
is for this.
And sort of it
didn't really blow
my mind because it all
made sense, right?
But it's still very
elegant to go through.
And this happens inside
the switch function.
So what does the
switch function?
Have you guys seen the
switch function right now?
Has anyone looked at
the switch function?
Do you know what language
it is written in?
Yeah, the switch function
is assembly, right?
And before I show
you the assembly,
maybe let's kind of
walk through what it's
supposed to be doing.
So it takes two
context structures.
It pushes all the C. So think
of the context switch as,
you know, an edge, right,
from A to B and A is the old,
B is the new, right?
And so the Cole is the A vertex,
and the collar is sorry,
the Cole is the B vertex,
the color is the A vertex.
So we push all the Cole saved
registers to the first,
then we swap the new stack
from the contact structure.
We pop all the cole saved
registers from the new stack,
and then we return.
So let's just look at
the assembly code for
the switch function.
So it's beautiful, okay?
Because we have two arguments
on the stack right here.
So on line 11, right here,
what we're doing is we're
taking the first four
bytes off the stack,
which corresponds to the pointer
to the old context, okay?
And we're loading into
the EAX register.
Then we're taking the second
four bytes off the stack,
okay, off the stack, right?
And we're saving this
into the EDX register.
And this is a memory address
associated with the new context.
So now EAX is a memory
pointer to the old context.
EDX is a memory pointer
to the new context.
Okay? Now, what
we're doing is we're
going to save the
Colley saved registers.
There's four of them,
the EBP EBX ESI EDI.
Okay? And here's where
the magic happens.
Two assembly line instructions
on lines 21 and 22 is
what switches the stacks
between the kernel
contexts. It's beautiful.
We're moving the kernel
stack pointer into
the memory address pointed to
by EAX register, which is old.
That means we're saving
the kernel the
current stack pointer
into the old structure.
And the next line on line 22 is
basically moving whatever
was pointed to by EDX,
which is the new contact
structure into the ESP register,
which essentially
replaces the stack.
And that's it. So now
basically we've
conceptually been
discussing how you need
to switch the stacks,
how you need to
switch the contexts.
You're looking at these two
assembly line instructions.
You've just switched the stacks.
Alright. Well, there's
some additional
elegancy that happens,
which in retrospect is obvious.
We're popping now that now
starting at Line 20 well,
right after Line
22, whatever it is,
right, we're actually on
the new stack on the destination
stack on the Cole stack.
And we're going to
pop from that stack,
the Cole destination,
new stack being very
deliberate, very precise.
Everything in reverse
of push, right?
So we pushed EBP EBX, ESI,
EGI, we're going to pop
EGI, ESI, EBX, EBP.
Make sense? And you're
done with switch.
That's how the kernel contacts
are going to be switched.
All right. Any
questions about this?
Yeah. What in doing sorry.
Lines 11 and 12.
Yeah, they're taking
the top element from the
stack of the current stack,
and they're moving it to EAX.
And what you pushed
on the stack,
basically you're
calling this switch
function with two pointers.
So basically, this right
here is actually taking the
top four bytes of the stack,
which corresponds to the
pointer pointing to
the old context.
Yeah, where the old
context will be saved.
Before you call switch,
you push those two guys?
No, no, you're going to call
switch with those arguments.
And the arguments
are going to be
saved on top of the stack.
All over.
Yeah. So the implementation
of a function call with
arguments in assembly is
that it's going to push the
arguments on the stack.
Okay. You guys covered
that in 2,200.
All right. All right.
Any other questions?
Now, what does this
have to do with
user and kernel
threading, right?
Okay. So let's switch
to user and kernel threading
now because I gave
you this context,
and you guys will be able
to appreciate why this
is important as we discuss
user and kernel threading.
Okay.
So why do we want threading?
This is supposed to be a
general discussion, right?
Because, clearly, as with
anything in systems,
when you introduce sort
of a new mechanism,
and threading is a
mechanism of something,
we're going to get to that, you
have some complexity
associated with that.
So can we live in a
world without threats?
Come on, guys, help me out
here. Why do we need threats?
Yes. Like, graphics, maybe
you separate threads.
What's that? Se graphics
graphics or something. Okay.
But why do it on
separate threads?
Can't you do it in
a single thread?
In a single process. So you
can always serialize any kind
of parallel computation, right?
Yeah.
Yeah. You can always
impose an order on whatever
parallel computation
you're doing.
So you could do
everything you're
doing in parallel
sequential, right?
So why do we need threads?
Yes. I net holping stuff.
We talk about fiming out, you're
waiting for one thing to go,
and then there's another
timer's running on
another thread.
I see. Very high level rig.
Okay. Okay. So basically,
you're providing
a use case where
threading could be
useful because you can
wait on a thread on
some socket that's waiting
for some network
activity, right?
And what you're yes.
Threading is useful for,
like, IO scenario. Uh huh.
So imagine like you had
a graph users track
you just had a single
thread of execution,
maybe there's some does
something this semester class.
Right, so what you're implying
here is that we actually
want threading for
performance, right?
So in many cases, you're
actually going to get
some performance benefits by
either executing
something in parallel,
as you mentioned, right,
because you can
actually split it up
into multiple threads
of execution.
All of a sudden,
instead of serializing
this in a single
sequential stream,
that was one use case, right?
So you're getting
performance out of that.
Yes, there's a raised
hand at the back.
So, I actually think it also
provides more modular in.
Yeah, so there are also
software engineering kind
of principles associated
with threading, right?
It basically helps you
kind of modularize
your code a little
bit so that you
can reason about
it better, right?
Because, for example, if there's
some unrelated activity that
has to do with UI, right,
you probably just
want to put it in
a separate thread
and not have to
intertwine these
heterogeneous blocks
of code in the same sequence
of instructions, right?
So that's another benefit,
and that doesn't have anything
to do with performance.
And as a matter of
fact, if I had time,
I would tell most stories,
for example, we use
threads forever.
We used threads way before 2004
when Moore's law
became a problem
when we actually had multi
process or systems, right?
So threading actually
helps even when you
have a single core, right?
So there must be some
advantages associated with
threading other than just
trying to run
things in parallel.
Um, so we can get
performance with multiprocessing,
right? We don't.
And in addition to
this, we can also
get performance with
multiprocessing.
So even if we do
make an argument for
threads that's rooted in
extracting more
performance out of them,
you could have achieved
that with just
using multiprocessing
system, right?
What's wrong with that? And as
a matter of fact,
even more generally,
here there's this whole
design space exploration,
and in fact, papers written
about these trade offs
between threading versus
multiprocessing
versus event based.
Those are all the
different ways in
which you can
approach something,
in which you can
achieve something.
And the question is,
what is that something?
Yes. Have a lot of
print and also maybe not have
so much shared state
or Shared state.
Okay, good, good. So now,
he's talking about
properties now.
We've gone through the use
cases, which is great.
Now, out of those
use cases, right,
as we start thinking about
design space exploration,
we are starting to think
about properties, right?
And so he mentioned one thing,
right, which is
sharing resources.
So in a multiprocessing system,
you are by design,
kind of creating a
separate address space
for every single process
in the system, right?
And that's what you wanted.
We were talking about
this from the very beginning
of the class. It gives you a
It gives you this notion
of being by yourself in
the system gives you isolation
and protection, right?
But threading actually very
actively breaks that and says,
I don't want you
isolation and protection.
By design, I actually want
to share the resources.
And the reason for this
is because it is more
performant than doing this
in a multiprocessing
fashion, right?
So it actually strikes
a different balance in
this trade off space.
What is that trade off space?
Isolation, performance,
two axis, right?
So if I were to ask you this
question about something as
trivial as the difference
between threading
and multiprocessing,
I encourage you to
think about what trade
off space is induced by
these two design
choices and what kind
of point they strike
in this design choice.
So threading, you can get
more performance because you're
sharing resources, right?
But you get less isolation.
And there's an additional
complexity cost
associated with that,
because now you need to
worry about concurrence.
Okay. And we're
not even going to
get into the event based
systems because you can
actually implement an
event based system
in a single process
on a single thread.
But what's interesting
is that all three of
these different design
choices give you the ability,
give you the abstraction
of concurrency.
So threading gives you
the abstraction here.
That's what I'm trying
to get to, which
is different from parallelism.
And we're going to get to that.
There's a lot of confusion
that usually arises when
people try to conflate
concurrency and parallelism.
We're going to try
to define both of
those by the end of this class.
Right now, at this
point in time,
I want you to remember
that threading is
a mechanism that enables the
abstraction of concurrence.
Okay, so we talked
about the benefits.
I'm going to just blast
through them in the
interest of time.
You get threading does enable
paralysm and it does that
with shared memory resources.
Threading gives
us an abstraction
to share a resource
like the address space.
And it's a way to multi process
or manage concurrency with
shared memory resources.
There are some challenges and it
doesn't introduces,
so it's not for free.
Like one of the challenges is
actually synchronization,
as I discussed.
So what is even a thread, right?
Let's see. We'll actually
get to the definition
of a thread
probably on the next slide.
So let's just skip the top
of this slide in the
interest of time.
There are some additional
benefits to threading, right?
I talked about and
encouraged you to think,
what happens if we only
have a single core?
So we used threads
even way before 2004.
We can use threads
very effectively,
even when there's a single
kind of physical core,
and we can get
both performance benefits and
non performance benefits
associated with threading.
Okay. Organization,
as someone mentioned,
basically, and the ability to
process asynchronous events is
one of the benefits
of threading.
It has nothing to do
with performance, right?
One of the use cases here
is having a UI thread
and a background process
that runs simultaneously.
So it gives us the ability to
achieve this notion
of simultaneity.
It provides us with
the abstraction of
concurrency
simultaneity of action.
And what do I mean
by concurrency?
What I mean by concurrency is
this basically illusion
of the ability to
make progress on multiple
simultaneous threads
of execution at
exactly the same time.
Okay? So in other words,
you have multiple
threads of Well,
I probably don't want to
multiple streams of execution.
Let me use a different word
so that you don't confuse
it with threading.
You have multiple
streams of execution,
and we have the ability
to actually make
progress on all of those
streams at the same time.
So that's what
concurrency implies.
And so the abstraction
of concurrency,
as is the case for every
single abstraction
we introduced in this class,
you know, there are
mechanisms that
enable those abstractions, okay?
So there's this
relationship between
an abstraction and
a mechanism, right?
The mechanism enable
abstractions.
One of those mechanisms
is threading.
Okay. So threading is
a mechanism mechanism of
what? Let's just recap this.
It's a mechanism for enabling
the abstraction of concurrency.
What is concurrency?
It's the ability to
seamlessly execute
independent streams of
execution at the same time.
Are there other
ways of doing that?
In other words, are there some
other mechanisms
for concurrency?
Yes, other than threads,
we also have multiprocessing
and event based systems.
And interestingly enough,
event based systems are so
lightweight that they sometimes
outperform the other two.
Yeah, no time for anecdotes.
Okay. But I've
implemented one of
those systems in the past
when I was a postdoc
at Berkeley.
It was a very highly
performed system.
What's also interesting with
event based systems,
if we had time,
we'd talk more about
this is that it's
a voluntary
preemptive mechanism.
So the takeaway here
is that using threads,
we actually gain a convenient
abstraction of concurrency.
Okay. And this kind
of breaks it down
what the advantages and
disadvantages or the properties
of each of the mechanism are,
each of the three mechanisms
of concurrency are.
Multiprocessing, what is it?
Processes that share
compute resources,
but not memory resources.
The key property
that's guaranteed here
by design is the memory
space isolation.
Threads, they ask this
disruptive question.
I don't want the
isolation guarantees that
are provided to me by the
multi processing system.
What happens if I break
this isolation guarantee
deliberately by design, right?
And so, therefore,
the key property of
the threading system
or threads in general,
is that they do share
memory resources by design.
And event based systems,
they are implemented
on a single process,
single thread, and they're
voluntarily preemptive.
So basically, the
way this works is
that you're executing
events one at a time.
As soon as you've
completed executing
an event that was added
to the event loop,
you kind of move on
to the next event in
the sequence that was added
on the event loop, right?
And so it's voluntarily
preemptive.
There are a couple of
definitions you will find in
literature for what
the thread is, right?
The first one says Thread of
execution is the
smallest sequence of
programmed instructions
that can be
managed independently
by a scheduler.
So that's interesting.
Why is it interesting?
Because they're
thinking of a thread
as a block of execution
at the granularity that is
visible to the scheduler, right?
And it connects to what we
want to talk about next, right?
The second definition here
is that what's a thread?
A thread is also
sometimes called
a lightweight process
or LWP in Linux, right?
Is a basic unit of
CPU utilization.
And then sort of it moves on to
say that it consists
of a thread ID,
a program counter, a
register set, and a stack.
So it's useful, right,
because it kind of becomes
very prescriptive about how
to implement the mechanism of
threading in an
operating system.
But at the same time, it is
an implementation detail, right?
It has its own program
counter, which is useful.
It has its own register stack,
which is useful and register
set and its own stack.
Okay. Any questions so far?
I'm going pretty
fast through this.
Okay. So the main property of
threads is the fact that it
shares memory with
another thread, right?
And you already knew
that from 2,200.
What we did here is
we just explored
the design space and kind of
conceptualized that it's a
mechanism of concurrency
as an abstraction that
you want to be able
to provide as an
operating system.
Okay, some of the other benefits
we discussed is that
responsiveness,
right, especially when you
have an interactive application.
And this is actually rooted
fundamentally within the
abstraction of concurrency.
If you have an activity,
an application level activity,
like interacting with
the user, right?
And you want it to be
interactive, naturally,
you wanted to make progress
in conjunction with
all the other activities
that are happening in
the application, right?
Which means that naturally
you need concurrency,
and this concurrency is
provided by threading.
So responsiveness is
one of the benefits
almost by logical
implication, okay?
Resource sharing
is another benefit
the default definition
of processes,
they define separate
arrest spaces,
threading shares
memory by default.
The economy here is
an important consideration
because we are actually able
to create and destruct
threads much faster and
with a lot less overhead,
and we already discussed what
the overheads are, okay?
Because I have a bullet here.
You know, you want to
be able to explain when
you say that something
something has overhead,
you want to be able to be very
precise about what
that overhead is.
But we already discussed
this in this lecture.
Um, and we can take advantage
of multiprocessors, right,
and achieve true
parallelism versus
single processor illusion
of parallelism. Okay.
So the learning
objective, I guess,
for this lecture is to discuss
the design trade offs when
implementing threading support
in your system, right?
What is the best
way to structure
and enable threading support?
Because as it turns out,
there's no one way to do it.
Okay? What is the
real difference
between a thread and a process?
Does there really
need to be one?
What is the interface for
thread creation and destruction
and threat management?
And so in the next year
five or six slides,
I'm going to give you
kind of something that's
sort of the key essence
of this lecture.
And we've finally
built up to that.
We've built up the definitions.
We've built up the motivation,
and we sort of built
up the context
to appreciate the
next five slides.
Okay? That's what we've
been doing. So here we go.
Here's one way that we can
actually support user
space threading.
This design choice is
called one to one.
In other words, for every
single user space thread,
you have a corresponding kernel
space thread or kernel context.
Just like in that previous
example that I flipped
through with the shell and CAT,
you had a user space
context for shell,
kernel space context for shell,
Uerspace context for CAT,
kernel space context for CAT.
Okay? So the number of
userspace treads should be
the same as the number
of kernel space threads.
Is that good?
Do we like this design?
Is this the most
prevalent design?
Have you seen this design
in operating systems?
We don't know.
Well, let's reason
about it, right?
What are the advantages
and disadvantages
again of this design
choice, right?
The attributes here are
that you do get
improved concurrency.
You have the ability
of running them in
parallel and literally
in parallel, right?
So if I have two threads,
user space threads,
they will have two
corresponding kernel
space threads
associated with them.
And what is the schedule C?
The kernel scheduler.
What is the kernel schedule C?
What is it schedule? Yes.
Yeah, it sees this, right?
It sees the individual
kernel threads.
Does it see the userspace
threads? It does not, right?
Can it make scheduling
decisions that
are aware of what's
happening with the
user space threads?
It cannot, right?
And therein lies the problem.
So here, in this
particular case,
if we have a one to one mapping,
we're literally scheduling at
the granularity of userspace
threads in the kernel.
And that's how we can actually
get true multiprocessor
parallelism.
So if we have multiple
cores, let's say four.
Let's make it very concrete.
We can have four kernel contexts
running at exactly
the same time.
Therefore, we can have
four user space threads
running at exactly
the same time, right?
We can achieve
parallelism this way.
The disadvantage here is that
there's additional overhead to
create the kernel thread
for every single
user thread, right?
So anytime there's
a user thread,
you need to create the
corresponding kernel.
Now, how many user threads
do we want in the
system, typically?
5500,
5,000 processes.
Yeah, yeah, but it's a lot.
Usually, if you look at your
just regular laptop, right,
and you do an HTp there
or some kind of a
processor count,
process count, you will find
that there are
thousands of processes,
each of which can actually
have multiple threads, right?
And so, clearly,
this doesn't scale.
Okay, so this is one design.
Here's a flip into
the complete opposite side
of the design spectrum.
So think of design
as a space, right?
It can be one dimensional.
It can be multidimensional,
and it has the kind of
opposite sides, right?
So this is the opposite side of
the spectrum where
the design choice is
a many to one user to
kernel thread mapping.
So what does that mean?
That means that you have
N user space threads,
and they're all going to share
a single kernel thread. Right?
So first of all, why
should we even talk about
something like this?
Well, we just
discussed how there's
additional overhead to create
kernel threats for every
single user threat.
Well, this one
eliminates this overhead
because there's only one
kernel context, right?
It's also very simple
and efficient,
and you don't even
need to contact
switch between the
kernel contexts anymore.
So clearly, you've
accomplished something, right?
Clearly, there are
some advantages and
some reasons why you might
want something like this.
That's called user
space threading.
In other words, the threads
only exist in user space,
and they are all multiplexed on
a single shared kernel
thread context.
We're going to get through
more illustrations that
sort of highlight that.
Now, tell me what are
the advantages and
disadvantages associated
with this one?
Yeah. But let's say
one of the user threads
decides to wait on something.
That means that every other
thread in that process
is blocked because they're
halting to read it in
the kernel thread.
If the kernel thread were to
see Thread one,
that, two, three,
34, one is waiting,
it blows all the erst.
Yeah, exactly. So basically,
if there's any blocking behavior
in any of these
user space threads,
because the kernel thread
is unaware of what's
happening above it,
right, the entire kernel
thread is going to be blocked.
So you could end up in
a situation where you
have some work that
could be done, right?
And you may even have
some additional resources
to do that work, right?
But you're not going to be
able to make progress because
of any blocking behavior of
any of the threads, yes.
As some kernel threads.
And then elastics another
combines the best of both.
There is a way. There is
a way to have the
best of both worlds,
and that's called the
hybrid threading model.
And that's what we're going to,
you know, end this lecture with.
But let's get there
in the next ten
or 12 minutes or so, okay?
So this is, in essence,
a foray into what's called
the user space
threading library.
As a matter of fact,
you can implement
threading entirely in
user space, right?
And this is pretty revelatory.
Why is it revelatory?
Um because you need
to remind yourself of
the switch function that we've
just gone through, right?
Did the switch function
require any privileged
instructions?
Do you remember those two
assembly level instructions
that it had to execute
to switch stacks?
Was there anything privileged
about those assembly
level instructions?
Anyone? I was doing
a move, right?
Of the ESP register into
the old context, right?
And then it was basically moving
the new context into
the ESP register.
That's it, right? That's not
very doesn't sound
very privileged to me.
You can do that in user space.
So what that means is
that miraculously,
you can actually have multiple
stacks in user space,
and you can actually manage
all of those stacks entirely by
yourself in user space
without any help from
the kernel whatsoever.
And that's amazing.
That's one of the labs that
you would actually do in
advanced operating
systems if you proceed to
take that class, 421-06-0210.
Okay. And so by the time
you finish Lab three,
which actually implements
kernel fretting support
in the kernel in this class,
and by the time
you finish writing
your userspace threading
library in 4210,
you will have done it
in both possible ways.
You will have become
kind of a world expert
in both kernel threading
and user threading.
And there are very few
people who can do both.
So the context switch can
actually happen in user space.
We can build this
library in user space.
And basically, the way
to think about this
is that threads are by
design cooperative, right?
And because they're by
design cooperative,
you have to necessarily
by implication,
think that you can
have a cooperative
scheduler in order
to schedule them.
And a cooperative
scheduler does not require
the kernel support, okay?
Because the threads yield,
they cooperate with each other.
You can switch
between the threads
without pre empting them.
Now, in the situations where
you are not cooperative,
you need a preemptive scheduler,
then you need the
kernel's involvement
because only the kernel
can break somebody's threat of
execution and switch contexts.
Okay? Alright, so why
does a user space threading
library make sense?
The key observation
that we've made is that
the threading mechanism is
designed, actually,
what I just said.
Now, I put it on the slide for
you guys because
sometimes you may
not follow what I'm saying.
So here it is on the slide.
The key observation
that we've made,
the threading mechanism
is designed with
an implicit assumption of
cooperation between
units of execution.
That's the key
observation that kind
of gives you some
food for thought.
What is the implication
of that key observation?
Well, the implication is that
cooperative scheduler
should be sufficient.
Well, if cooperative scheduler
should be sufficient,
you can do that in user space.
User space co op
scheduler can switch
between user space threads
and user space tacks
without relying on the
preemptive behavior
that is enabled by the kernel.
If you need preemptive behavior
for anything whatsoever,
you need to have the kernel to
step in and do
this work for you.
Does that make sense? Like,
I'm trying to build up
the logic that actually goes
into these design decisions.
And yes, you do
need to worry about
synchronization primitives,
but as we've discussed
during the previous week,
you can actually build the
synchronization primitives
with user space atomics
and concurrency
primitives, right?
So in the end, we make the
conclusion that there are
no privileged instructions that
are needed from the kernel
in order for you to develop
a user space threading library.
Because the thread
context, the stacks,
the register state is all
available to the
application in user space.
Kernel space is
unnecessary for this.
So that means finally,
the punch line here,
which I already said
is that switching
the stacks is possible in
user space. Does
that make sense?
And how you would
actually explain this to
somebody else why this
is actually possible
in user space.
And if I were to
ask you on a test,
why is it possible
to do in user space?
You have to be able to reason
through this yourself. Yes.
So would you need two
different schedulers,
one in the user space for
the thread and then one
in the kernel for
universal processes?
Sorry, could you
repeat the question?
Two different schedulers,
one for the threads.
Space Yes, absolutely.
Now we're dealing with
two different schedulers,
one user space scheduler,
and that doesn't mean that we've
completely got rid of the
kernel space scheduler.
Now we have two schedulers
happening at the
same time, right?
The user space scheduler is
going to be responsible for
multiplexing user space contexts
within a kernel thread.
And the kernel space scheduler
is responsible for
context switching
between the kernel
threads. Makes sense.
And we have some
examples of this here.
So on the left hand side,
we're basically looking at
what the kernel sees, okay?
So let's see that the
kernel sees a process.
This process consists
of two threads.
So this is this red block
corresponds to thread one.
This is red block
corresponds to thread two.
They share an address space.
And there's a different
proc right here, okay?
And in the red box,
you basically have this one
to one kernel threading model.
So the kernel that means
that the kernel sees
every user space
thread corresponding
to its own separate
kernel space thread.
On the right hand side,
yeah, as I mentioned,
the kernel scheduler
is responsible for
switching between
the kernel contexts.
On the right hand side, you
have user spaced threads,
each with its own stack,
right, but they are completely
invisible to the kernel.
And so with the left hand
side implementation,
the kernel scheduler,
I should say, has the ability to
actually switch between the
threads, one, two, three.
Let's say round robin, right?
Then one, two, three,
again, one, two, three,
and so on and so forth.
So it understands and has
visibility into which processes
have multiple threads.
If it doesn't have
that visibility,
then it basically is not
going to be able to make
the scheduling decisions in
favor of multi
threaded applications.
It will allocate them
the same amount of
time and space and
resources, right,
as to the other process
that doesn't have
any threads running
in the user space
application at all, right?
So here, this is going
to be one process.
This whole thing on
the right hand side,
the green box is going to be
one process from the
perspective of the kernel.
And when the kernel performs
the switch to that process,
it will have to multiplex all of
its threads within the
context of one kernel thread.
Okay. Yeah, that's basically
what I described right here.
So on the left hand side,
you have the kernel,
what the kernel sees, right?
It only sees this
single red box,
the kernel context, right?
But what it doesn't know
is that it could be
a multi threaded
application with
multiple user space threads
associated with that.
And it just decides
which process to
go to schedule
next in a way that
is completely unaware of
the multi threaded behavior
of one of these kernel contexts.
So that means that there's
a semantic gap from the
kernel's perspective,
that is one of the disadvantages
of the userspace
threading library.
Okay, so yeah, not going to
have the breakout discussion.
So here are the advantages
of the kernel space
versus advantages of the
user space threading, okay?
On the left hand side, we get
parallelism, we get preemption.
So kernel space
threading gives us
the ability to perform
preemptive scheduling,
as I mentioned, right?
We have more information
available to the kernel,
as I mentioned with the
example on the previous slide,
because the kernel knows
that this application,
this process has
multiple threads because
all threads are visible
to the kernel, right?
This gives us better ability
to control resource utilization,
and we can make thread
aware process scheduling.
We've already discussed this.
On the right hand side.
So what's interesting if you're
doing your threading
in the user space,
you have more information
about what this
application is doing.
You have more
semantic information.
One concrete example
I can give you is,
let's say it's a map
reduce application, right?
And we all know that you
need to schedule through
all the map threads
before you can
start reduced threads,
for instance, right?
It's a very simple example.
And so at the application
level scheduler,
you know which threads
are map threads
and which threads
are reduced threads,
so you can actually
prioritize them
accordingly in your
scheduling decisions.
So that's what this semantic
awareness is corresponding to.
This application level
semantic awareness
in user space
scheduling decisions.
You got rid of some of the
context switching
overheads right here.
And of course, because
you're staying within
the same process and
you're sharing memory,
you have a lot of
cache locality as one
of the benefits if
your user space
threading design choice.
These threads are
actually lightweight.
And you guys will see that in
the context of lab three,
why they are lighter weight.
You have very concrete,
very hands on code
level understanding
of what this bullet point means,
which is really exciting, okay?
And there's much lighter
weight overhead of
thread creation,
and you will also understand
why this means after
you're done with
lab three, okay?
And so these are
some of the examples
that some of the people
have already alluded to.
What happens if we actually are
doing user space versus
kernel space threading.
So let's say that we have
a single kernel
space thread, right,
that tries to,
um go through and there are
two user space threads,
thread one and thread two, but
they're sharing in
the same context.
So Thread one has the
ability to do some work,
and then it goes
to sleep, and now
we're blocking on sleep, right?
So there are two problems with
this user space
threading situation.
I'm just going to get
through this, right?
Thread one sleeps,
and this is a ciscoL,
it will yield the CPU
to a different process.
So even though there's still
some work remaining to
be done in this
particular process,
we're going to yield
the control of the CPU.
So PC one has just lost the CPU,
even though it has more work.
And the second problem here
has to do with this
read right here.
So let's say we
finished the sleep,
and now we're going
into the read.
As we discussed, it's going
to block our kernel thread,
even though there's some work
that could have been done in
parallel while we're waiting
for the blocking read to return.
So that's the second
problem with this, right?
And so we can handle
this by breaking it up
into one kernel thread
each for each of the
user space threads.
This is going to solve
this problem, right?
It's going to address
this problem,
but it introduces
its own challenges
of kernel context overhead,
managing multiple contexts,
and so on and so forth.
So the question is, can we
get the best of both worlds?
Somebody asked me this, right?
Can I allocate
user space threads
to N kernel space threads?
So this is what I refer to
as the hybrid threading.
It's sort of a design
choice in between.
And as the name would
suggest, basically,
you have a handful of
kernel threads that you're
multiplexing over and you have
many more user space threads
than there are kernel
threads, okay?
So now, what are
the advantages and
disadvantages
associated with that?
Now, let's see what
problem did it solve,
first of all, if any?
Yeah. Stay.
Yeah, it's this blocking thing.
It's the annoying
blocking thing that
you that we've
talked about, right?
It's going to take
care of that because
now you have more kind of
threats to multiplex over.
And so the advantages are
the user space threads
can run in parallel,
right, because you have
multiple kernel contexts
to multiplex over.
You also have fewer
context switches.
This is relative to
one to one, okay?
So this is relative to
one to one right
here because one to
one has one kernel context
per user space context.
You have lightweight
user space threads,
so you're basically
taking advantage
of userspace threading
here, right?
So you're dealing with small
user space threading cost.
But there are still
disadvantages
because you are still subject to
kernel thread stalls
because you're multiplexing
multiple user spaced threads per
single kernel context, right?
So you can still
experience some of this thread
blocking that we talked about,
and it's still not
cooperative use of the CPU.
So it depends on the kernels
ability to preempt, right?
So, at the end of all of this,
the question is, what
are the operating systems
actually do, right?
So we have these
three design choices.
Just tell me what's actually
happening in practice.
In practice, mostly it's
kernel threading, right?
But there are some
tips and tricks
that the modern operating
systems are doing.
For example, many
of the operations
are kind of pushed as
many as possible are
pushed to user space.
The futex Cisco allows
mostly user space
concurrency primitive,
so it only depends on
the kernel for the
purposes of sleep and
wake up because I
mentioned that we have to
have the kernel for those.
But all of the synchronization,
all of the atomics are
actually being handled
at in user space.
There's a trade off between
the user and kernel efficiency,
where the kernel manages
IO sleeping, right?
It gives us the ability to
kick out a process that's
just waiting on IO to
happen for the more
efficient use of
the physical resources
or while a process
is sleeping switches to a
different context, right?
Okay, so where do
we stand in XV six?
It's basically the kernel stack.
Each process has its
own kernel stack,
and there are no
user space threads.
And your goal is to
develop the support for
user spaced threads here.
Right? And the schedule on
top of this actually has
no awareness of threading
and has no S&P
support whatsoever.
So you get to implement
that in Lab free.
So you're basically here
from a historical
Unix perspective,
this is where XV
six is right here.
And this is where we
want to be, right?
We want to allow threads
to be scheduled.
We want to retain
performance advantages
of threads, share memory,
and take advantage of
the performance of
the kernel threading,
and we want to be
able to implement
the synchronization
primitives like waiting,
spinlocks, mutexes, and
conditional variables.
And that's Lab three, and I
will end my lecture here.
Thank you so much.
Hello.
Oh, nice.
A lot. It's a lot.