At this point I
I A
All right.
Good afternoon,
everyone. So today,
we're going to talk about
the OSN networking.
This is the last lecture
that you're going
to need to know for
the purposes of Exam one.
Next week on Tuesday,
we're going to have a professor
from School of
Cybersecurity and Privacy
covering the Security
One lecture.
Then on Thursday, we are
going to have Exam one prep.
So we're going to spend
basically a week from today,
we're going to spend some
time actually trying to
prepare for your first
exam in this class.
And let's see.
Your actual exam is going to be
the following
Tuesday of March 11
in this class. So
I'll get to that.
Today, we want to talk
about operating systems and
networking and basically how
networking interacts
and works inside of
the operating system
and why we care
about networking in the
first place, right?
Because after all, there are
other networking
classes precisely.
After all, there are
other networking classes
that you can take where
you can go in depth in
term how all of these
layers are actually
constructed and how
the policies are
constructed and the algorithms
associated with networking,
which is a lot of fun, but
it's out of the scope
for this class.
In this class, we're
going to be focusing on
the abstractions that
you have to sort of
build up layer by layer in
order to get to the point
where you give the applications
and the user something
that they expect,
something that they can
actually work with.
And I'm going to try to make
a case for how networking
really is no different from
the virtual memory
management, for instance,
right, or the file system
or other sort of verticals
in your kernel from
the perspective of
the abstractions and
the way you sort
of reason about
those abstractions.
All right. So clarification
on class effort.
I'm going to say
this exactly once,
and I'll probably not
come back to this
again because you're into
your lab three right now.
So it really doesn't make
sense to repeat this
too much, right?
So the reminder here is that
our goal is for you guys to
spend on average about 10 hours
a week of out of class work.
So that doesn't include
supervised labs,
doesn't include you being here.
Thank you very much for coming.
This is outside, out
of class work, okay?
And so what that
means is that if you
get a lab and you get
three weeks to do it,
that means that
the expectation is
sort of 30 hours on average.
Of course, there's going
to be a distribution.
Some people can get it done
faster, some are slower.
That's obvious, right? With
by the law of large numbers,
there will be some sort
of a distribution.
But if you're sort of
falling under that,
then you might or actually,
let's take an extreme example.
If you do sort of 0 hours
for two of the weeks,
then yes, of course,
your third week is
going to be 30 plus
hours of work.
And this is not a problem
with this class, right?
This is not a
problem with the TA,
so with the instructor,
it's a problem of time
management in this class, right?
So let's just be mindful of
that because that's
just how math works.
If you are spending a ton
of time beyond this goal,
and that happens consistently,
right? And it's not improving.
You now should be much
more comfortable
with the code base,
it should not really
be happening where you
spend more time than 10
hours per week on average.
Then, you know, please let
the course staff know, right?
If you're stuck trying
to debug something,
you know, you can easily
spend a lot of time on this.
You know, please
make sure you sort
of do spend some time on this,
but then also try to engage
the teaching assistant
and try to engage them in
supervised labs and
office hours, right?
That's obvious. We,
the instruction staff
are being very careful and very
deliberate in how we
design assignments.
You may be surprised
that, for example,
for me to put together
an assignment or to put
together an exam is a
lot more effort and
for you to take it.
A lot like an order of
magnitude, more effort,
especially if we
count the human hours
collectively across the
entire course staff.
The way we approach
designing assignments is
that we aim for a balance
of learning and work.
So we don't want you
to just basically 100%
of your assignment
to be perspiration.
We want this to be a balance
of inspiration and perspiration.
Okay? We want you
to be inspired.
We want you to learn something,
to come out knowing something
you didn't know before.
That's sort of a
necessary condition.
Of course, it's not a
sufficient condition.
The perspiration has
to be in there, too.
You have to put in the work, you
have to put in the hours,
and then you're going to
get a combination of
those two things.
My objective is always
to maximize learning.
That's what I care about.
That's why I teach this class.
I don't have to
teach this class,
but I want to teach this class
because I believe it's
at a pivotal point,
both in your personal
development and
your professional development
as a CISRc professional.
Um, and my goal here is
to have you thinking about
interesting systems
design problems,
to shake up the foundation
of your knowledge,
to get you to start
asking the why questions
instead of just
basically recalling
something you have learned
in previous classes
without really
understanding the
reasons that underpin
the design decisions someone
has made on your behalf,
because without asking
the why questions,
you really cannot approach
designing anything new at all.
And then you're stuck recalling
stuff for the rest of
your life without really
creating anything new.
We don't want that to
happen. All right.
I already had this
slide last time.
How many of you have not seen
the absory slide? Should
I just skip that?
Okay, consider this
a three week lab,
even though you have weeks
five calendar weeks to
get it done, right?
I wanted to re emphasize we have
a couple of bonus
opportunities here.
It's the longest lab that
you have in this class.
I don't know if
it's the hardest.
Every time I pull the students,
they tell me that Lab
two was the hardest.
Some people say lab
three was the hardest.
It really depends, but
it is always a toss
up between those two.
Once you get past your
lab two and lab three,
once you've survived
that plus the exam,
you know, you're going to
be in a pretty good shape.
You should be feeling good
about yourself after that.
So this is a bonus
opportunity where we sort of
created a checkpoint
due date on a pie day,
March 14, right,
where we want you to
complete and be on track to
complete parts one and two.
And you really should
do that, right?
This is a very
meaningful checkpoint,
and we're trying to
incentivize it with a bonus.
You get bonus for the
percentage of tests 1-21,
inclusive that you
have completed by
the deadline. Any
questions about that?
It will be automatically
calculated for
you as part of the
or grader test,
and it will be logged
to your autograder log.
So you'll be able to
see it if you look at
the autograder log. Yeah.
Okay, and another one that
I'm personally excited
about is that we're giving
you an opportunity to
actually design a policy
for the scheduler,
and we want you to
bid the system.
We want you to bid
the stock schedulers
that you have to implement,
which is required as part of
the rest of the
assignment, okay?
And there are people who
get truly excited about
this and they come up
with novel solutions.
And we want you to actually
prove to us that your
schedule is better,
kind of drawing on
the insights and
the success metrics that
we have already
discussed in this class.
All right, that's a
second bonus opportunity.
Exam. Again, everyone here,
were you in attendance
in previous lecture?
I can skip this. We can come
back to it next Thursday.
But here's a set of
topics that we're
going to be covering for
the exam, et cetera.
One thing that I guess I
didn't mention is this.
We are going to post some
sample prep questions
to codas by next week
so that you guys
will actually have some
sample questions to practice
on because as I
mentioned last time,
the exam is going to be
different from your labs.
The exam is going to be testing
your knowledge of
the lecture material and
your ability to think.
This mid term this
exam one prep,
I should say, is going to be
one week from today,
next Thursday.
Here's a set of topics.
I mean, somebody asked
for a study guide,
I believe this is what
a study guide is.
It's sort of topics that
we're going to be covering.
And in general, I
generally focus on
conceptual knowledge.
I like to ask questions testing
your understanding, okay?
And that's the reason
why it's going
to be completely
open notes, right?
I really don't care
how many references
you can bring in the whole
library if you want,
because that's just
recall information.
And in real life, you will
be able to look stuff up.
You will be able to refer
to static material.
What I want what I really
want to test is your
ability to sort of
work with that material
in an agile fashion
mentally, right?
Under time constraints.
And I want to see you
figuring out why something
operates the way it does,
as well as how it changes
if we actually change
some underlying assumptions or
some conditions
around the problem.
So this sort of requires
some mental agility.
Be prepared to think. It's
not going to be a recall,
true and false kind of midterm.
The exam will be open
notes, closed Internet.
So you can bring any
static material you want.
You can download the slides,
you can download whatever
you want on your laptop,
but we will be disallowing
access to the Internet.
And the exam will be proctored.
So you have people
walking around,
kind of taking a look
at what you're doing,
what's on your screen.
And the reason for that is
because there's just really,
really increasingly hard
for us to figure out,
are you just doing a good old
fashioned Google
search with keywords,
which in my personal opinion
would have been fine,
or are you literally copy
pasting the parts of the
question into the Google search?
Because the back end for
Google search is
now Gemini, right?
We just there's no way for
us to police that, right?
And so it's just going to be
easier to as a matter of policy,
say that, okay, Internet
is not allowed.
And again, there's a
good reason for that.
The reason for this is
because we really want to
test your ability to
think, not only test,
but also develop your
ability to think and
measure how successful we
were at teaching
you how to think.
I don't want to
test Gemini, right?
I'm pretty sure Gemini
is pretty good.
I want to teach
you and I want to
measure my success at
being able to teach you.
So that's really
what it's all about.
It will be in class
here on your laptop.
No charging stations, as
I mentioned previously,
please make sure your
laptop is charged.
It will be sort
of a Canvas quiz.
So obviously, you will need
access to Canvas, that's okay.
Please bring bus cards,
and they'll be checked as
you're taking the test.
I think that's pretty standard.
And, of course, it's an
individual assignment.
This is anyway, whatever.
It's an individual assignment.
Okay, so let's talk about
networking unless there are
any questions about the
administrative a so far.
No, good. Okay. So we
like to talk about abstractions
in this class, right?
It's all about abstractions,
abstractions, abstractions.
And there's a very
good reason for
that because operating
systems are all about
bridging this abstraction gap
and providing higher
level abstractions.
From day one, I was
saying things like,
you know, what is an
operating system?
Remember, that's
number one question
that I asked during the
very first lecture.
Why do we need an
operating system?
Is it necessary, right?
And some of the good answers
that I got from you
guys, actually,
is that we have a
bunch of resources
in the system that
we don't really know
how to use because they're
because there's something
wrong with them,
and I'm not going to give
you the answer
right away, right?
So let's consider and
discuss this again in the
context of networking, right?
So what does our
networking hardware
look like in the
operating system?
What abstraction
does it provide?
Can anyone give me an idea?
What is a networking card doing?
Yes. Bids data from the
network as like a file.
Huh, does it do that?
The network card itself.
Oh, not the network.
Yeah, the network card itself.
Yeah. So see already
but it's good because
you're already
foreshadowing something
that I'm going to talk about.
Yeah.
The card has the Mac address,
so that's the unique identifier
for the device on the network.
Okay, so you're
talking about, how
do we make things work,
the mechanisms, right?
But what it really
provides us is the ability
to essentially send frames
on the wire, right?
Even lower level than that,
it sends some
signals on the wire.
You know, how good of an
abstraction is that to work
with as an application
developer, right?
Or do we tell the network
interface card directly?
Go to www.google.com, and
pass the query, please.
That's not exactly how we
interact with the
network card, right?
So in general, in the old days,
basically we had this
standard network card.
You have a computer here on
the left hand side,
you have a NIC.
And basically, from the
Nick's perspective,
it has the ability to pass,
let's say, frames
of information in
a point to point fashion to
the down the line,
down the cable.
That's it. That's what it does.
But what really happens,
is that somehow magically,
given this low
level abstraction,
we're able to traverse the
entire Internet somehow, right?
And let's say we're in
the United States and
the other servers in Europe,
right, for instance.
And then somehow we
were able to cross
the ocean and successfully
communicate it with a
network interface card
that was locally installed
on some remote server.
And we do that with
the interface,
which is extremely low level,
send some fixed
Ethernet frames down
the wire, period. Right?
So the question is,
how does this happen?
How do we go from
having this point to
point network interface card
to network interface card,
communication mechanism and on
one hand side or at the
bottom, right, of our stack,
and all the way to building
a worldwide web
where you can have
anywhere to anywhere
connections and
communication mechanisms, right?
And so as we think through this,
this is a good sort
of teaching moment
where I like to introduce
the following, right?
It is essential for
the building blocks to
have the two
fundamental properties.
You know, basically, in order
for us to be able to bridge
this huge semantic gap
from talking signals
on the wire, right,
to being able to provide
the worldwide web
implementation,
you need to have the
building blocks that have
the following two properties,
orthogonality and composability.
Okay? So in system design,
you will encounter
multiple situations
where you sort of have to
work with the interface
that we were provided
and oftentimes create
a new interface or
cater to an interface
that is expected.
So you need to bridge
that gap, right?
And that's where system
design really comes in,
including software engineering
and middleware system design.
And so the way you approach
these design problems is
by thinking about constructing
primitives that are
orthogonal and composable,
just like lego blocks.
It's really good to think
of them as egoblock.
So what does that mean?
What's orthogonality?
Orthogonalogy is sort of a term
that's borrowed from
PL community, right?
And it means that you have
a relatively small set of
primitives or primitive
constructs to work with.
So again, using the
legal analogy, you know,
how many different
blocks you usually
operate with? It's
not a lot, right?
It's not like you have 1,000
different pieces to work with.
There's usually a handful of
different but fundamentally
different pieces to work with.
And so that's what
orthogonality is referring to.
And at the same time,
you want to make sure
that they can be
combined in a relatively
small number of ways.
So if you have two lego blocks,
what are the different ways
you can combine them, right?
You're not going to
screw them together.
nail them together.
It's usually just like a snap.
Pretty much one way to
combine two lego blocks.
So that's another component
of the orthogonal design.
So that's why ego is so
successful because
it's very simple.
It comes with very primitive
kind of set of constructs,
but that compose with each
other in a very small
number of ways.
So in other words,
it's easy, okay?
And composibility
basically has to do with
a system design that
deals with interrelationship
of components.
So a highly composable system,
it provides the components
that can be selected and
assembled in various
combinations
to satisfy specific
user requirements.
And so we are going to
observe basically how
these two properties manifest
themselves in a network
protocol stack.
So what does our
networking hardware
look like to the
operating system?
It essentially looks like a
device that provides us with
a low level capability of
point to point
communication, right?
That's what it looks like
at the very low level.
And if we get to
that, I actually have
some diagrams that I drew from
Linux kernel documentation in
terms of how real Network
percostxs are implemented.
But how does this differ from
the Internet abstraction that we
provide to the
operating system users
and applications, right?
Applications, so the user
they operate at a much
higher level of abstraction.
What do they expect?
Just at a high level.
What an application or
a user might want to
expect if they want to
conduct any sort of
networking activity.
They don't want to send
signals to the wire,
right? What do they want?
Yes. Sending a message
or email, yes.
Protocols like H GDP.
So that's sort of a mechanism
of how we enact something
to happen, right?
So in this particular case,
it's basically looking up
some information on
the Internet, right?
Did you have. Alright,
so if you have
RDBMS engine somewhere
and you actually want
to perform queries on
a body of data, right?
It can be structured or
unstructured queries, right?
Interacting with
data in general.
Some of you may go into
fourth year database
classes, right,
and you will actually be
building database engines
that enable that that have
their own set of protocols.
And so, basically, in general,
the takeaway here is that
communication starts by
sending some frames on
your Nick to the
next neighbor in
order to communicate to the
computer on the other
side of the world,
but the packets are being
routed through a bunch
of switches and routers
in betweens, in between.
And this is completely invisible
from the perspective of
the end points of this
communication, right?
Everything that's happening
here is completely invisible.
Um, which is what we want,
because we want to
sort of achieve
transparency from the
application perspective.
So all of this is
happening while you
think you the user or
the user application,
you're talking directly to
the other side of the world.
So that's the abstraction
that we really provide.
And in general, what
the user applications and
kind of network
application want,
right, is they want
the ability to have global
addressing and naming, right?
So in other words, let's say you
have a browser and you
want to put in a URL
or a domain name,
you want to have some sort of
DNS resolution, and in general,
you want your query or
HTTP query to go to the
specified URL, right?
What's also enabled
a point to point
communication and do we
have a how many different
active connections
can we have at any
given point in time?
Let's say we have
one laptop, right?
How many different
networking connections
do we have on that laptop
at any given point in time,
even as we speak right now?
A lot, right? How many
nicks do you have?
One, right? You have
a wireless adapter,
which is also a Nick, talks
a different protocol, right?
And how does that happen?
Our applications even aware
of the fact that you
only have one Nick.
So this deals with
multiplexing, right?
We have one Nick,
many connections.
And even for the way this,
in fact, we have one
nick and many ports.
Let's start there.
So we already have, 65,000
ports or whatnot, right?
That can be hosted or
rather enabled and
supported on the same nick.
But even for every single port,
we can actually have multiple
connections per port, right?
More generally, let's say
if you're talking about
interactive streams or
interactive content,
like playing a video or
using IP telephone, right?
Any kind of audio call that
you make over the Internet,
the application here assumes
the ability to have a
stream of information.
And what is a stream
of information?
Clearly, this is not something
that Au Nick knows
anything about.
Right? By the time
that information
goes down to the
network interface card,
it doesn't know that
these frames are actually
related to each other and they
belong to a specific stream.
So this construction must
happen at a higher level
of abstraction, right?
And we'll see exactly
where that happens.
So streaming here just
to make it a little
bit more precise,
what I'm referring
to is basically
having semantically
relevant data.
And when you have a
concept of flow, right?
So you don't just send
a single message, to
your point, right?
Maybe there's a sequence of
messages that actually create
a flow or a sequence of
video frames that
you want to send,
right, with certain
QS guarantees.
Or a sequence of audio messages,
packets that you want
to be able to send.
And so that sort of
becomes a stream.
And we also depend
or really want
to depend from the application
level perspective,
we want to have some
sort of reliability.
So if you're talking
to somebody on
the phone that is using
IP telephony, right,
how garbled can your
message be if you don't
introduce anything to sort
of reorder the packets
or make sure they arrive
in the right order, right?
Even more generally,
forget about reordering.
More generally, you can have
failures because I
just mentioned that,
you know, we have this thing.
We have a network of
different network
enabled devices in the middle
between the two endpoints
of communication.
And there are actually
multiple pathways
that you can take
as you traverse this set
of vertices in this
directed basically graph.
Oh, and by the way, sometimes
it becomes a non directed
acyclic graph, right?
Sometimes they are
actually cycles here.
And that's when the backbone
starts to go down and
you have outages.
So you have to have the
ability to detect cycles and
make sure that it's directly
a cyclic graph, right?
But let's go back
to reliability.
So let's say that this
router fails, right?
Do you still want your
message to go through?
You don't? Not
through that router.
Yeah. Yeah. But in general,
as a matter of fact,
you don't even
want the application to notice,
right, because you want to give
them that sense of isolation,
right, and fault tolerance.
So if this router fails,
we want to basically as
I think what you
were alluding to,
we don't want to use that router
because it's malfunctioning
in some way.
We want to remove
the link around it,
and we want the adjacent
routers to actually be aware of
this that this link is no
longer a feasible link to take.
So I think that's what
you were going with.
Yeah, that's a good point.
Right? So we need to update
something some state
that encapsulates
the adjacent links in this
network in this directed to
cyclo graph that from
this router right here,
you can no longer route
messages down here,
and this router right
here should not
expect any messages from
this particular location,
this particular edge, right?
Okay, so instead, what we
want is a green route,
for instance, because
it's a healthy route.
And I'm trying to emphasize
the fact that all of
this is happening
without the application
even being aware of this.
And as a matter of fact,
you're not even making
any global decisions.
So there's no global
scheduler that says,
reconfigure the
routing tables on
every single vertex in
this fashion, right?
Because that would be
really expensive and
your network would suck because
everything would
be extremely slow.
As a matter of fact, these
decisions are actually made
very locally in a thing like
a vertex type of fashion,
which is awesome, right?
That sort of lends itself
very nicely to the
orthogonality and
composability of the
individual components
that I was talking
about previously.
So the routing tables
individually can be
updated in such a way
that these updates
are highly local and they take
care of actually
avoiding the bad routes.
And the way this typically
happens is by updating
the weights associated with
specific routes in
your routing table.
So if you set away to
infinity, for example,
you're never going to
take that route, okay?
And then if your detection
mechanism has detected
that this router has come
back to life, then again,
you need to have
automated mechanisms
to lower the cost of
that route and dynamically
adjust it appropriately.
Okay. So why are we
talking about all of this?
We're in an operating
systems class.
Have any of you
taken networking?
Oh, gosh. Okay, can
you raise your hands
higher. So what is it?
Half the class has
taken networking.
So you know all of
this already, right?
So let me make a
connection to this class.
Why are we talking about
networking in this class?
The reason for this
is because the
network protocol stack or
this magic black
box that sort of
fits in the kernel
proper, right?
It actually provides
us with the same set
of abstractions that we
have come to expect from other
verticals in the kernel,
like virtual memory and file
systems, et cetera, right?
So we get the following
abstractions.
We get naming, we
get reliability,
we get isolation, right?
We get multiplexing.
And all of those,
do I have one more?
Oh, yes, we get protection.
And all of those should
now start to sound really,
really familiar because it's
sort of a repeating theme
across the different components
of the kernel that we
have already studied
extensively and
we continue to study
extensively until the
end of this class.
Naming reliability, isolation,
multiplexing, protection.
So if I were to ask you,
let's say, on your
final exam or exam
One, right? You know,
give me examples of the
specific functionality in
the kernel that provides
these abstractions
and name three examples.
I will want you to come up
with those three examples.
Of course, one of them is
networking. The other is VMM.
Okay, so I think we've belabored
the point quite a bit.
We're dealing with very low
level networking interface.
It provides an
unreliable transport,
but it has the ability
to not ability.
It doesn't do anything
about packets
accidentally reorienting
themselves in the
network, right?
Sometimes you can
even drop data,
which is quite unfortunate,
and it communicates
using a MAC address,
and it doesn't
provide any security.
And I think the TLDR here,
the takeaway is that we're
dealing with bare bones,
sort of frame based, unreliable
P to P communication system.
And starting with the
data link, right,
it uses something
extremely low level,
like, for example,
a MAC address,
which consists of six octets.
And I guess, just to
spend a minute on this,
it really is an ordered
piece of information.
The top level three octets
comprise the organizationally
unique identifier.
The bottom the least
significant three octets
are the network interface
controller specific part.
And basically, if you look
at one of the octets here,
in the six octet tuple,
the least significant
bit corresponds to
whether or not it's a
unicast or a multicast,
and then the second
least significant bit is
whether or not it's globally
unique or locally administered.
So that's how low level
the interface is at the
data link layer, right?
But what we want, right?
Is for the operating system
to provide a reliable transport.
We want for the operating
system to give us naming
and the ability to resolve
host names like G tech dottGU.
We want the operating system
to give us multiplexing,
like having many ports and
many connections even per port,
which I'm referring to here
as fine granularity
multiplexing,
and we want protection or
some sort of security,
some sort of at least
limited security.
And this is sort of the
focus of what we're going
to talk about in this
lecture in this class, okay?
This is what provided to us
by the networking stack.
Okay, so how do we build
these abstractions, right?
Those of you who have taken
the networking class,
are you familiar with the
seven OSI layers, right?
Do you remember
what they are? Yes.
Transport application.
I think I'm skipping.
Yes. So there's something here.
Let me do this for
you. Okay? And then
let's make sure that it actually
lines up with what you remember.
Here's the way I remember this,
and I've remembered
this for the past,
I think, 25 years or something.
That's a long time. So
it's a good mnemonic.
All people seem to
need data process.
And you're going to remember
it for your next 25 years.
All people seem to
need data processing,
and this is the one that you
refer to as a link layer.
So it's either data.
It's called the Datalink layer.
So basically, this is
the application layer.
This is the presentation.
Layer, this is the
session layer,
and this is the transport.
This is the network layer,
and this is the data
link. And physical.
Okay. I'm also going to
be not just me, actually,
the network backend ups
are usually referring to
these layers in a
very specific way.
They usually say that
this is an L four.
This is an L three,
L two, and one.
Did you see that
notation? Okay, good.
And also, usually in
textbooks or whatever
or other classes,
people sometimes refer to
this whole thing at the top as I
cannot draw sideways as an
application layer right here.
Okay.
And so in this class,
we're kind of primarily will be
concerning ourselves with
these two layers right here,
but I wanted to make
sure that you have
awareness of all of the layers
because they're important.
Why they're important?
Because starting at the top,
starting at the application,
you want to have a
single piece of data.
So this is your data or payload
being sent from one post.
So this is your host with data.
To another hot. This is
your other host with data.
And all you want is you
want that data essentially
at a high level to be
propagated to that host, right?
But what really happens
is that this data,
this piece of data starts
going down the protocol stack,
and every single layer in
the protocol stack starts
prepending or potentially
appending different headers
and suffixes to that data.
So for instance, you could
end up with a UDP header,
so that basically
your L four protocol,
adding a UDP header,
prepending a UDP
header to your data.
So now you have this.
Right? And then
you keep going down the
stack to the network layer.
So the network layer is
going to add an IP header.
So now you have IP.
Yeah, that's good.
IP, followed by UDP,
followed by your payload data.
So this is the L three
addition to this.
Now we're going to
go down to L two,
and for the purposes
of this class,
let's assume that we're
dealing with Ethernet.
So what are we going to
prepend at the L two layer?
Half of you have taken
networking, I recall.
So what are we prepending here
as we keep going down the?
Yeah. Ethernet header.
Ethernet header.
Can somebody tell
me how many bytes is
the ethernet header?
And do you know why I know this?
Because I know the
reason for this.
Okay, let's assume that
we're dealing with
Ethernet as our L two protocol.
You're going to
basically end up with
an ehader as ethernet
frame header.
Which is going to
consist of 14 bytes.
Six of which are going
to be your source MAC.
Six of which are going to
be your destination mac
and two bytes basically
for the type. Okay?
And after all of this,
you are going to have your IP,
then your UDP, and then your
payload, your data, right?
So look at what we have just
constructed and how much
overhead there is for
us to actually send
a single piece of data, right?
Now, why do we need
all of this overhead?
As I mentioned, anytime you
see some sort of
complexity or overhead,
there's usually a
good reason for this.
So let's try to break this down.
Um, Okay, so I already
talked about this.
We have physical at
the bottom, right?
This is the layer that's
responsible for essentially
communicating
signals on the wire.
For instance, one
protocol you could
be talking is fiber
optic cable, okay?
You can have coaxial cable.
You can have unshielded
twisted pair, cat five E.
You can have shielded
twisted pair, at six.
Okay? There are many
different protocols that
you can actually
be communicating
at the physical layer.
There's a whole bunch.
And this is not even my area
of specialty. I can
think of several.
I'm sure the electrical
engineers here
in the audience can come
up with many more, right?
Then you have the
data link layer,
and this is the one that's
sort of responsible
to provide you with
essentially the containers,
the binarized containers
to ship your data.
So if we again,
assume Ethernet
frame ether network,
right, it gives you
these rant frames
as a container to ship your
data, wherever data you want.
That's the container
you can put it in.
So that's the way
to think about it.
Your eranet frames
are like containers.
Then the networking
layer is actually
responsible for kind of adding
the semantic awareness
of host to host
communication because
it kind of gives
you an idea of what's
the address of
this end node that I
want to talk to, right?
And so here you will have a
source IP and destination IP.
A higher level, this is
the transport layer,
the L four, let me add
this here, the L four,
which is going to
give you basically
some connection oriented or
connection less information
on top of just bare bones point
to point communication
provided by L three.
So that's what the
transport layer is doing.
And then the application
layer on top is basically
just handling whatever's
necessary from the application.
Perspective is sort of
outside of the scope
of this class.
Okay. Oh, yeah, and
someone mentioned HTTP.
HTTP is a very good example
of the specific protocol,
hypertext transfer protocol that
we are using at the
application level, okay?
So what I'm trying
to say here is that
even layers above L four,
so L five plus have
their own protocols.
Like HTTP is one protocol.
FTP, the file transfer
protocol, SFTP, right?
HTTPS. I'm going to put them
in brackets right here.
All of those are kind of
application level protocol.
L five plus.
Now, here for your transport,
you have TCP and UDP are
the quintessential examples
that we're going to
talk about and you need
to know for this class.
Then, of course,
network IP, right?
These are the ones that you
really want to know
for this class.
And below that, there are
different wired and wireless
data link protocols
that are usually defined in
the eight oh two
X standard of IE.
The very bottom,
you basically have
some physical medium
through which the signals,
the electrical
signals propagate.
All right.
So one way to
think about it is that as
you go through the stack,
you traverse the
sequence of protocols.
You have to, in order to
unwrap the data that you
are trying to send, right?
And going down the
protocol stack,
you are wrapping it in
these layers so that
each individual layer
can actually interpose
and extract the necessary
information to make
the control decisions
that it is making, okay?
Okay, so this is what
I have just drawn
on the whiteboard.
You can also see it
kind of more cleanly
on the slide with a little
bit more information.
So again, you have your
payload right here,
then it's sort of wrapped into
transport layer protocol data.
Let's say TCP protocol,
like port numbers and
things like that,
source and destination ports.
Where did that go?
Okay, then you
have a Senders IP
address on top of that.
See, I put it right here.
And then after that, which is
also source and destination
IP address information.
After that, you
have the receivers
and the Senders MAC address.
Okay.
So, um, ink layer communicates
on a single link.
Internet layer manages
multiple hops across
links and transport layer
manages data reliability.
So this is really to reemphasize
that our goal, right, is this.
Right here, we want to send
some data from Host A to
host B and have
it traverse whatever
it needs to traverse.
But what really happens is that
it starts at the
application layer and
basically starts
to go down through
the protocol stack all the
way to the link layer,
right, hits the medium
that it gets sent over,
then starts going back up the
stack on the next device.
Depending on how semantically
aware that device is,
it could be L two, right?
It could be L three,
and sometimes
it's even L four aware.
But usually, it's either L two,
which is your regular
switch and L three,
which is your regular router.
Makes sense. So this is
L two is where most of
your switches live,
and L three or repeaters,
for example, repeaters are
even dumber than that.
And L three is basically
your routers because routers
need the networking information.
L four Aware routers exist.
Cisco four Aware routers exist,
for example, and they kind
of try to provide
you QS guarantees.
They tried to provide
you with the notion of
flows and streams so
that if there are any quality of
service guarantees imposed
on a particular stream,
let's say audio video stream.
The only way to do
that is if you have
some L four sematic information.
Alright.
Okay, I think so we've
gone through this.
I'm not going to go
through this again.
The point that I was trying to
make is that you will traverse
up and down and up and down
and up and down the
stack multiple times.
So it's not just a direct point
to point communication
anymore, right?
The data flow is much more
complicated than this.
And then finally,
you go all the way
back all the way up to the host.
So it's a lot of processing
that actually happens
under the hood.
And, you know, by the way,
this does show up in
interview questions.
I remember I myself when
I was interviewing
for Microsoft,
people would ask me, you know,
what happens when I communicate
between two hosts, right?
And it's a very
interesting kind of
interview question
because they try to test,
you know, how deep your
knowledge really goes.
The test for the breadth and
the depth of your
knowledge simultaneously.
And if you give them this,
you know, it's a good start.
Okay, so let's start talking
about the two layers
that I mentioned, right?
The transport layer and
network protocol layer.
It's called here the
Internet layer, right?
That's the L three.
That's the same thing as
the network layer right
here. So what does it enable?
It gives us the ability to
address hosts
because now we want
to have a notion of
talking across hosts.
Host to host communication
is the semantic
awareness of L three,
and it also enables routing.
So remember, I
mentioned that we have
these routing tables in
the vertices of this
director basically graph.
You wouldn't be able
to have any kind of
routing if you didn't have
addressing capability.
So this three layer gives you
the addressing capability.
Okay? Let's see.
And so this routing kind
of starts to hint at how
we provide reliability to
the network applications
in general.
In fact, does anyone know what
the first successful
network built ever was,
at least as far as we know, yes.
It was like DARPA, right?
It was pre DARPA, actually.
It was arpanet. Exactly.
It was arpanet. And they
had a very serious concern.
Just kind of interesting
in retrospect,
they had a serious concern.
If you only have direct point
to point communication, right?
And let's say you
need to talk between
East Coast and West Coast and
you have a direct line
of communication,
then you have a single point of
failure at every single
vertex in between, right?
So you take out any telecom
base station or whatever.
I don't know what they
were using at that time,
any one of those
vertices, right?
Then you can no longer communicate
between East and West.
And so you needed to
have some sort of
redundant network so that if
one of the vertices is actually
taken out for whatever reason,
or if it fails, you
want to be able to sort
of still make a connection
between East and
West Coast, right?
And so this was successfully
achieved with ARPAnet,
where we started to see some
original and some
first kind of routing
protocols that would
automatically fail
over between the vertices if
the vertices were to fail.
And I believe, if
I'm not mistaken,
at least, let's say
five years ago,
this was the case,
it's still kind
of part of the backbone
of the Internet
that we have today.
Okay. Yes.
And so DARPA is really
credited with coming
up with this project.
You're correct. And
because it was always sort
of at the forefront of
enabling these technologies.
It was the one that was credited
with essentially the birth of
Internet before
the World Wide Web
became popular a couple
of decades later.
Okay, L four, this
is a layer of particular
interest to operating systems,
right, because L four
is where we start
some interesting abstractions
to really become implemented.
And remember that the
abstractions that
we talked about are the
streaming interface,
the reliability, and point to
point communication, right?
So how do we provide
streaming interface
if we send packets?
What does that even mean, right?
So remember that
the way to think
about packets of frames is that
this fixed container that
you ship and it goes, right?
So how do we make this look
like a stream of
arbitrary data rights?
Because from the
application perspective,
you just want to open
up a socket, right,
and you want to write
arbitrary amount of
data into that socket.
We break it up,
right? So basically,
the transport layer gives you
the ability to break it up.
And conversely, if your
writes are extremely small,
then do we really want to pay
this entire overhead
for every single write?
You know, all the overhead
and all the headers
if you're trying to send
a single byte of data
over the network.
We don't want to do that, right?
So we also depend on the
transport layer to sort of
coalesce multiple rites
into a single packet so
that we only pay the
overhead of slapping on
the additional kind
of metadata on top
of that once per
multiple small rites.
So this is sort of a
performance optimization.
Right? So we use
multiple packets
for a single write if
the write is very big,
and that happens
completely transparently.
Application doesn't care,
doesn't know that this
is actually happening.
You push your protobuf into
a socket and you've
just serialized it,
you did a socket right,
and you're done, right?
And what happens
underneath the hood,
what's enabled by
the transport layer
is that you break it up
into multiple packets.
And conversely, as I
mentioned, multiple packets,
a coalesced into
multiple writes,
a single packet.
Now, what happens if
packets are actually
reordered or drop, how
do we handle that?
Right? So some of the
protocols actually
give us the ability
to handle that
specifically the TCP protocol.
Okay. And let's talk about
how the TCP protocol
actually enables
basically handling
packets arriving out of order.
So what do we need?
What sort of mechanism
do we need in order to
ensure that packets are ordered
when they are received?
We can take care of
ordering them when they're
sent because we have
control over that, right?
But then remember that
we let it loose onto
this network and
something happens in
the network and they can
actually arrive out of order
because they can take
different pathways.
There was a hand back there.
You need numbering
on your packets.
Right. So you need
numbering of the packets,
and that gives you a
detection mechanism
if they arrived out
of order, right?
So you can reorder them
on the receiving end.
The sequence numbers are
sufficient for us to handle
out of order arrivals, right?
Are they sufficient
for us to handle
dropped packets? No, why not?
What else do we need? Yes.
A packet.
We need some way to detect
that and know which one
we have to set out.
Yeah, so let's stop right there.
We need to first of all,
we need the mechanism
to actually
detect the fact that
a packet was dropped.
What is that mechanism?
Say it again. Yes.
So we have an acknowledgment
mechanism, right?
We have an acknowledgment
mechanism,
but how do we know when to send
the acknowledgment for
a particular packet?
Actually, do we send an
acknowledgment per packet?
Yes. TCP. Wait Yeah.
I where it came from.
Right. But what do you actually
encode as part of
your acknowledgment?
Does anybody know?
Yes. But for TCP,
the acknowledgment is the number
of the bite that
you expect next.
So it can actually also
acknowledge multiple
packets that way as well.
Yeah, exactly. Yeah,
that is exactly right.
So basically, what happens
is that you have a buffer,
receive buffer that you're
putting your packets in order.
The ability for us to order
receive packets does come
from sequence numbers,
as you mentioned, right?
But it's not enough for us
to actually handle draw packets.
Let's say it always work
through an example.
So let's say, I'm going to
draw here a receive buffer on
the receiving side and a send
buffer on the sending side.
So this is our well, anyway,
so this is host source,
this is host destination.
And we send one,
two, three, four, five.
And here, we've already
received sequenced
and reordered, one,
two, and then four,
well, actually, let's
say, four and five.
Right? And so now we want
to send an acknowledgment.
What we're going
to acknowledge is
we have the ability to
send the acknowledgment
for the whole prefix
that is ordered
without any missing packets,
without any missing
segments, right?
And so we're going to send
an acknowledgment back
saying we've already
received up until two,
and we expect three.
And that's how the
sending note actually
knows that three has not
arrived if it was sent.
Makes sense? Okay, so
we need an acknowledgment
mechanism. Yeah, question?
Well, to me to really stick.
Huh? How do you know how do
you know how do you know,
you have to send an at at
that specific moments? Yeah.
Yeah. So you're really
getting at what I
wanted to make sure that
I get to in this lecture.
It is super important.
And in fact, it's very, very
important from distributed
systems perspective as well.
Like, when Because this
is a control decision.
Action always is following a
specific control decision.
The control decision here was
to send an acknowledgment.
Right? But how does this
control decision happen?
How do we know when
this must happen?
And let me start even
from a simpler question.
A acknowledgments sufficient
for us to actually
enable reliability
and retransmission
of the dropped packets?
So sequencing is sufficient
for us to reorder.
And then the second mechanism
is acknowledgments.
Acknowledgments are sufficient
for us to acknowledge.
Are they sufficient for us to
handle the problems
of dropped packets?
Yes. The acknowledgment fast.
Huh? Acknowledgement getsrong.
Well, now you're getting
into the details
of the actual protocol.
We don't have time to
go that deep, right?
I want to build the
motivation for the timeouts.
So the timeouts here
and this notion of
time in these protocols are
actually really important.
And without having a
timeout mechanism,
you don't even know when to send
the acknowledgment mechanism.
The timeout mechanism also
answers your question,
by the way, as well,
because you can start
a timer on a source,
and if you haven't received
the acknowledgment,
and the timeout expires,
then you know that you just
need to resend it again.
Does that answer your question?
Yeah. And so it is not
sufficient for us to just rely
on sequencing and
acknowledgments alone.
We actually need
a notion of time
in the system and
timeouts in particular.
It is very important.
And as a matter of fact,
because it is a
very basic example
of a distributed system,
we are going to have a
distributed systems lecture
later on in this class,
where I'm going to prove to
you guys that without timeout,
we cannot even arrive at
any consensus in a
distributed system.
So that's really cool. You know,
without having the
ability to impose
a timeout on the sending or
receiving of your message,
you cannot even arrive at
any sort of consensus, probably.
Probably between these two
nodes. And this is insane.
So that's why whenever you see
a timeout or timeout
retransmission timeout,
it's just a mechanism,
but there's so much
depth to that.
In fact, mathematically
provable impossibility
results in distributed
systems that
depend on you to
implement that timeout.
Okay.
So people we kind
of mostly talk about TCP and
UDP in this class,
right, because why?
Because the examples of
two fundamentally
different protocols
with fundamentally
different properties.
And that's really what
I care about, right?
I care about properties
and abstractions.
So TCP, what does it provide?
It provides data reliability.
It gives us this notion
of bitstream interface.
You know, we just push
bites into the pipe,
and they just packetize
themselves and
reorder themselves
and retransmit
themselves on a specific time.
And their policies
associated with setting
the timeout and controlling
the acknowledgment mechanism.
It also gives us the ability
to avoid duplicates,
so we don't receive the
same packet multiple times
and it takes care
of drop packets.
UDP is an alternative to TCP.
It actually provides
the only guarantee,
which is that your data
has arrived uncorrupted.
At least we have that
kind of guarantee,
and it does that with checksums.
You data has arrived and
your data was uncorrupted.
But that's it. It
doesn't give us
any guarantees as
far as reordering,
retransmission, duplicates,
out of order arrivals,
or drop packets.
Why would we ever want UDP?
Yeah. Streaming information
where it's more useful to
just continue the stream
rather than paying
the overhead of resending
your phone call,
for example, you'd rather
just miss a section
of your phone calls
and have to wait for someone
to send that piece that
didn't get their original.
Yeah, exactly. So this has to do
with the property of the
workload in some sense,
right, the property of
the data that you send,
I should say, because in
this particular case,
let's say you're a gamer, right,
and you probably don't want
to slow down your game to
make sure that that
one missed frame
actually arrives and
is placed in sequence,
you just rather skip that frame
and move on to the next
frame, maybe, right?
I'm not a gamer myself.
Uh, so that you
actually have much higher
frames per second,
even if that one drame arrived
out of water and has
to be dropped, right?
So you'd much rather
have less guarantee,
higher throughput.
And so, oh, I just
gave it away, right?
So basically, the
disadvantage is
that it gives you
less reliability.
But the advantage
is that it gives
you higher performance,
typically,
because it doesn't have
to pay the overhead
associated with
actually imposing
all of these guarantees
provided by TCP.
So this is yet another trade off
guys that I want you
to think about, right?
TCP versus UDP doesn't
mean that one is better
or worse than the other.
It just means that there's
a trade off
associated with that.
It can be better or worse
for different scenarios,
and we want to be able to reason
through these trade offs, right?
Oh, it's 3:00. And I
guess that's where I'm
going to stop the lecture.
Thank you.