So actually
so it
would be unable to
All right.
Let's go ahead and get started.
We have a ton of material
to blast through today.
So I'm not even going
to remind you that you
do have a lab to do tomorrow.
Couldn't help myself.
At the end of last lecture,
we stopped at a specific
example we wanted to go over,
which is round robin scheduling.
And this round
robin scheduling is
the default schedule
in XV six, okay?
So let's go ahead and take
a look at this
example right here.
What you have basically
going top to bottom here on
the left hand side are
the various processes
with the tuple, okay?
The tuple consists of two parts.
The first part is when
this process arrived,
and the second part is
basically the duration,
the expected duration
of the process.
Okay. It says here,
arrival time burst time.
So what that means
is that this is when
the process arrived
into the system,
and the second
component is basically
how much time does it need
in order to complete.
Okay? And the Basically,
what you start out
with is the CPU is
scheduled to run process
one, P one here.
It only needs a single
time unit to complete,
so it completes the schedule
of switches to P two,
at time equals to one,
runs that for two
time units because
that's all the time you
needed, completes it,
switches to P three, o,
and runs that for
three time units
because that's the length
of our time quantum.
And then even
though it still has
one more time unit left
in P three to finish,
it nevertheless
switches to P four.
P four is round for three
time units right here,
and the total duration
that's expected for P four
is six and six minus
three has three remaining
units to complete.
And so it's not
done with P four,
but it's going to switch
to P five because it's
a round Robin
scheduler. All right.
And now we're running P
five for three time units,
and it's also not done.
And by that time, we are
at time equals to 12.
Okay, time equus to 12.
And by that time, we
have one, two, three,
four, five, five new processes
that entered the system,
so the round robin can actually
continue to the new
processes that arrived
into our runable Q
and picks up P six.
I picks up P six and runs
that for three time units,
not done with that, moves
on to P seven and
so on and so forth.
What are the problems here?
If any, does this
look like a perfect
scheduler to you guys?
So dark black color is
basically when the process is
actually running on a CPU.
Light gray is the time
that it is in the system,
in fact, in the runnable
state, but it's not running.
So is anything just
immediately jumping out
at you as an issue?
Yeah. That's switching.
Okay. But if the
switching cost is zero,
let's say, in this case, yes.
Psychos very small amount
of time but teaming
up for his initial is
still preempted to wait as long
as it basically scales up
the size of the queue.
Right. There's a large wait time
short time remaining efficient.
Right. So, what's
your name again?
Aman. What he is referring
to is this process P
three right here, right?
Notice that it only had a
single time unit to execute,
and it would be
completely finished.
But no, we moved on
from that process,
and we're not going to come
back to that process until
we took a full cycle
through the Runnable ue.
And you guys will see that when
you start working
on your lab three,
I know you're all locked in
on your lab two right now.
Actually, how many of you
are done with Lab two,
and you're actually
receptive to this material?
Oh, that's why you're
all here, right?
And all the empty
seats right there,
they're thinking
that they can catch
up on this after Friday, right?
Of course, I'm not going
to get a yes from them,
but maybe later because
it is recorded.
So, yeah, that's actually
a really good point,
and it's one of the issues
with the Round Robin scheduler.
Even though the system
actually has information
about how much work is
remaining in this
particular process,
and there are mechanisms
that we have at
our disposal to take advantage
of this information.
Nevertheless, the
policy itself sucks.
The policy is unaware of the
duration of the process.
The policy is unaware of
this additional information
that is provided
to us on input to
this policy algorithm.
Any other problems?
Yeah. Outside of
projects and onwards,
the pretty much take forever
to, like, actually read.
Right, yeah. So remember,
I told you guys,
we spent a whole like
last lecture talking very
high level stuff, right?
But that very high level
stuff really touched
upon some very fundamental
and important things.
And remember, once
and for the rest of
your professional or
academic careers,
right, it is very
important to reason
precisely about the success
metrics that you care about.
So here, let's say
the success metric is actually
an end to end response time.
How do we define it again?
We define it as the
time between when
the process into the system
and the process
out of the system,
fill in the blank, please.
Yeah, enters and exits
the system, right?
And so, basically, when
it enters the system,
that's its arrival time.
When it exits the system,
that's when it was
completed by the system.
And so that entire time
is end to response time.
If this is our success metric,
if this is our if this
is what we care about,
how do you think how well
do you think we're doing
with the scheduler?
Not great at all, right?
And so how can we
tell quantitatively?
Can you convince me
quantitatively that
we're not doing great?
Remember the CGF, right?
You have a list of processes.
For every single one of them,
you can write down a number that
corresponds to the length
of this rectangle, okay?
And you're going to
get a distribution,
and you can tell me what
the median is, right?
You can tell me
what the mean is.
You can tell me what
the tail latency is.
You can give me the
entire cumulative
distribution
function, a CDF plot.
Okay? Just by looking
at this one example.
And if I start asking
questions, well,
what if I do a shortest
job first, right?
Instead of this or shortest
remaining time first,
instead of this, right?
Then it's going to all of
a sudden change the success
metric that we care about.
It's going to change
the end to end
response time that we can
measure for every
single process.
Redraw the plot. Overlay the CDF
for the two policies
that you're comparing.
Figure out how does it
compare with respect to mean?
How does it compare with respect
to worst case performance?
How does it compare
with respect to
99th percentile or tail latency?
Do you see how cool it is?
And so I actually wanted
to write a quick and
dirty, you know,
Python simulator for this to
actually demonstrate that if
you switch between the policies,
give everything else constant.
This is your workload.
The workload consists
of the processes,
when they arrive
and how much work
they carry that needs
to be executed, right?
And on the right hand side, this
is basically your
set of resources,
which is a single CPU in
this particular case, right?
Both of those things constant.
The information provided to
the scheduler is constant.
Everything is
constant. All you are
changing is the policy
you're going to get.
You can get much
better performance
with respect to the success
metrics you care about.
Now, what if I told you that
those processes actually
have latencies?
All of those processes are
actually not just processes,
but they are
autoregressive decode
for successive token
generation LLM.
They actually have a TBT time
between Token SEO, right?
And that becomes a constraint
within which the
scheduler actually
has to run these tasks
in the system, right?
Is the Round Robin scheduler at
all informed about
this information or
does it does it make
its control decisions in
a way that's informed
of these deadlines?
No, right? So why
would we even want to such a
schedule in the first place?
What are the advantages?
Yeah. I think
you went first. The one
in the middle. Yeah.
Yes. Slightly longer processes
don't just take them all the
time. There's no starvation.
Okay, so basically starvation
free system, right?
Because we're
guaranteed to cycle
through them at some
fixed quantum of time.
You guys see that? It's actually
a pretty desirable property.
Like, for example, when you
show up to office hours and,
you know, there's like
ten of you, right?
And there's 1 hour, and
someone comes with,
I haven't even
started on lab two,
help me out here, and
someone says, Oh,
I have a very quick question on
this hand graded
assignment on lab one.
Do you want the entirety
of the time to go
towards the first guy before
the second person is serviced?
No, right? You want
some sort of round
rob in fairness here.
You want starvation
freedom, okay?
Because some of you, especially
with the short requests,
and you're going to experience
head of line blocking.
Scheduling is everywhere.
I'm telling you, you can
think about you can find
scheduling formalisms and a way
to think about everything
from resource
management perspective
if you start thinking
deeply enough.
So the advantages are
starvation freedom,
fairness, guarantees, and it's
also super simple, right?
Like, you can write this policy
in a couple of lines of code.
And in fact, that's
what Xpix does.
You know, it has like
two or three lines
of code that just iterates over
a set a set of bis
runable processes,
and it moves on to
the next one consecutively,
very, very simple.
In a single for loop.
We'll see that code.
The disadvantages we've
already discussed.
So let's just blast
through them real quick.
So the advantages are we
assign a fixed time
unit per process.
So that means we get to
every single student.
We kind of at least
give them a chance,
you know, to get
started on their task.
And if it's a short task,
we actually get a chance to
finish that task, right?
So there's no head of
line blocking here.
The starvation freedom.
He's a very good advantage of
round robin scheduling that
should not be forgotten,
but there are significant
disadvantages.
It does not distinguish between
the urgency or the
priority of the processes.
It's deadline unaware.
So if I were to impose the
deadline, it doesn't care.
You know, it's just going
to move on to the next one.
Do you guys know if any
deadline aware policies,
off the top of your head?
Yeah. What? Priority.
Okay, well,
it's a bit of a you can use
priority as a mechanism to
represent deadlines, right?
And, yeah. But actually,
you can use deadlines explicitly
in your scheduler
policy as well.
So anyway, this is
completely deadline unaware.
It doesn't handle the disparity
between throughput and
latency because
it's completely latency
insensitive, right?
It just does the simple thing
of moving to the next process.
So there are a bunch of
different ways we can think of
scheduling as I was
hoping you would sort
of appreciate by the
end of this lecture.
You know, what are some of
the other scheduling policies
we can think of, right?
Round Rob and FIFO.
So the E Ware policy I
was referring to is EDF,
earliest deadline first
policy. It exists.
It's actually fairly powerful,
especially when your resources
or workloads are
homogeneous, okay?
Someone, I think in the
middle row over there
mentioned last time
shortest job, right?
And there are two
variants of that.
You can actually
run shortest job
first by taking care
of shortest requests
in their entirety,
or you can be
preemptive and you can
do shortest remaining
time first, right,
by preempting them anyway,
but then prioritizing the tasks
that have the least
amount of time left over.
So if you were to go back here,
because let's say we're
context switching here, right,
from P three to something,
and if we're switching
P one and P two were
already done, right?
So what do we have
in the runable Q?
We have P three and we
have P four and P five.
P four and P five haven't
even started yet, right?
And so they have six
units of work left and
eight units of work
left respectively.
But our P three only
had one unit of work.
So the scheduler here,
if it were shortest
remaining time policy,
what would it do?
Yeah. Sorry?
No, no, Which specific process
would it conteate Yeah.
The PTN hasn't arrived yet.
Oh.
P two has completed. Yeah, see?
It seems like pretty
straightforward,
but you can't immediately
answer that question.
Two. It'll be P
three again, right?
And it's a bit of a trick
question because we've just
contact switched out
of P three, right?
Our time quantum has ended.
We finished running
a particular task,
whatever the hell it is,
right, for three time units.
And so we are contact switching
back into the kernel.
The scheduler context, we're
making a control decision,
who gets to go next.
Okay? What do we have
in the Runnable Q?
P one is out, P two is out.
P three is still there, P four
is still there, P
five is still there.
What is the shortest
remaining time?
P three, okay?
So we get to pick P
three again. Yes.
Like, is the time quinta,
like an interrupt,
it's like an external timer
that hits every time
the interruptus?
Yeah, basically,
you literally have
a software interrupt
that runs on a timer,
and it interrupts basically
whatever's currently
running on a CPU and
the handler for that
interrupt is the one
responsible for you to
switch between the
processes and the.
It's like a trap. It's a trap.
Yeah. Because without that,
the only option you have is
cooperative
scheduling and yield.
And we'll hopefully get to that.
If not this lecture,
the next lecture.
Okay. Are any of them ideal?
That's a trick question.
Can you just give me a
policy that is the best?
Why can't we just solve this
problem once and for all?
Come up with an algorithm that
just solves all
scheduling problems.
Yes.
Metric.
It depends on your
success metric, okay?
Right. So you need kind of
different that caters to
different success metrics.
That's correct. Anything
else that sort of
is problematic here? Yes.
It depends on your workload,
how long your jobs
are on average.
It depends on your workload.
Now, when you say
that on a test,
I will want you to be
more precise, okay?
When you say that,
I will want you to
think about the properties
of the workload.
Like what properties of
the workload do you
specifically have in mind?
And there are a couple of Oh,
you have an answer to that?
Yeah, I was just going
to say the priority
of the different schedules.
Now, see, there
was nothing about
priority in that
workload, right?
In Linux, you can assign
priorities. That is true.
But if I give you a
specific example like this,
priority wasn't part
of your input, right?
So be careful about that. You
don't always get priority.
And I don't have time
to talk about this,
but, you know, priority,
in my opinion,
is actually a shortcut to
implement policies like
earliest deadline first,
like the actual maximizing
value type of things.
It's sort of a proxy for
capturing those things
in a static way.
And it is sub optimal.
So I actually really don't
like priority based schedulers.
Yes. So is that a
property of the workload,
or is it the property
of the system?
Sort of a telemetry that you
could measure when you're
running the system in
steady state, right?
So that's part of the
telemetry of the system, yes.
Workload. That would be
a case where you want to do
something like short first.
But if you have
longer processing,
mix the shorter process.
Right. That's an example
where no longer.
Exactly. So basically the
distribution of job durations.
That's a most succinct way to
capture what you just said.
One of the properties
is the distribution
of job durations.
They could be, for example,
all completely homogenous.
Then you can very
tightly pin pack
them very tightly and you can
actually have almost zero
weight between those processes.
Or if they could be
heterogeneous and they don't
quite fit into your time
quantum and you
have to break it.
Right? Or anything in between.
And so depending on
this distribution,
you can sort of apply different
scheduling heuristics
will be more amenable to
those specific properties.
I should also mention
that interestingly,
a lot of people actually
miss arrival times.
So arrival time is
another property
of the workload, you know,
and only the workload
that has a huge effect
on the performance of
the system and scheduling
policy in particular.
But let's not get into
that right now. Okay. So
Well, it seems like it's
sort of an insurmountable
task, but we do have Linux.
We do have MacOS running
on your laptops,
clearly, they are doing
something and you have
thousands of processes running
there at any given
point in time.
How the hell do they
do that, right?
And they don't even
have any information
about the duration of
your tasks, by the way.
So what do they do, right?
Well, this is the enabling
motivations observation
that we can work with.
Processes that constantly use
full CPU are likely
lower priority
than those that mostly sleep.
Example here, sort of a
motivating example here is,
let's say you have a network
server that mostly sleeps,
but whenever you get
a network packet,
you want to process
it right away,
right, with high urgency.
Whereas, in contrast to that,
let's say you have a cron job
that just runs or a batch
job that has very high
arithmetic intensity,
but it doesn't it consumes
the CPU quite a bit,
but it doesn't necessarily
have that same kind
of urgency as a server
running in the bag.
Okay, so the idea here is
that as a CPU consuming
resource runs,
you want to reduce its priority,
right, and reduce priority
from processes that
always consume full CPU.
Yeah, you want to
reduce its priority,
and as the process sleeps
or doesn't consume the CPU,
you want to increase
its priority.
So let's see how that works
specifically in the
context of this example.
So you have two jobs. You have
a Jeep learning
training job running.
Horizontally, you have time,
vertically, you have priority.
Higher priority has to be
scheduled or has to be
prioritized, right?
And your Deep
learning training job
is a very long running job.
It occupies the
CPU all the time.
And so over time, what
we're doing is we're
going to lower
its priority as it keeps
occupying and consuming CPU.
Now here, we have
a periodic sequence of
activity coming from our
server that mostly sleeps,
but sometimes wakes
up because it
receives a request that
needs to be processed.
And this is, for example,
something let's say an
inference server would do.
An inference server would
basically get a request.
An image with a cat
that needs to basically
perform image classification
task on that request,
on that image, and return
an answer to the client.
And this is sort of
happening periodically.
It doesn't happen all the time.
So what we're going
to do is while
that inference server is
occupying CPU resources, right?
While it's doing that, we're
going to lower its priority.
But while it's
sleeping over here,
while it's slipping, we're going
to increase its priority.
And then we're going
to keep doing that.
As it's using the CPU,
we're going to lower the
priority and then increase it,
lower and increase it, and
so on and so forth, right?
And so the result of
this is that, of course,
depending on the properties
of this workload,
its priority is going to
remain pretty high while
this one is going to
start dropping off.
And so guess what's going to
happen when the new
request comes in,
while your deep
learning training job
continues chugging along.
We will do what with the
inference server task.
Yeah. Deep learning
training task
and take care of it first.
Right, right. Because
it's going to
maintain as high priority
because of the sort of
priority dynamics over time
indicated in the
red zigzag line,
right, is going to maintain at
relatively high
priority compared
to the Jeep learning
training task.
So what we're going to do if
we have a single
resource, right,
we will actually preempt
the Jeep learning
training job in
order to schedule our
inference survey task. Okay?
Yeah. Dynamic allocated priority
every single let's every time
the quantum window arrives,
you a let's reassess
which process should
be preempted or Yeah.
At every point in time,
do we add another stage
of priority to the
casks and then
just remove one from
the running one?
Basically, there are
some very efficient
algorithms that just in
order one complexity can give
you an estimate
of that priority.
So let me just go
through the next slide,
and I think it'll
capture the answer to
your question, okay?
So basically, what the
Linux scheduler does,
which is an example of a modern
high performance system,
it implements the
weighted fair queuing.
And what that does
is that it shares
the resources proportionally
to the process's weight.
So for example, you
have two processes.
You have an inference
serve task,
and you have a Jeep
learning training task,
and one of them is going to be
allocated higher
amount of weight.
And so if that
let's say twice twice
the amount of weight.
And if that is going to happen,
you will allocate
twice the amount
of resources to that task.
And the resources here are
spatiotemporal resources.
Let's say if you have one CPU,
you will probably
allocate twice as
many time quanta to that task.
Or maybe if you're allocating
multiple CPUs at the same time,
that process is going to get
twice the number of course.
Okay. And so CFS,
the completely fair scheduler
is the Linux's solution to
this dynamic behavior of
the priority of the
different tasks.
And it's an implementation of
the weighted fair queuing, okay?
So that's basically
what the Linux does.
It uses CFS.
Okay, and so I will
conclude the discussion of
scheduling by referring to
the hard and soft
real time problem,
real time operating systems
because I mentioned
them previously
and I just want to
complete that thread
of thought, right?
They are fundamentally different
because both of
them are SLO aware,
by the way, both of them
are aware of the deadline.
So that's one property that
these two operating
system types share.
Now, what is the difference?
The difference is that the hard
real time operating systems,
the situation there is
that they need to complete
critical tasks within a
guaranteed amount of time.
And if that doesn't happen,
you know, something
terrible happens.
There's going to
be loss of life.
Your drone is going to fall down
into the enemy
territory. I don't know.
There's something
that you really,
really don't want to happen.
And this is usually
something that is
applicable to various embedded
devices, medical devices.
You know, I've seen
your info cards.
I think some of you are actually
working on medical
device research.
So that's going to
be appealing to
you to look into hard real
time operating systems.
Now, soft real time systems,
they share the property
that they're SLO aware.
They are latency aware.
And they do want
those latency SLOs,
those latency deadlines
to be satisfied.
However, if they're
not satisfied,
right, it's sort
of less critical.
You can probably lose money,
you can lose revenue,
but you're not going
to lose a life,
or your drone is not going
to fall out of the sky.
Okay. So that's a soft
real time system.
And from a mathematical
standpoint,
there's a fundamental
difference here
because with hard real
time operating systems,
you treat a deadline
as a constraint.
Okay? So from anyone who's
looked into optimization
problem formulation,
you know, it has an
objective function
and it has a set of constraints.
Now, in hard real time, a
latency SLO is a constraint.
So it's a constraint
satisfaction problem.
In soft real time, we are
treating SLO attainment
as an objective function.
What that means is that
we are trying to maximize
the number of tasks for which
the latency SLO was satisfied.
Do you see the difference?
It's a very concrete
mathematical difference
between those two, as well.
And this is not
something you can
read in any textbook,
by the way.
Okay.
Yeah, I told you I can talk
about scheduling forever,
but we have to switch,
unfortunately, allow me a minute
to switch to a different
deck of slides,
which is the one that
I planned for today.
Okay. So today, we want
to talk about ordering,
waiting, and we've already
talked about scheduling, right?
So let's go back to our
synchronization primitives.
We've discussed locking and
what locking actually enforces.
So let's sort of contact switch
into that mindset again.
Now, why did we need locks,
and what do the locks enable
at a high level. Do
you guys remember?
Yes. Access, shared resources,
cross multiple screenton.
Access. Just access
to shared resources?
Because that's a
liveness. It's not
a safety property, right? Yes.
You, yeah. So it
poses relative atomicity
between two running processes.
Okay. Why?
How does that happen? So it
enables relative atomicity.
You basically jump to the end.
It is true that it enables
relative atomicity.
And that ensures the
safety property.
But how does that
happen exactly?
Yeah.
So it imposes, actually,
you're correct.
So it imposes some
sort of order, okay?
It imposes order in which
a critical section is
going to be accessed.
So it is true that
it's enabling access,
and it is true that it's
enabling relative atomicity.
But add those two
things combined,
what you actually
end up with is that
it ensures mutually
exclusive access,
first of all, right?
So put that qualifier
on your answer.
And second, it imposes
a dynamic order of
access that is safe to
the shared resource.
So let's consider those two
timelines, T one and T two.
And let's say we have
on the left hand side,
we have some critical section.
We're going to put
an acquiring release
around that critical section.
On the right hand side, we
also have a critical section.
Let's put an acquiring release
around that critical section.
And so with the logs,
we are ensuring that what are
we ensuring specifically?
We're ensuring that let's say
the block on the right hand
side is in its entirety,
either executing before or it's
executing after the block
on the left hand side.
Do you guys see that? That
gets back to the point that
he made about
relative atomicity.
In some sense, you basically
ensured that there's
this dynamic ordering that's
taking place between the
critical section axis.
Okay. So now the
follow up question
is whether or not I actually
need the locks to
avoid a data as,
because we were trying to avoid
the database in the left
hand in the previous slide.
Just as a reminder, it's
really important for you to
memorize the definition
for what a database is.
The database is
when you have two
unordered is to the same
location in memory,
so shared resource, right,
at least one of
which is a write.
If that is the case,
you have a database
by definition.
Whether or not it manifests
itself in your code
is irrelevant.
You still have a database.
And remember that there are
implications of that, right?
Be DRF zero says that if
there's a database,
all bets are off.
Okay? So whether or
not the database manifests
itself is irrelevant.
You will have a database
in your code if you have
two unordered accesses to a
shared location in memory,
at least one of which in
write is a right. Okay?
So do oxadOering we added logs.
First of all, did we take
care of the database?
The logs gave us the ability
to take care of the
database, right?
Yes. Are we sure of that?
Okay. The answer is yes.
The answer is yes. But
how did this happen?
This happened because
we actually imposed
dynamic order of access
to this critical section.
So we have ACS two X, ACS to Y.
We put the locks around it.
Remember, just to put that
on this slide as well.
And that sort of ensured that
one block executes before
or after relative
to the other block.
So this ensured
dynamic ordering.
So it provides us with
an ordering mechanism,
but this has a very weak
ordering semantics.
And I'm getting into some
advanced terminology here,
but it's actually
useful for you to
understand why we
need the next set
of primitives that we're going
to use for the purposes
of synchronization.
So the locks have a weak
ordering semantics.
And the weakness here comes from
the fact that the
ordering is dynamic.
So you don't know which one
is going to happen first.
It's either the first
one or the second one.
It doesn't really matter, right?
You don't have a strong
ordering guarantee.
And the reason why
this happens is
because you reduce the
space of possibilities.
Okay, Oh, Jesus.
Let's go through
this really quickly.
Take a look at this
code. You have a struct.
It's a typical, you know,
singly linked list
structure, okay?
You guys should be
familiar with this by now.
Then you have a global variable,
struct list over here,
and I'm sure you have that in
your lab two already, right?
And it's a pointer that's sort
of initialized to Null right?
And then you have this insert,
which now on its own,
local stack kind of
instantiates well,
with this malloc line 13
right here is going
to instantiate or
heap alloc data struct
element, right,
is going to then write
the data into data,
and then it'll make L next
pointer point to global list,
and then the global
list is going to
point to the thing that you've
just that you've just
heap allocated, okay?
Now, you have two threads,
T one and T two that are trying
to actually use this
at the same time.
So let's break
this down a little
bit at the course
of granularity.
So let's say T one at
some point is going to
create L one, right?
Then it's going to L
one next assign list
and then list assign L one.
And on the right hand side,
Thread two is also going to
attempt or even process
two, doesn't matter.
It's going to attempt
to create L two,
then L two next assign list,
and then list assigned L two.
What's the problem here?
Do we have a database?
If we don't have a
database, we're done.
Links because there's
no guarantees.
Okay, so when I ask
this question, right,
you may have an idea
of the right answer,
but the precision that
I'm looking for, right,
is going back to
the definition of
what the database is, right?
And what does the
definition say?
The components of
the definition,
they included some
sort of shared axis.
What is that, right?
The other components
are that two axises,
what are the two axises?
And then which one of
them is the right?
So in order to answer
this question on a test,
you would have to give me
those precise components
that match the definition.
So is anyone ready to do that?
Yes. Two other There
are two unordered operations
one next equals list
knows next equals list,
both of which are
light operations.
So first of all, what's
the shared thing here?
Right, right. So
the shared resource
is this list struct, right?
Do you guys see that
that's the shared thing.
Now, do we have two
axises to list, right?
This is the access to list.
This is the access
to list, right?
This is the access to list.
Now, is at least
one of them right?
Right. So now we've
satisfied those three
conditions of a definition.
And therefore, by implication,
truly mathematically, you
have a database, okay?
All right, so how do we this
is o, now let's
walk through this.
What can possibly go wrong?
You can create L two on
the right hand side,
follow the arrows, basically,
follow the arrows.
And let's say that
our execution was
serialized and interlafd
in the following fashion.
You created L two,
then created one,
then L two next assigned list,
and then you did an L
one next assigned list,
and then you did List asignL
two and list assignLO.
Is that okay?
No. Yeah.
You're going to lose something.
Basically, the bottom line here
is that you're going to
use one of the inserts.
Now, make sure you see that.
And I will take this offline,
make sure you take
this offline and
walk through this code
and make sure that you
trace this execution
and convince yourself
that one of the inserts is
going to be lost, okay?
Because here, the L two
next is now pointing to
the global list, right?
Then we make a one next
point to the global list,
and then we reassign list to
0.2 and list to 0.2 el one.
One of the updates
is going to be lost.
And that, of course,
is undesirable.
And the reason why the
interleaving happens is
because we have a
database condition
that we haven't done
anything about.
So let's do something about it.
Let's put locks around
the critical section.
And the critical
section here is,
of course, the read from a list.
To assign into next
and the right to
list on the left hand side
and the same thing on
the right hand side.
You want those two operations
that read and write
the list variable,
which is a shared resource,
you want those two operations
to be transaction, okay?
And so the acquiring release
slapped around those two things
is going to take care of it.
Now, conceptually what
you've done using
the set of locks is that you've
reduced a set of possibilities.
You've imposed this
dynamic order on
the execution of those two
relatively atomic
blocks of code.
Okay. Now, are there any
other ways to add ordering?
Because remember, I
told you that logs
actually give you weak
ordering semantics.
Do you need logs,
or is there some other way for
you to in principle,
add ordering?
Because try to conceptualize
what is happening.
What is happening is
that essentially you
have even outside of
computer science,
you have just a single piece
of thing that everybody
wants, right?
A resource that everybody wants.
And you don't want people
to compete for it.
You don't want the
consumers to compete for
that shared resource
simultaneously.
So you have to impose
some sort of ordering.
Ox is one way to impose
ordering with weak
ordering semantics,
but is it the only
way to do that?
So let's start thinking
of an example here.
Really help you with the
answer to that question.
Think of an example. So let's
try to build a producer
consumer queue.
You have two threads.
One of them is
a producer that sort of
adds elements to the queue,
and the other one is a consumer.
So what is the consumer doing?
As long as there are elements
to take, remove them, right?
But if there are no elements,
what we want the consumer
to do is we want to
wait for the next element to
show up to the queue, okay?
We want to wait. So the
concept here is the concept of
waiting that is not
really provided
to you by the locks themselves
because logs are mutexes.
They enforce mutual exclusivity
and dynamic ordering.
They do not give
you any ability to
wait until something
happens, right?
It cannot be given.
The concept of waiting cannot
be given to you by
using mutexes alone.
You need to have something else.
That will provide you with
stronger ordering guarantees.
Okay. And remember, when
I ask you to think about
sort of the if
something is wrong with
a particular implementation of
a multi threaded or multi
process application,
you need to think about
these three properties
that I already introduced
to you previously,
the safety property,
the liveness property,
and the efficiency property.
So let's try to
step through that.
So the goal here, again,
is a computer efficient
waiting primitive, right?
Because what you could have done
is you could have just put
a bunch of logs around on
the producer side and
the consumer side,
and we'll get to
that that slide.
You actually see the code for
this very specifically written.
But what's going to happen if
you just use logs
without waiting?
The consumer is going to spin,
waiting for the element to
be deposited into the queue,
and it will have to
endlessly keep checking
for that condition
of whether or not
the queue is empty before it
can pop the element, right?
So if that's the
implementation you're
going with, do you
have liveness?
Can the system make progress?
That's liveness. Good stuck.
Okay, let's get to that in
the context of this example.
But I want you to start
thinking about this.
Do you have liveness?
Do you have safety?
Do you have efficiency, okay?
And that's going to be one
of the ways that we'll
try to implement the producer
consumer relationship.
So here, the motivation
is for us to introduce
a different
synchronization primitive
that's not just a mutex.
I'm trying to convince
you guys that
just a mutex alone is
insufficient because it has
weak ordering semantics,
and it's also inefficient
in terms of computation.
Okay? We want something
that is much more
efficient that will simply
allow one of the threads to wait
until some interesting
condition becomes true.
Okay? So let's go through that.
So we need some way
to wait efficiently.
So our main weighting
primitive that I
think a lot of you already
familiar with is a
condition variable.
Have you heard about
a condition variable?
Have you used the
condition variable before?
Okay? Now, just like in
all the previous lectures,
I asked you this question and
then expect to be mind blown.
And hopefully we'll achieve this
by in the next 10 minutes or so.
So the traditional interface
that sort of gives us
the ability to use condition
variables is the weight.
You pass a lock, okay?
And this weight primitive allows
a process calling
weight to go to sleep,
and as it's sleeping,
it releases the lock, but if
it wakes up, it
holds the lock back.
Remember that? So
how many of you
are familiar with this interface
for conditional variables?
So you guys have used
conditional variables, right,
but you don't necessarily
remember what the interface
for conditional variables
is, right? Okay, good.
So this is going to
be useful then to go
through this example.
Then you have a
second primitive,
which is really important,
which is a signal.
And the responsibility of
the signal is to wake
up one of the waiters.
So if any of the
waiters is sleeping,
you need to have a mechanism
in order to be able to wake
up that sleeping process
because how else is it
going to get out of sleep?
You see that? Once a
process goes to sleep,
it cannot wake itself up.
There needs to be an external
mechanism that wakes itself up.
And that external
mechanism is a signal.
So the weight and signal
are operating like a pair.
Now, the variant of a signal,
which is not
a necessary condition,
but it's there, right?
Is a broadcast because you
can wake up all the waiters.
So it's a primitive that gives
you the ability to wake up every
single one of the
processes that's
sleeping on a particular
conditional variable.
All right. So can we write
a producer consumer cue
using the conditional
variables and the lock?
So now, please
work with me here.
This is supposed
to be interactive.
We have a producer on
the left hand side.
We have a consumer on the
right hand side, right?
The producer is trying to push,
the consumer is trying to
pop and return a variable.
Does this work
what you currently
have on the slide?
Really quickly?
No, because Data ase.
Thank you. Yeah, I wanted
to hear that, okay?
So we've tried to take care of
a database by putting the
set of locks around this.
We've protected
the producer push
with a set of locks.
Is this sufficient?
No, because we still have we
still have a database, okay?
No, that's a trick question,
but we still have a database.
Now, let's put the
set of locks on
the right hand side.
Did it take care of it?
Why not? Uh huh.
Because the consumer can pop
when the queue is empty, right?
So is that a liveness violation?
Is it an efficiency violation
or is it a safety violation?
Safety. Okay? So this
specific problem
this specific solution
has a problem
because there's a
safety violation.
How do we resolve this?
We don't want the pop
to happen if the queue
is empty, right?
Okay, yeah, so we've
gone through this.
Okay, so let's try to put
a NIF statement right
in front of that.
If the queue is not
empty, then pop.
Does that take care
of it? Oh, come on.
Can somebody say yes? All right.
Why does it not take care of it?
Let's see. I want more people.
Yes. Checks.
And pushing checks.
So this is actually the kind of
implementation that
you could have, right?
When I mentioned that you
can implement it with
locks and wi dering
semantics, right?
This essentially
makes the consumer
busy wait until the
queue becomes non empty,
and when it becomes
non empty, it can pop.
So do we have liveness?
We have liveness because the
system can make progress.
The producer can produce,
the consumer can consume.
I don't think there's
anything preventing
the producer or the consumer
from making progress.
Do we have safety? We're not
blowing up when the
queue is empty, right?
If the queue so let's see.
Let's go through all
these scenarios.
If the queue is
empty, what happens?
And the consumer is going to
release the lock and it's
going to basically get out
of the consume call, right?
And so it unblocks the producer.
There are no deadlock
situations here.
There's no circular
dependencies here.
Everything appears to be
fine with respect to safety,
right? But is it efficient?
Oh, why? Yeah. Like consumer
can talking schedule.
And in that case,
you're never going to
us and just keep on scheduling
it acquiring lock in.
Yeah, so basically in
this particular case,
the consumer is having a
problem with efficiency, right?
Because it's simply
spinning and constantly
checking unnecessarily
checking the queue,
even though the queue may only
sporadically receive an element.
This is highly
inefficient, right?
So what we want instead is
we want to use a weight
primitive and go to
sleep if there's
nothing in the queue.
Okay? So notice how I
change the code on the
right hand side in case
you haven't noticed the consumer
is now checking is if
the queue is empty,
I want to go to sleep, okay?
And remember, just
as a reminder,
the weight takes a lock
as a parameter and
is going to release the
lock while it's sleeping.
But in order to get out
of the weight call,
it's going to
reacquire the lock.
So we're holding the lock
when we're calling
the weight, okay?
And we're holding the lock
when we're getting
out of the weight.
But while we are blocking
inside the weight,
the lock is going to be
released, okay? Now,
Did that take care of it?
Do we still have safety?
Do we still have liveness?
Do we still have
We got efficiency.
We solve the efficiency problem.
I think we're fine
with liveness. Yes.
I don't think there's liveness,
there's a deadlock that can
happen. What's the deadlock?
We're not signaling after
we push. You guys see that?
So what's going
to happen is that
the consumer thread is
going to go to sleep,
but is there anything
that's making it wake up?
No. You need both of
them for the system
to operate exactly.
Yes. Quick question.
Yeah. Why is it wild?
Because we didn't get there yet.
Okay. We need a signal, okay?
Now, you don't answer
that question.
Are we done? Yes.
Because if multiple threads
are waiting on a signal,
they might all wake up and
they're all collectively
at the same time.
So we need to continuously
check if the is empty.
Mismck I see.
Okay, there's usually a
simpler there's usually
a simpler problem
that people identify.
Have you heard of things
like spurious wakes?
No. So you will
definitely hear it in
the context of X XV six.
There are these things called
spurious wake ups that
can make a process wake up
from a weight primitive,
even though there was
no signal or broadcast.
And so what happens if
the consumer actually
sits in a wait and then
spuriously wakes up,
and there's still
nothing in the queue.
And it's going to
proceed to pop, right?
I'll just use a laser pointer.
So basically, right now,
the consumer is sitting
in the wait, okay?
And there's a spurious wakeup.
We woken up. We have
woken up from the weight,
and we proceed to pop,
but the queue is still empty.
So that violates the
safety property.
So spurious wakeus definitely
cause a problem in
this particular case.
So that's why, well, actually,
but even if there's
no, uh, Right.
But even if there's
no spurious wakeup
heard that there's still
actually a problem.
Now let's assume that there
are no spurious wakeups.
If there are no spurious wakeus,
there's still a problem
with this code.
Now, as he mentioned
on the far left,
what happens is that if you
have multiple consumers,
right, we can actually
construct a scenario where
we have a safety violation.
And in the interest of time,
normally, I would have
you think through it.
But in the interest of time, I'm
just going to walk through what
the safety violation
here is unless
somebody wants to give
me a safety violation.
So if you were to get this code,
and you have one producer
in the left column,
two consumer threads in
the middle and the right,
can we construct a scenario
that violates safety?
Yeah. Us if one
consumer wakes up and
then pops from the queue,
then the other consumer
gets signal and comes
out and tries to pump
it's already empty.
But if one consumer
wakes up, right?
And pops and what? Does it still
hold the log or does
it release the lock?
It releases the log.
Okay, so then it
released the log,
okay, so it got out of the
critical section, then what?
The other consumer
Where was it before?
What was consumer to doing?
Waiting. So you're saying
both of them were
waiting, right?
Okay. Now, why would the
second consumer wake up?
We're not doing a broadcast.
We're doing a signal. Okay.
What determines which
consumer wakes up the signal?
Undefined. There can
be some policy, right?
Maybe, but this is
actually irrelevant.
It can be undefined. Yeah.
Calling CD signal in there
will take both of the consumer
wants to call CD weight log.
Both try to acquire
the log to wake up.
Only one of the signal
the definition of signal is that
it wakes up exactly one sleep.
Yeah, we're not
doing a broadcast.
So I'm giving you
this definition.
Signal wakes up
exactly one sleeper.
Now with the broadcast, I think
the far back, you
would be right.
If they're both waiting, right?
If they're both waiting and
you're doing a broadcast here,
that would be another
safety violation.
So I actually don't
think that you
gave an answer to the
original question.
So nobody knows
what the answer is.
What is the safety violation?
Yes.
Keep on signaling the consumer.
That you keep on signaling?
Uh huh. Yeah, it's possible.
It's possible. Yeah.
So it is actually
possible for one of the
consumers to never wake up.
But that would be like
a scheduling problem.
It's sort of a starvation
of a particular thread,
where we can construct
a scenario, I guess,
where the consumer to
just gets extremely unlucky
and it just keeps
getting stuck in wait.
And we always prioritize,
let's say, consumer one.
Let's say we wrote a brain
that scheduling policy, right?
And it just always
schedules a lower PID.
For a consumer. And then
we've introduced a
starvation problem,
but that's not a
problem with this code.
That's a problem with
the scheduling policy.
A very interesting observation.
They do work in tandem,
and the combination of
those two things can
actually create safety
issues as well.
Okay, so here's what happens.
All right, so you
have a producer
and you have two consumers.
Now, producer is
indeed signaling.
The producer is
Now, let's imagine
that consumer one
is actually in the
weight right here.
Consumer one is in the weight,
and remember when consumer
one is in the weight,
the lock is not held,
okay? And it's sleeping.
And so it starts to go through
the wake up procedure.
It starts to go through
the wake up procedure,
but hasn't acquired
the lock yet.
Consumer two is for
whatever reason,
scheduled by the
scheduler. Consumer two.
So sorry, producer signaled
and unlocked, okay?
Signaled and unlocked.
So consumer two got out.
This triggered C one to
start a wake up procedure.
The wake up procedure involves
locking the lock and then
getting out of the
blocking wake call.
But it hasn't had a
chance to do that yet.
C two comes in, grabs the
lock, checks the queue.
The queue is not empty,
pops and returns.
Okay? Now the queue
is empty, right?
And C one finally reacquires
the lock because the lock
is not held by anyone.
And pops a queue and
there's a safety violation.
Okay?
So that can actually happen.
So what I'm trying
to tell you is that
you can get really funny
interleavings here,
even if you don't
have spurious wakes.
And so this really motivates
what someone said
in the beginning,
I think that was you, why
are you not using Wil?
You really need to
be using a Wile.
And the While will
take care of that,
but you didn't know why.
And this class is
all about the why.
Yes. Wakeup same time. No.
So while we'll take care of it.
So basically what
you're checking here is
that while the queue is
empty, you go back to wait.
So this takes care of
spurious wakeus, right?
You woke up, you check
the queue, right?
You woke up for whatever
reason, I don't know.
Including the spurious wake up,
maybe you were signaled, maybe
you were not signaled,
doesn't matter.
Just check the queue and see
if you can pop something.
If you can pop something great,
if not, go back to sleep.
That takes care of
that. It also takes
care of the situation that
I have just described.
That's the solution,
right? Are we done?
So the answer is we are done.
Okay? This is the
correct solution.
So when we wait, we really
need to do that in a while loop.
Please remember that forever.
If you didn't know that, this is
a very important and
useful thing to know.
And this is actually do
we need to be in the Wil
loop because of a data as?
Or do we need to be
in the Wile loop
because of a race condition?
There was actually no in
the interest of time,
I'm just going to give
you answers, right?
There's no data as in
that particular case,
but there is a race condition,
and so that's why we needed
to introduce a wild Loop.
Now, where should I
place the signal?
And I promise this is
going to be my last slide.
Where should I place the signal?
So we have a couple of options.
Now, the produce
the consumer code
is the bottom right hand corner
just for your reference, okay?
It's not going to
change. Now, there are
three different ways that
we can write the producer.
We can put the signal where it
was right after push, right?
Can we put the signal outside
of the lock and lock?
I will reason through this, yes.
Someone can signal
to you. I think.
But is that a problem?
Because the purpose of
the signal is to make
sure that it's to
guarantee liveness.
Without having a signal
one time when you
didn't have a signal,
that was a liveness
violation, right?
Because nobody would wake
up, nobody could wake up.
But if some consumer woke
up for whatever reason,
they're going to consume
that element that
you've just produced.
So that's fine, right?
Now, can we put the signal
before this critical section?
No, right? And here's
how to think about it.
Here's what we are
trying to achieve.
What we are trying to
achieve here, guys,
is we're trying to establish
this happens before
relationship between a
producer and a consumer.
So in other words,
making it a little
bit more concrete.
We want to make sure that
the push happens
before the pop, right?
That's what we would
like to achieve.
Now, how do we do
that? So that's
sort of what we would like to
enforce. This is our goal.
And we do that by introducing
these two synchronization
primitives that work in tandem,
the signal and the weight.
And by construction, by design,
the signal and the
weight already have
a happens before relationship
between them, right?
Because the signal is going to
complete before the
weight completes.
We by construction have
designed a pair of primitives
in such a way that it
gives us this happens
before relationship.
Now, as long as the push
happens before the signal,
and by transitivity and
the weight happens
before the pop,
by transitivity, you're going to
have push happening
before the pop.
Do you see that? So let
me walk through
that one more time.
This is by construction.
We already have an edge.
This happens before
relationship graph.
It's a graph, okay?
We're just putting in the
edges into this graph,
and there are four vertices,
push, signal, wait, pop,
push, signal, wait,
pop. We have an edge.
Okay? We want to
ensure that there's a
path between push and
pop in this directed
acyclic graph
in it happens before
relationship graph.
Okay? Now, as long
as the push happens
before the signal and the
weight happens before the pop,
by transitivity, you're
going to get that path.
So anyway you put push and
signal relative to each other,
to make sure that
this holds true,
we have ensured that there is
a happens before relationship
between push and pop.
And that's where I'll
end the lecture.
Thank you.