It's a
r.
And
I
so
far.
All right. Good
afternoon, everyone.
Seats.
So, you know, at the time
I sort of prepare for
the lecture and come here and
I get the lecture started,
I think to myself, Wow,
you know, you guys are
in it for a treat.
And it literally happens
almost every time.
You know, I said that
for the VMM lectures,
right, you're in it
for a treat, right?
Then I said that for
the previous lecture,
you're in it for a treat.
And as I was preparing for the
schedulers lecture, again,
I sort of come here
really motivated
and really excited to
talk about schedulers.
Um, even though a
lot of you might
actually think that
schedulers are boring,
just judging from where everyone
is looking at right now.
Someone is looking
at their phone,
someone is looking
at their laptop,
and not a lot of people
are paying attention.
But as a matter of fact,
schedulers are, in
fact, everywhere.
You know, the more you
think about scheduling,
the more you can think of it
as a basic building block of
the Every fabric of
our society itself.
It is ubiquitous, right?
And if we talk about
systems in particular,
scheduling is actually
a very often overlooked
underdog in systems research.
And there's a reason for that.
There's a very good
reason for that.
The reason for that is because
people think that scheduling
is a solve problem.
How many of you think that
scheduling is a solve problem?
How many of you think
that scheduling
is an unsolved problem?
Okay. Okay, good.
So there's a handful
of people who think
that there's still some work
to be done in scheduling, right?
And so if we rewind the
clock back 14 years ago,
when I was starting
as a PhD student,
I wanted to work on distributed
operating systems that
sort of changed the way we think
about operating systems in a
cloud computing environment.
Cloud computing was what it is,
like what LLM is today,
back in the day right?
Really exciting, very popular.
Everybody was thinking about
it in academia and industry.
People were implementing it.
Startups were popping up,
just offering various
cloud based solutions.
And so one of the issues
that Cloud computing needed
to solve was scheduling.
So I started working on
resource management,
slash scheduling aspect
of Cloud computing,
slash distributed operating
system at the time.
And people were thinking that
I must have gone mad, right?
I read too many papers or I
have a bad advisor who
sort of didn't advise
me to to give up on
that area of research.
But I ended up writing
my entire dissertation
on scheduling.
You would not believe, right,
how deep I went on that topic,
going all the way back
to the early 1900s and
reading books on
the theory of value
and finding various
interesting connections
with communitorial optimizations
and communitorial actions.
And topological geography
and things like that.
So you can actually go quite
deep into scheduling
if you really want to.
And at the time,
I was also interning at Google,
and I had numerous
conversations,
actually at Microsoft
first, Google second.
I had numerous conversations,
especially with some
of the Google people
who were literally
working on Borg.
Okay. And we had
these furious arguments about
the approach you
would have to take.
You have to take with respect
to efficient scheduling on
distributed environment
or distributed
set of resources that Google
had to schedule their jobs over.
And we're going to get
to that when we start
discussing the success metrics
later on in the lecture.
And so the reason
I find that people
have arguments in
general, actually,
specifically systems arguments,
but any kind of arguments,
even political
arguments, is because
they have a fundamentally
different set of assumptions.
So if you actually think about
it and you put all emotions
aside and you try to reason
through any kind of argument,
you will ordinarily find
a difference in a set of
assumptions that the
two parties are making.
And what are the set
what is the set of
assumptions that people are
typically making
with scheduling?
Well, one of them is that
you have a lot of resources,
and so whatever you
do is fine, right?
There are some examples
of that, for instance,
populating the West Coast.
You could think of it as sort
of first come first serve
land grab type of
scheduling, right?
Would that work on
the East Coast?
No. Why? Because there's
fewer resources,
more people. Okay?
So that must have something to
do with the patterns
of the workload itself
with the properties of
the resources and
how much resource
there is to schedule relative to
how much demand there is
for that resource, right?
Another set of assumptions
that people would
typically make,
especially a decade ago is
the heterogeneity of the
resources or hetero sorry,
homogeneity of the resources.
Basically, they're all the same.
They're malleable. And so if
I gave you K resources from,
let's say this rack and K
resources from that rack,
they're indistinguishable
from each other.
And that if you make this
axiomatic set of assumptions,
then that is different from
your own, then of course,
you're going to think
that you're dealing with
a very simple system for
which there have been
decades of research,
especially in the HPC community,
including operating
systems community as well.
Okay. So we're still on
the very first slide,
and there's already so much
said about scheduling.
So imagine what the rest of
the lecture going to look.
So going back to the
initial set of assumptions,
we need to basically it
forces us to go back
to the initial set of
assumptions anytime there's
a fundamental tectonic
shift happening,
and you need to as
a systems research,
you need to identify
those tectonic shifts.
And you need to go
back to first of all,
figuring out what
those assumptions
were because oftentimes
they're very
implicit and people are making
those assumptions unaware of
the fact that they're
making those assumptions.
So you need to externalize
those assumptions first,
and then you need to figure
out whether this axiometc
base has changed.
So the TLDR here is
if you're working on
something fundamentally
deviates from
what everybody else
is doing, okay?
Do not let anyone tell
you that what you're
doing is wrong because
oftentimes you might simply be
operating on a different
axiomatic base.
So that's sort of a moment
of inspiration for you.
Administratvia.
In sharp contrast a
moment of respiration.
Your lab too is
due in three days.
Now, back to the Earth.
Three days is not a
lot of time, right?
If you haven't submitted,
and I know that there are
a lot of groups that
haven't submitted.
I looked at the
submission history.
Please do so ASAP.
You may or may not
realize that you only
have 15 submissions left
before the deadline.
Maximum. That's what
three days means.
Three times five,
equals 15, okay?
And people do spend more than
15 submissions to get it right.
On average, it will likely
take that many submissions,
if not more, to actually
pass all the tests.
Your last supervised lab is
tomorrow on Wednesday
before the deadline.
Make sure you come to the
lab, prepared with questions,
figure out what it is is not
working or part two of the
lab or whatever, right?
Talk to the TAs.
They're there for you.
Um Okay, Lab one.
Despite the delay, the
grades are now out.
The course staff, I should say,
worked really hard to get
this feedback back to you
in time for it to be
useful for lab two.
So I know that you're
all locked in on your
lab two right now,
and by the way, thank you
for showing up to lecture.
You know, I heard that people
have a tendency to skip
lectures when the lab is due.
So I'm glad to see you all here,
but we'll see what happens
on Thursday, right?
So basically,
we try to make sure that
we give you the feedback,
especially on the hand
grading of lab one,
so that you have a chance
to sort of look at
it and incorporate it as you're
working on your lab two.
And one more thing.
I already posted this as
an announcement on Piazza,
but just wanted to
reemphasize that in lecture,
the exam one is scheduled
for Tuesday March 11,
same time, same place as
the section you're in.
I E this section, okay?
And again,
try to it involved
a lot of discussion
with the core staff.
And the reason for this is
because March 12 is actually
the withdrawal deadline,
three or 4:00 P.M.
I can't remember the exact time.
And so we want to make
sure that we try to give
you that feedback on
your Exam one before
the withdrawal deadline so
that you actually
have a chance to kind
of make informed
decisions accordingly.
All right. Any questions
about administratvia?
There's going to be,
there's one more bullet.
There's going to be more detail
on what Exam one is
going to look like,
et cetera, but it will be in
class and it will
be on your laptop.
And so you have to make sure
that you bring your
laptop charged.
I noticed that there
are no chargers
integrated into the desktops,
which is a little
bit concerning.
So maybe you should start
testing how long
your laptop lasts.
For example, I see a
lot of laptops open.
See if it actually lasts
through the 50 minutes
that you're in class.
If it doesn't, you
may want to bring
a charger and sit somewhere
on the side, okay.
We'll see if we can try to
provision some power cords,
but no guarantees there.
Again, boring logistical
details, but important, right?
Stay tuned for more
detail on Exam one.
So let's start with
this question.
I sort of prefetched
that a little bit with
my preamble on the first slide.
Why do we need
schedulers, right?
Have you studied schedulers
in 2,200? What did you learn?
Yes.
Loops that can be used.
Different scheduling
algorithms like what?
Round Robin.
Okay. What else?
First come first search. Uh huh.
Okay. Okay. Okay. Did you talk
about sort of the trade offs
between those
different policies?
Yeah.
You did. Okay. So what
are some of the Actually,
before we get into
the trade offs,
sort of why do we need
schedulers in the first place?
Could you get away and get
along without schedulers?
So in other words,
another way to ask
this question is,
when do we need the schedulers?
Do we always need schedulers?
Are there some contexts or
some situations in
which scheduler
is actually not necessary?
One of those assumptions
that we make
is that schedule
is always there.
Doesn't have to be always there.
Doesn't always have to be
there, you're not dealing with
a system that has multiple
threads or multiple process.
Sorry, could you say it again?
If you're not dealing
with a system that has
multiple multiple threads
happening at the same time.
I see. So you
mentioned two things,
actually, which is quite
interesting, right?
You mentioned
multiple processors,
right, and multiple threads.
Or did you say processes?
Process.
Processes. Okay. I thought
it was a little bit
more interesting.
But yeah, you're right.
Basically, if you
have multiple this
works too, right?
If you have multiple consumers
of resources that you
need to deal with,
right, and they're
all competing.
They all need resources,
then this is sort of one of
the necessary conditions
where you need the schedule.
If you only have one process in
the system, to
your point, right?
Do you need a schedule?
Sounds pretty
obvious, but it is there.
I don't think you do, right?
I don't think you
need a scheduler.
Okay, well, let's try to
extrapolate that a little bit.
If you have two processes and
two CPUs or two cores,
do you need a schedule?
Unlikely, right?
And why is that?
Yes. Ah.
So basically, you can
allocate one CPU to
each of the processes,
and then you don't need to
multiplex between them.
Ah, I think I gave it away.
So what are we looking for here?
Here are the properties of
the situations where the
schedulers actually make sense.
The properties are as follows.
You need to be in a situation
where you have multiple
resource consumers.
And by the way,
I'm going to make
an analogy here with an
economic system because
an economic system
is also all about
actually scheduling
resources that
you have access to, right?
And who gets access,
how much access do you get?
And what are the priorities
associated with people
getting access?
What are the mechanisms
associated with
distributing access
to shared resources?
So once you think about
scheduling long enough,
everything sort of becomes
a scheduling problem,
including economic theory.
So just like in the
economic theory,
we have multiple
resource consumers.
We have multiple
consumers, right?
That sort of
necessitates a set of
mechanisms to share
those resources.
And in addition to this,
the second sort of
necessary condition that
necessitates schedulers
is a scare set
of resources that
we're sharing between.
Right? So if you
had an abundant set
of resources and only
a few consumers.
So, relatively speaking, fewer
consumers than there
are resources to share.
Then in some sense,
you sort of, you know,
throw everything at
the resources and
someone everybody will land with
a sufficient amount of
resources without any schedule
interposing on the control flow
of your application, right?
So we're looking for
those properties.
And so together, it sort of
should remind you of
something that we've
already discussed in the
context of at least one
other vertical or
one other subsystem
in the operating system kernel,
I E virtual memory
management, right?
There are multiple consumers
of those physical frames.
There's a scare set
of physical frames,
and we need to perform
what function of an
operating system
in order to accommodate that.
Yeah, we need to ensure
isolation and we need to
multiplex between them, right?
So schedulers are
basically a mechanism
for us to actually provide
support for multiplexing,
the scare set of resources
between multiple resource
consumers in the system.
Okay? So do you see how we
sort of reason through,
even though it may be
obvious in retrospect,
a lot of things are in systems.
We reason through the
need for schedulers in
a very systematic way by
looking at the properties of
the situations where
you actually need
such a thing because
such a thing called a
scheduler is not free.
You're imposing some additional
complexity into the system.
You're kind of adding
an additional component that
you need to be able to write,
you need to be able to maintain,
and it has some overheads
associated with
running and interposing on
the control flow of
your applications.
So there must be a really
good reason for that.
So that's why you need to
step back and sort of
think to yourself,
do I even need a schedule
in the first place, right?
Okay, so it's one of
the mechanisms in the
operating system that
enables process isolation
and resource multiplexing.
And basically, it also
provides us with a way to
ensure fair access
to the resources and
provides us a way to ensure
reasonable or high
resource utilization.
Okay? Because you don't want to
end up in a situation
where, for instance,
let's say you have two
CPUs and two processes,
but for some reason,
because there is no scheduler,
the processes are
actually getting
scheduled on your core
zero every single time.
Right? And so this
leaves the second core
completely underutilized.
So it's sort of a bad allocation
decision in scheduling.
And that can happen, actually.
When you start writing programs,
you will see that often
because the CPU zero,
the first core is
sort of a default core where
all the processes
get instantiated,
you may actually with the
poor scheduling policy
or in the absence of having
a scheduler in the first place,
you may actually end up in
a situation where all of
your process is running
on core zero, right?
So that sort of speaks
to the second bullet
right here that we also need
schedulers to ensure good
resource utilization.
So the schedule is
this arbiter, right,
between the consumers and
the producers of resources or
the providers of resources
that provides us with the
ability to sort of go through
this matchmaking process that
enables some of
the properties for
the consumers and some of
the providers.
And the consumer properties,
they are, you know,
fairness, and there's a bunch
of others that we're going
to talk to in a moment.
And from the resource
perspective, it's, you know,
oftentimes resource utilization.
That we care about.
Okay? So you can have
a mental picture of consumers
and providers or I call
them producers
because they produce
capacity and the properties
that we want to enable
with the schedulers,
both on the left hand side
and on the right hand side.
Okay, this is a little
bit too abstract,
but bear with me for just
a couple more slides.
So we've established that we
need schedulers in
order to mount.
Now, what do they schedule?
What are some of the things
you can imagine scheduling,
given everything that
we've discussed so far?
Oh, man, time flies.
Let's go quickly through
this. What are we scheduling?
Okay, processes, is that it?
Yeah. IO. Do I have that?
Okay, yes, I have that.
We can schedule discs.
Okay. And specifically, disc
requests like IO, right?
What else can we schedule?
That's it?
Have a couple of more. We can
schedule network requests.
We can schedule basically
resources on a cloud system.
We can schedule things like
machine learning, right?
And we'll get to some of
the examples of what
I mean by that.
And so, given this, you know,
given the set of things
that we want to be
able to schedule,
what is the goal of
a scheduler then?
You know, can somebody
sort of take a step back?
I know you've
studied Round Robin.
I know you know your FIFO
and first come first
serve and all of these
other interesting policies.
But then the question is, what's
the goal that we're
trying to achieve?
How do you know
that the schedule
is actually doing a good job?
Versus a bad job? How do
you take one scheduler
versus the other and actually
compare their performance? Yes.
Like, reducing wait time.
Huh? Rducing wait time.
Okay, reducing wait time.
Is that the only thing that you
might be optimizing for? Yes.
Spotting the amount
of work done.
Right. So more generally,
in cases when you
are having a conversation
about a scheduler,
you want to maximize
the amount of
work that you care about, right?
And the care about part can
be extremely heterogeneous,
and we'll see lots
of examples of that.
So it comes down to reasoning
about a measure of success
for your scheduler.
And there's a whole,
laundry list of
different kinds of measures of
success that you may
actually care about.
And in each one of those cases,
we always want to
maximize the amount of
work that we care about.
Okay? So that's kind of
a very general statement
of the scheduling goal.
So specifically,
here are a couple of
things that we might
want to maximize.
We might want to maximize
throughput, right?
So that's sort of referring
to throughput scheduling.
A good example of that is
a disc or basically
scheduling accesses,
reads and writes to disc.
And so depending on the policy
that you actually
implement for disk access,
the performance can
actually be orders
of magnitude different, okay?
So it's a huge function.
So it's a function of
the policy itself,
but even fixing the policy,
it's a function of the
access pattern to the disk.
And so let's see here.
Are you even familiar with
the discs that had
rotating platters?
Because they don't
use them anymore.
So I'm just wondering if you
still have that notion of
rotating platters and
in a disc, right?
They used to manufacture
them as near perfect mirrors
in almost like fab
lab equivalent type
of pre sterile environments,
and they would put them
together and they would
allow them to rotate.
And so the actuation delay to
enable the rotation of one of
those platters was a
significant overhead, right?
And so because of that, it
actually made it necessary to
change the scheduling
approach that
you use with disc scheduling
versus process scheduling, okay?
Because with process
scheduling, for instance,
the actuation delay of
switching between request
one or process one and
request two or process
two was much lower
compared to switching
between disk IO requests.
Okay? And so that's
how sort of the notion of
the elevator
scheduling was born.
And why was it even called
an elevated scheduler?
Why do you think an
elevated scheduler
is a good fit for
disc scheduling?
Yeah. I remember from 2,200,
if you grab it out the way
that you traverse the disk,
it kind of goes all the way
up and then all the way down
to how elevator works.
Okay. Yeah. Anybody else?
Is that you agree
with that? There was
another hand that came
up over there. Yes.
Takes longer to different I
guess
enter access everything
on the Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So you're basically getting
the general idea here.
And the general idea,
the analogy between an elevator
and disk is the following.
That in an elevator,
typically what happens is
that an elevator okay,
here's a hypothetical
thought exercise.
Imagine an elevator using
a first come first
served schedule.
Would you like an
elevator like this in
your building? Why not?
First come first
served. Seems like
a very fair thing to do, right?
Very commonly
utilized scheduler.
What's the problem with that?
Yes.
Because the elevator
is doing a lot of
movement which does not serve
as many people as
it potentially can.
Like if the elevators moving
in a certain direction.
There's people who press it on
the way, it wouldn't
stop for them,
but rather go to the next
person be anywhere
in the building.
Right, right. So
that's exactly right.
And another way to say
this is that basically,
there's a non trivial
amount of time that it
actually takes to service
a particular request,
and there's an actuation delay
to switch between requests.
After both of those
two things combined,
make a set of
policies like first come
first serve or round robin,
for that matter, a
very poor policy.
So what you want to
do is because there's
a significant
overhead associated
with moving the elevator,
this cyberphysical system
in the first place, right,
you might as pick up
all of the requests
along the way as you're
servicing the previous request.
So in other words, the elevator
will stop and pick up all of
the requests that are
heading in the same
direction as the request.
It's already in progress
of being served.
Okay? Same thing with the disk.
Basically, what the disc
schedule is trying to do is it's
trying to batch reason writes
and reorder reason
writes for that matter.
We're going to talk
about that when
we get to file systems,
which is another super
exciting module in this class.
Reorder reads and writes in
such a way that it actually
maximizes the number of reads
and writes it performs as it
services as it performs
a single spin
operation on the disk.
Okay? So there's an
implicit assumption here.
I wanted to make a point that
the implicit assumption was
the heavy overhead
or actuation delay
associated with switching
between the requests.
So people rarely talk
about assumptions.
This is the class
where we talk about
assumptions and trade offs
and overheads and
things like that.
CODA elevator doesn't
work like that.
It works differently.
So what happened there?
Why is it not using an
elevator scheduler?
Are you guys familiar
with a elevators?
Okay. So basically, it's
a system that is much
more rare where you
come to sort of a
centralized control panel
and you press a floor
that you want, right?
And then you wait, and it
tells you which elevator
shaft to go to.
Okay? And so you don't just
press an up or down button,
just like on the
normal elevators.
You actually have
a control panel
where you specify which
floor you want to go to.
And then after some
non trivial amount of
time, typically in seconds,
but nevertheless, it tells
you which elevator
shaft to go to,
okay? So it's different.
It's much more sophisticated.
And this sort of gives
a very interesting
intuition or insight
into the declarative requests
where you're specifying
real requests to
the serving system
in a declarative fashion.
You're saying that my request is
that I want to go
to floor 15, okay?
With a regular elevator,
the elevator doesn't
know where you're going.
Knows that you're going up or
down in the best case
scenario, right?
With this one,
you're declaratively
specifying your intent,
and it uses this information
to make better bashing decisions
and therefore
maximize throughput
given this declaratively
specified information.
So do you see how much
depth there is just
by talking about trivial
things like coda elevators?
I don't know. I
think it's exciting.
Um, but let's move on.
So scheduling to minimize
response time.
Social media feeds.
Actually, not just social
media is already
pretty outdated.
Everybody knows it's
bad. Don't use it.
But there are other
things like ARVR
headsets, for instance, right?
Any sort of thing that
has a response time
component to it.
If you're writing a
scheduler for that system,
you need to make sure
that your requests are
serviced in an interactive
response time fashion.
Because if you don't
do that, basically,
you start losing users.
There's going to be
a disassociation.
There's going to be user
drop off and things
of that nature.
Um, you also have schedulers
that maximize latency
SLO attainment.
What the hell does that mean?
SLO stands for service
level objective.
Latency SLO is typically
a deadline or latency
slack or budget that you
are given within which
a particular request
must be satisfied, okay?
So notice that it is
actually qualitatively
different from the
second bullet point,
the minimizing response time,
because in the
second bullet point,
we're treating response time as
an objective function
to minimize.
In the third bullet point,
what's the difference?
We have to satisfy the
specified deadline.
So let's say the deadline
is 36 milliseconds and we
did our request in 35
or 15 milliseconds,
does it make a difference?
No, because in both
cases, we've satisfied
Line, right? So we're
trying to satisfy
a specific latency constraint.
So it's a constraint
optimization
problem in the third case.
So examples here
include ad serving.
For example, when
you're loading a page,
the ad serving platform, right,
has a specific latency
deadline within
which it needs to
figure out what is
the most appropriate
ad to serve, right?
And if it fails to do that,
then you're not getting
a really good ad.
And so you're going to
severely impact your
click through ratio.
You click through rate,
which is really important for
revenue, obviously, right?
So when you start thinking
about these things, okay,
let's use a more modern one,
the LLM intertken latency.
Large language models,
they have this process called
oro regressive decode.
And as you are generating
tokens, basically,
you have intertken
latency or the amount of
time it takes for you to process
subsequent tokens, right?
So there's actually a latency
SLO attached to that,
and it's called the TBT SLO,
time between tokens is slow.
And my lab is writing
schedulers, in fact,
to actually maximize
latency SLO attainment
in the context of
large language models,
catering to that TBT SLO.
Okay, another example is
scheduling to minimize cost.
I can talk about this for hours.
Okay. And so one of the
let's skip this slide.
I just dit it today. I wanted
to say that basically,
at the end of the day,
you can't have all
three of the faultjecture.
You cannot have all three
of simplicity,
performance, and cost.
Usually, you can get two out
of three, but not all three.
And this really applies
to schedulers as well,
because oftentimes you
can solve the problem by
throwing resources at it
or by increasing cost.
And you can also get good
performance out of this,
but this is complex, right?
Or you can get performance
and simplicity,
sorry, performance and cost.
So cheap and performant,
but this requires complexity.
And so there are basically
different examples that show
up in scheduling where you get
two out of these three
vertices, but not all three.
And there's this famous
systems conjecture that
tries to capture that.
Okay, let's talk about latency
distribution functions.
How many of you know what a
probability distribution
function is?
What Oh, good, good, good.
What about cumulative
distribution function?
Okay, do I need to go over that?
Okay, what is a cumulative
distribution function?
How would you define it?
I think a PGF is a simpler one.
Yes. The variable takes
on a value or less value.
Right. Generally,
it's this, right?
And more concretely,
thinking about this from
the perspective of the
Y and X values, right?
You have Y here,
you have X here,
and your Y equals to
the probability that
your stochastic variable X
is less than or equal
to a lower case X.
So that's the accumulative
distribution function
definition, right?
In our case, why is it relevant?
Well, it's relevant
because this is how
we're going to measure
end to end response time.
In Lab three, Okay?
This is how we're going
to measure latency.
And the reason for this is
often because you
get different to and
response time as a
function of the task
itself and also the policy
that you apply to
service this task.
And we will see that with
the example of Round Robin.
And basically, as you
service your requests,
they are kind of on
a timeline, right?
So you have a
timeline, like this.
That's your T. And your requests
come and at some
point they complete.
And for each of those requests,
you have this TSA B, right?
And so these TSA Bs are
all going to be different.
That's your no and response
time, not arrival time.
Enter and response time.
So you have a list of
enter and response times for all
of the requests that
entered the system.
So obviously, given this list,
you can construct the probability
distribution function,
which means you
can also construct
a cumulative
distribution function.
That's going to look
something like this.
Okay? It's monotonically
increasing by definition.
Okay. Now what is tail latency?
Does anybody know
what tail latency is?
Tail latency stems
from, you know,
the definition of a probability
distribution functor
Let's say it's a normal.
And so the tail corresponds to
kind of the tail of that
distribution, right?
And where would
this tail show up?
Because this is your PGF,
and this is your CGF.
Where does your tail
show up in the CGF?
Yeah. Why equals one?
Yeah, close to, by
the way, this is one.
This is one. And it
does not intersect.
It just kind of approaches
and it stops somewhere, okay?
Because this is your
worst case performance.
That means that this
corresponds to if I
were to ask you about
questions about the CGF,
you should be able to
know it inside out, okay?
Because if I ask you what does
this point correspond to?
That's basically that's
the max of the list of
the enter and response
times that we talked
about over here.
That's your maximum latency that
was observed by
the system, okay?
Now, the tail is
basically the behavior
of your system around here.
So the tail has to be specified.
So for example, people normally
talk about 99th percentile.
So that's 0.99 on this
graph right here.
And basically, you try
to figure out, okay,
where does it intersect with
my cumulative
distribution function,
and the X value corresponding to
that intersection is your
99th percentile latency.
Okay? Now, why do we
care about tail latency?
We care about tail
latency because a lot of
the online platforms are heavily
dependent on the
tail performance
of the system
because for that 1%,
if you did not satisfy
their latency SLO,
they will drop off
your platform.
They'll go somewhere else.
You know, instead of Amazon,
they're going to go shop to
Ebay or something like that.
Not that familiar with
online platforms,
so you have to forgive me.
Maybe Facebook Marketplace,
something like that, right?
And so there's a very
clear financial penalty
that you pay if the tail of
your distribution actually
doesn't satisfy the
latency SLO that is deemed
reasonable to keep the users
engaged with your platform.
That's why we care about
tail latency slow.
I'm going through
this rather quickly,
but let me just show
you one graph here.
This is a cumulative
distribution function
for latency end to end response
times in the system that
we actually built in
my lab for serving
inference requests for
machine learning tasks, okay?
And the behavior of
the actual forward path
is highly predictable.
And so the question is,
where does the
distribution come from?
Right? If you have
a particular task that
always gets executed,
let's say in 20 milliseconds,
well, in a specific
number of milliseconds,
a constant number
of milliseconds,
how do you get a
distribution, right?
That's not that actually
is wider than that
particular constant value.
Well, you get that distribution
because there's
actually some amount of
waiting that happens in
addition to this request
being serviced as well.
Okay? That happens because
your enter and response time
is not just your service time.
It's also a combination
of your waiting time
plus the service time.
Do you guys follow? Okay.
Using this as a
this as an example,
let's say this is your
99th percentile and
the 99th percentile latency
happens to be 35.67.
And your latency SLO is 36.
Okay? So your 99th percentile is
less than or equal
to your latency SLO.
So this is what we
would refer to as
tail latency or very
high percentile latency.
And over here, let's say
if we have a deadline,
let's say 36 milliseconds
in this particular case,
you draw that as a
vertical line and
figure out where that intersects
with your latency CGF.
So in this particular case,
let's say we had a latency
SO of 36 milliseconds.
Okay.
So here stepping back
from the CDFs and
PDFs a little bit,
let's go back to thinking
about scheduling scenarios.
So let's say you have two
different CPU
scheduling situations.
In one of them, you
have long running jobs,
and in another one, which
is completely separate,
you have very short
running jobs.
So what kind of
schedules would you
want to use for your
long running jobs?
Yeah. Round.
Why? Because if you just
do a sequential schedule,
I guess, it's gonna be a wait
time range plastic huge.
Uh huh. But if you do a
round robin scheduler.
And with Round
Robin, Round Robin
has this specific property,
right, which is what?
Do you run them to completion
and then do a round robin or
do you do something else?
You preempt them, right?
And so, basically,
when you have long running jobs,
basically, think about this.
Would the first comfort serve
scheduler be a good fit here?
No, right?
Because like he said, sir,
what's your name?
Ashwin. Ashwin. Yeah.
So Ashwin said that it
would not be a good idea
because it would induce
a lot of wait time for
the long running jobs
that have already arrived and
are simply waiting
for their return.
They're making zero progress
until you've completed and,
in fact, our experience
in head of line blocking.
There's this, you know, very
important and famous kind
of bad property of
schedulers called head
of line blocking.
And so, unless you're
using preemptive
schedule in this
particular case,
you would be subjecting them
to head of line blocking.
And what about the very
short running jobs?
Do you want to preempt
them frequently?
What kind of scheduling
would you want
to use with very
short running jobs?
Yes. Shortest job and shortest
job remaining time. Right.
So basically the idea
here is shortest
job remaining time.
Okay, and again, this
implies that the shortest
job remaining time
or shortest job first has
this property of what?
Is it going to be preemptive
or non preemptive?
Would you want it
to be preemptive?
Preemptive. Yeah. Say non
preemptive because the cost
of actually switching would be
more than just completing
the job. Exactly.
So at that point in time,
you have to start thinking
about the overhead
associated with the mechanisms
that your schedule is using.
And so you mentioned
two things, right,
because you just
happened to know
the algorithms for them, right?
But you didn't know that
one of them actually
requires the schedule to be
preemptive and the
other one does not.
Right? So you've learned
something new today.
So the shortest job
first does not require
the scheduler to be
preemptive because
you basically take
the shortest job and you
just run it and you can
run it to completion.
But shortest remaining
time implies
that implies some sort of
preemption happening, right?
Because it's talking
about the remaining time
in a task, okay?
And so, you know,
think more deeply
about these policies that
you have learned in 2,200.
So, right.
So there are some other examples
like delayed scheduling,
which actually made
it into a conference,
and it's a very, very
simple construct.
And the idea there
was to basically,
instead of making the
placement choice for
a task right away,
we basically allowed
this task to
wait for some specified
fixed number of seconds,
let's say, 5 seconds, right?
And it did wonders. It did
wonders because in those
5 seconds, magically,
if that task had any
sort of preference,
preferential treatment
of resources,
let's say a 100 versus
H 100 nodes, right?
Or H 100 versus H
200 nodes, right?
Within those 5 seconds,
that task would actually have
a higher probability of
getting its preferred
placement, obviously, right?
The more you wait, the higher
the probability you have of
actually getting your
preferred allocation.
That's very clear, right?
But this is the first
example that you're
seeing that makes a non
work preserving decision,
because instead of placing
something right now,
because you have the resources
to run their task right now,
you're making a non work
preserving decision
by delaying the
scheduling decision,
expecting something better
to happen later on.
And that's when it
becomes interesting.
Those are the kinds of
conversations I was having with
Google Borg team and
telling them that sometimes
you want to wait.
And they were thinking
that I'm crazy
because why would
you want us to wait
if we have so many
billions of dollars
invested into these
data centers?
Don't we want to keep them busy?
It's really hard to argue
with that question, right?
But the answer is, it depends
on how you're keeping them busy.
You can keep them busy in
efficient or inefficient manner.
You can give them
preferred allocations with
a slight non work
preserving delay, right?
Or you can try to be very eager,
and this is a lazy
allocation, by the way.
This is an example of
a lazy allocation.
Or you can be very eager with
your resource allocation,
and of course,
you reduce the probability
that your task is going to get
a preferred preferred
placement choice.
Power of two choices. How
many of you have heard about
Missen MacherPower of Power
of two choices out of Stanford.
Very simple policy.
Almost trivial, okay?
So basically, you have
a bunch of notes,
and you're simply instead
of doing Round robin.
So if you have a
bunch of resources,
the Round Robin policy
would essentially give
you a anyway, we'll
get to Round Robin.
I don't have time
to get into that.
The Power of To
Choices basically
tries to test two nodes and
try to figure out which
one of them is less
loaded and we'll send the
request to that node.
Seems straightforward, it
reduces the complexity from
O N to 01 with respect
to the number of
resources to consider.
Okay, which means that
the scheduling performance
is extremely good,
is highly efficient, and it
also has provable guarantees.
You can actually prove
some guarantees about the
par of two choices policy.
But there's an implicit
assumption here.
What implicit assumption
is it operating on?
That's not even discussed
in the Mitzonmachers paper.
That the jobs are going
to be short, okay?
In other words, and
in other words,
what I'm trying to build
towards is this
concept of fluidity.
Basically, the shorter
the tasks are,
and the smaller
are the fragments
of resources that they ask for.
So basically, the smaller
is their spatiotemporal
granularity.
The more liquidity you
have in the system,
and the easier it is
for you to actually
come up with very simple
policies because if
let's say you have buckets of
resources for buckets
corresponding to
resources and your tasks are
basically sand and you're
just kind of sifting sand and
moving your hand like this.
It's very, very easy
for you to actually
accomplish near perfect load
balancing by doing this.
And it doesn't even matter
what you're doing with
your hand because you have
so much fluidity, you know,
so much liquidity in
the fine granularity of
the sand that you're trying to
distribute across the buckets.
Now, if you're dropping
bricks or boulders,
this is going to be a completely
different story, okay?
Because you may have
made a very bad decision
a couple of times
and all of a sudden
your bucket is
overflowing. Does
that make sense?
And so this concept
was really what I
was kind of exploring in
my tetrasct work that
was published at
US is 2016 with spatio
temporal Bin packing,
and we're going to have a
lecture on this later on,
basically after you're
done with your exam too.
And so we'll have a whole
lecture talking about this.
I'm not going to spend
time on this right now.
So what should I consider
when I build a scheduler?
We need to think about the
costs of scheduler, right?
Because there are costs
of interposing on
control flow because you
need some time for
the scheduler to
run that has its own
complexity, right?
And what are some of
the other costs associated
with scheduling?
So this used to be a discussion,
but we just don't have
time for discussion.
Very briefly, what are some of
the costs interposing
on control flow?
Yeah. Huh?
Yeah, yeah, context
switching, right?
When you're context switching
between processes, you
have to save stay.
So if you're context switching
between ten millisecond tasks,
and let's say for the
sake of the argument,
the overhead associated with
your context switching
is ten milliseconds,
is it worth it?
You have just reduced
the utilization
of your system by a
factor of two, right?
Might as well let them run
and maybe or maybe change
the granularity with which
you're interposing on
control flow in this
particular case, right?
What are the costs
of interposing
on control flow and
costs of scheduling?
Why do you want to schedule?
Why would you not want
to schedule, rather?
What are the disadvantages?
What else is happening?
I'll give you an example,
right? You have two processes.
Let's say that they have
an identical runtime.
You have one core, right?
And let's say that each
of them runs a second.
And basically, you have
a couple of options.
In one of the options,
your time quantity
is ten milliseconds.
So your contact switching
every ten milliseconds
between those two processes.
Another 100 milliseconds, and
yet another one is 1,000
milliseconds or full second.
Which one is going to
be more efficient?
Why? You only have one switch?
Like the overhead
from one switch.
Yeah, so the overhead
is one thing.
But actually, it
turns out that we
got the overhead to
be pretty efficient.
So it is definitely
a consideration that
you want to put in
the answer to that
question, right?
But this is actually not
the most expensive part of
switching between the tasks.
What else is happening when
you switch between the tasks?
You guys are experiencing
this in lab two. Yeah.
That's our cache.
Yeah, exactly. So basically,
your data cache is going
to be swapped out, right?
Especially if one of the
tasks is memory intensive,
or if both of them
are memory intensive,
they're going to
basically stomp all over
their data cache when
you context switch.
It's not going to
happen in its entirety,
but it will happen to so extent,
depending on the memory
intensity of the process.
Now, what is going to be
swapped out in its entirety?
Yes. TLB, right?
You guys are doing
this in your lab, too.
TOB is going to be swapped out,
and TLB why is that a bad thing?
Why is that a problem?
Every single time.
So every ten milliseconds,
if you decide to contact
switch between them,
your TLB is going to swap out.
Why is that a problem? I mean,
you already know the
answer to that question.
Yeah. This translation
process takes over.
Yeah, because then
you're going to have
to do the page table
works and repopulate
the TLB for the task
for the process that you're
swapping into, right?
You just got it flushed. Okay.
So context switching, we
already discussed this.
The caching costs, the
schedule of time complexity,
because depending on the policy,
the scheduling complexity
can be either order
N or order N M or order one,
or we can actually talk about
different complexities of
different scheduling
algorithms in
your copious spare time, right?
For example, what was
the scheduling complexity of
the miss and MahersPower
of two choices?
You're scheduling one task.
So you've already imposed
the order on tasks.
You're considering tasks one at
a time in a FIFO fashion, right?
So if N is
the number of tasks and M
is the number of resources,
what's the scheduling complexity
of the power of two choices?
What? No.
We're making two choices, guys.
We're making always
like a fixed number
of choices from the set
of resources, right?
And we're looking at
how loaded they are,
and we're picking
the less loaded one.
So what's the
complexity of that?
Of one, right? And
so it's beautiful.
It's beautiful because you
have regardless of how
many tasks you have,
regardless of how many
resources you have,
the complexity here is O of one.
Tetris Cat had combinatorial
complexity, for instance.
And so that was a
significant concern
that I had to deal with, right?
And this complexity may
or may not make sense.
For example, if
you're scheduling
402nd jobs cloud in a
distributed cloud environment,
thinking for 4 seconds
corresponds to 1% of
the end to end duration
of a job, right?
And so that 1% is going
to be insignificant.
It's going to be a
drop in the bucket.
Right? But if you're spending
a second thinking in
the scheduler to
schedule 1 second tasks,
then you're doing
something wrong.
It's 100% of the duration
of the task, okay?
And so the scheduling time
complexity matters a lot.
And so when you're
implementing your lab three,
you're thinking about
your schedulers.
Don't think about two
processes. To processes.
Think about 1,000 processes,
2000, 10,000 processes.
And what's going to happen to
the time complexity of the
scheduler design that
you come up with.
Another one is predictability.
So that's the one we talk
about the least, right?
But it's one of my
favorites, actually,
because predictability is
a very rare commodity
to have in systems.
And it's nearly
impossible to build
an operating system with high
degree of predictability.
So much so it is so
hard that special
there's a separate
discipline for
this called real time systems.
And I don't do real
time operating systems.
We'll talk about the
difference between
hard real time and soft real
time operating systems.
I deal with soft real time
operating systems in my lab.
Now, given all of this
and all of these overheads,
there are benefits, right?
We are able to get better
resource utilization.
We are able to basically achieve
more work on the tasks
that we consider
important or give
priority allocation value
to the work that we
consider of higher value.
We're also able to provide
stronger quality of
service guarantees or
stronger QS properties.
Without scheduling, this
would have been impossible.
So the takeaway is that
hopefully by now, you know,
50 minutes into the lecture,
you're convinced that
we're dealing with
a huge design space that's
induced by all of these
scheduling considerations, okay?
You might want to think about
throughput versus
latency, right?
Am I optimizing for throughput?
Like megabytes per
second, task per second,
queries per second, in the case
of Lo leminfen serving, right?
Or am I optimizing for latency?
Basically, am I trying to
minimize the latent end
to end response time?
You have to think
about fairness, right?
Basically, are you in
a situation if you're
starving some of
the tasks or some of the tasks
with specific properties like
long jobs or short jobs,
for instance, and
fairness typically
comes up in a very
interesting way
in a heterogeneous context,
if you have heterogeneous set of
resources to schedule or
heterogeneous set of tasks.
You need to think about
whether or not you want
a schedule that's pre emptive
versus cooperative, right?
And whether or not you want
to design a schedule to
be global versus local.
Now, what does that mean?
The fundamental difference here
is resource state visibility.
For example, if you have
a distributed system
that consists of multiple nodes,
you can actually have multiple
local schedulers that
only have local resource
state visibility, okay?
And then they periodically
communicate with each
other in various ways,
if at all. Okay?
They don't have to.
Or you could have
a central central global
centralized scheduler
that actually sees everything
that's happening with
your resource state.
So it sees every single
core is every single GPU,
and it is able to interpose on
the control flow of all of
the tasks that you're
trying to schedule.
Presumably, with a
global scheduler,
if you didn't have to worry
about the complexity of
the scheduler, okay?
Because it can grow as
a function of M and M,
as I mentioned previously.
If you didn't have
to worry about that,
presumably, you can make
better allocation decisions.
And I've shown that
in my dissertation.
But there is a cost
associated with that.
Need to worry about scalability.
What does that mean?
You know, it's not just a word.
It means, how many jobs or
tasks you do you have
the ability to process?
So basically, how big is the
N and how big is the M that
your scheduler is
capable of supporting?
And you need to worry
about the performance
of the scheduler as
I mentioned, right?
Then granularity,
both with respect to time
and with respect to space,
we've already discussed, right?
Because the final
the granularity,
the mental model
that you should have
is that you're dealing
with sifting sand.
It's much easier to schedule.
And using the time quantum or
time slide, as an example,
you might want to
think about whether
or not it's more
beneficial for me to
have much smaller time quanta
or much larger time quanta,
or maybe I want to
set it dynamic.
And if I want to set my
time quantum to be dynamic,
what sort of systems
performance telemetry do I
want to look at in order to make
this control decision of
setting a time quantum?
Because clearly it is essential
to the performance of my system.
You want to think about
constraints, you know,
are you dealing with some
real time constraints?
The latency SLO that
I mentioned previously,
like deadlines, right?
You know, are you running
this system on an
embedded device?
Something that runs on an
airplane, for instance.
And basically things related to
resource starvation and
performance consolidation,
like what you would
see in the Cloud.
So scheduling is hard.
You have to deal with
all sorts of complexity.
You have to deal
with heterogeneity.
There's no perfect universal
solution or policy.
And the reason for this is
that you have to deal with
contradicting and
heterogeneous goals, okay?
And anyone who tells you
that scheduling is simple,
they simply don't know what
they're talking about.
If you go out there and
you start writing and
building real systems and
you're responsible
for scheduling,
you will find contradicting
and conflicting goals, in fact,
that you have to be
responsible for supporting,
like maximizing throughput and
minimizing latency
at the same time.
That's a fundamental systems
trade off that you
have to deal with.
Or minimizing response time
versus maximizing scalability.
Or you want to assure fairness
while at the same time,
making sure that your
schedule scales, right,
or maximizing
resource utilization,
like in the case of the Google
conversations that I had.
They wanted to see
their resources fully
utilized because if they
are not fully utilized,
they believe that they're
wasting money, right?
And they're not wrong, right?
But there's a nuance
associated with that.
Um, versus maybe you
want to maximize well,
I guess, in this case, you want
to minimize energy consumption,
or if you want to treat power
as the power envelope sort
of as a function of time as
your constraint that you
need to schedule within.
So all of those
considerations just kind
of come together as
a perfect storm and
dropped onto a small handful
of people usually who are
dealing with scheduling as
part of their life job and
day to day operations.
There are many
potential solutions.
You've heard a couple of
policies that were discussed.
We're going to go over one of
the policies in a little bit
more detail in the next class,
the Round robin policy.
And the reason for this is
because I want to
demonstrate just how bad
the round robin policy
is depending on what success
metric you care about,
and we start this
discussion on Thursday.
Thank you so much and I
hope you enjoy scheduling.
I