All right, everyone.
Good afternoon.
As.
So during the last lecture,
I can't even remember what
today is, Thursday, right?
Okay. During the last
lecture, in any case,
we finished off by making
this key statement that
interrupts are a mechanism that
we have for concurrency.
Do you guys remember that?
So we talked about interrupts.
It all seemed somewhat boring
and mechanismic, right?
But then we actually
discussed how interrupts are
actually fundamental for us to
be able to do so many things
in our system, right?
And so this is where
actually as a sidestep here,
if I may, you know, a lot of
the system design is
actually like this.
There are people
who received turing
awards for things that are
in retrospect, so obvious.
But the reason
they're so obvious
is because it wasn't
always obvious, right?
Someone came up with
something that sort of became
so commonplace, like
polymorphism, right?
Everybody Yeah, of course,
polymorphism makes sense.
But somebody came up
with that, right?
And in retrospect, it's
obvious because it sort of
became a natural component
of your curriculum.
But that's exactly what
we're looking for
in system design.
We're looking for
these things that
seem almost trivial interrupt.
Trivial. But then, you know,
what you should be looking
at is, what does it enable?
You know, what are
the things that we
can do with this mechanism?
What is the policy space
that's actually
enabled by these very,
very simple and therefore
elegant things.
So today, we're going to
talk about concurrency.
Uh let's see.
How many of you are
excited about this course?
Okay. So for those of you
who I saw not everybody
raised their hands.
And for those of you who are
not yet excited by this course,
you know, this
lecture is going to
get you really excited, okay?
We are in the
business of blowing
your mind in this class,
and this is going to be one of
those lectures where
you'll be mind blown.
At least 98% of you
will be mind blown,
maybe a couple, maybe three
students will not be,
but I think the
98% will be, okay?
We're going to talk
about concurrency from
the perspective of how we
build concurrent primitives,
how do we properly
handle concurrency,
why it's challenging,
why it's hard.
What is the
conceptual model that
you need to have in
your mind in order to
actually reason about the
properties of concurrent code?
Okay, because instead
of just trying to think
about the interleavings of
your multiple threads
at the same time,
I will actually attempt
to give you a kind of
a more conceptual way of
approaching these problems
so that this skill
is transferable
beyond this
particular course and
so that you can take that
with you to your senior year.
Okay? So let's see.
Oh, yeah, sure.
So basically, just a few
bits while people
are still coming in,
please take a seat.
There's plenty.
I strongly recommend submitting
tomorrow for lab two, right?
Not going to dwell
too much on this.
I think you all know what
happens if you don't.
I mentioned that on Tuesday,
and please do try to submit
both parts of the lab.
And the reason for this is
because even if you do feel
confident that your approach
to solving Lab two is correct,
there will be use cases that
you may not have thought of.
Part of that actually does have
to do with concurrency, okay?
And we're going to talk
about concurrency today,
so hopefully that'll be helpful
for your lab two, as well.
It will take multiple attempts.
If you are actually implementing
your lab from scratch,
which you should be, right?
And it will take some
strong unit testing,
which hopefully you guys
have actually attempted
to do in your supervised labs
yesterday, is that correct?
So yesterday,
the supervised labs were
supposed to be focusing
on helping you out
with thinking about
how to test your labs.
Was that helpful or is that
not what happened yesterday?
Anyone? I will ask my TAs.
How many of you found the
yesterday supervised lab
helpful for lab two?
How many of you found it
not helpful for lab two?
Okay. All right.
So remember that we
have office hours,
piazza support, and if
you're feeling stuck,
please reach out.
And the reason I
mentioned this is
because I personally
have witnessed
the common case failure
scenario kind of
being rooted in procrastination
and not just that, right?
We all susceptible to
procrastination to some extent.
But procrastination
specifically driven
by hesitation to ask
questions, right?
You might think, Oh, somebody's
going to think that I'm
stupid and you have
this you know,
you think you're a smart person.
I think all of us think
that we're smart,
but we're trying to figure
something out and we're stuck.
And so it makes us feel bad.
You know, get over that,
okay? Just get over that.
This is the class where
you'll have to get over it,
no matter how smart you are.
And, you know,
this also includes
the instructors and the
course staff as well.
You know, there are things in
this class that we all needed
to figure out at some point.
There are things in this
class that we had that
we were stuck on at
some point, okay?
Lab through is
around the corner.
It's going to be released
next Friday. Alright.
And so, one thing that I
am concerned about and
I don't know how to
reason about this
is that there are
only 23 submissions,
and this includes whatever
TA submissions there are,
which is very low.
I hope to see, you know,
something closer to 75
submissions by Friday midnight.
Let's make sure
that this happens.
You know, if you're really
listening to my lectures,
really listening to
these warning signs,
tomorrow midnight, there
should be 75 right here.
Okay? You guys promise me that?
Can I go tomorrow midnight
and check for 75?
Okay, I will do that.
Okay, so we stopped
that thinking about
interrupts as a mechanism
for pseudo concurrency.
And just because we
have a mechanism that
enables concurrency
doesn't necessarily
mean that we can do
whatever we want, right?
We're in the
business of actually
remember always
throughout this class,
there are these two
things that we're
forced to provide as
operating system developers.
We're forced to provide
protection and
isolation mechanisms,
and we're in the business
of providing them in a way
that is protected
and safe, right?
So the code that you
write inside the kernel,
it should be giving you these
protection and safety features
that we want. We
always want that.
So in order to appreciate
what kind of issues
we're dealing with,
let's walk through an example.
So here's an example.
You have kernel code
on the left hand side,
and the kernel code is
sort of accessing
some shared variable,
and in fact, it is writing
to a shared variable, okay?
Um, okay.
And on the right hand side,
we have the interrupt
handler code,
and the interrupt
handler code is going to
attempt to read from
the shared variable.
So on the left hand
side, you have
kernel code right into
a shared variable.
On the right hand side, you have
the interrupt handler that
is reading from the
shared variable, right?
And most likely you probably put
some locks around your shared
variable in the kernel code.
Now, what do we need
in order to make
this code safe and correct?
What is missing right now?
Just as a warm up exercise.
Let's start trivial. What
is missing right now?
Is this code correct?
Yes. Sorry, could you speak up?
Text checks on the as well.
Yeah, so on the right hand side,
you're saying that we need
to make this access to
the shared variable be a
critical section as well,
right? Everyone
agrees with that?
Are we cool with that? So
because without it, right,
access the read access to
the shared variable is
completely unprotected, okay?
And just jumping
ahead a little bit,
if you have access to
a shared variable that is
unprotected, in other words,
that means that the
kernel code and
the interrupt handler have
the ability to access
a shared variable,
in a read and write fashion,
and that creates a problem.
We'll make a proper definition
for this later on
in this lecture.
So at the very least,
you need to make
sure that access
to a shared variable
is mutually exclusive.
And how do we
accomplish this from
all the previous courses
that you guys have taken?
Chances are, you
probably want to
slap some locks around
this, as well, right?
So now we have two
critical sections,
one on the left hand side,
one on the right hand side.
Is this safe? Is this
correct? How we done?
I see some nodding. I think
people are feeling
good about this code.
Okay, any more nodding?
Okay, how many people think
that this is safe code?
Remember that we're
going to get over
our superiority complex in
this class, including
myself, okay?
And just just go out there
and raise your hands.
How many people
think that there's
a problem there's no
problem with this code?
Okay, good, good, good.
How many people think
that there's still
a problem? Okay,
what's the problem?
I think you can
interrupt while you're
in, no, no, no, no.
Okay, it's good that
you're thinking in
the right direction and at
the same time being confused.
That means that this
is now going to be
a complete waste
of your time. Yes.
If you interrupt kernel code,
then you can get deadline.
If you get interrupted
in the kernel code,
then you can get dead locked.
Right. Now, let's break that
down and that's see
exactly how this happens.
Remember, interrupts
are especially
interrupts that we're
not masking, right?
If they happen, they can
happen at any point in time.
So on the left
hand side, we have
this sequence of instructions
happily executing, right?
Our kernel code is
doing some stuff.
It's acquired a lock.
It is successfully
acquiring the lock.
Now it's doing some stuff
over here between the lock
and the shared variable,
and then maybe it's already
updating the shared
variable right here.
And remember that interrupt
can happen at any time.
What happens if the
interrupt happens
in the middle of the critical
section on the left hand side?
So the interrupt has happened.
We've switched to
stacks just like we
discussed last time to
the interrupt handler,
and the interrupt
handler starts to run.
What's the problem? Yes.
Interrup handler
will try to lock,
but it came because
kernel code hasn't
unlockedn't share it yet.
Right. Exactly. And so
that's what leads us to
a thing called huh?
No, there is a race condition,
but it's even worse than a
race condition right now.
Yeah, a deadlock, right?
Where the liveness condition
of this code is violated.
Like, basically, we
cannot guarantee
liveness because it is
possible for the interrupt
handler to be deadlocked.
Now, how does it get deadlocked?
So that means we
can't really make interrupt
handler ignore the locks.
We have to be actively
thinking about what
happens about the locks.
Um, where do I have
this animation?
So let me just step through
the bullets because I want
to get to my animation.
Yeah. So how do we
get the deadlock?
The reason the deadlock
happens is because when
the interrupt handler is getting
to this lock
statement right here,
it takes a dependency on
this unlock right here.
So there's this
dependence relationship
between these two statements.
In other words,
this instruction A
cannot proceed until this
instruction B completes, right?
Everybody agrees with that.
Okay. And so what's
wrong with this
instruction completing?
Well, this instruction
is oh, okay.
This instruction unlock on
the left hand side
is depending on
the progress to be
made right here
where the kernel code has
actually stopped executing.
And that sort of depends on
the interrupt handler
lock acquire, right?
So that really gives us
the cycle of dependencies.
Anytime you have a
cycle of dependencies,
that leads to a
deadlock situation.
So deadlock in one
way or another,
kind of gives us
symptomatically,
gives us the symptomatically
is manifested by there
being a cycle of dependencies
somewhere in our code.
And this is one concrete
example of this.
So the next question then is,
how do we resolve
this situation?
How do we break the cycle
of dependencies, right?
So does anyone have
any ideas in terms of how to
resolve the cycle of
dependencies in principle.
Yes.
Like statement or something,
check if the web has already
acquired and if it has,
then you're technically still in
the walk section
so you don't need
to try and impart the w again.
Oh, yeah. So that gets
complicated because now you
have multiple if
conditions that are sort
of unprotected by the
critical section.
And so we're going to get
to the Peterson's algorithm
later on where it doesn't
really solve the problem. Yes.
Same, yeah, you're
jumping ahead.
Okay. But in principle,
what we want to
do in some sense,
is because that's a mechanism
for what we want to do.
What we want to do
is we don't want to
take interrupts in the
critical section, okay?
We don't want to be interrupted
while we're running
a critical section.
And, of course, the
mechanism for that
is to delay the
interrupts, right?
You have it right
here on the slide.
You know, I there some way
for us to delay the interrupts?
So whenever I'm holding a
lock in the kernel code,
I want to have the
ability to delay
the interrupts because it leads
us to the possibility
of a deadlock.
Okay? So in order
to accomplish this,
we do this by disabling
the interrupts when
we're trying to
acquire the lock and re enabling
those interrupts
as soon as we are
done with this critical section.
And this is something.
How many of you have seen this
in the XV six code already?
I have a few hands.
Okay, good, good.
One, two, three.
Anyone else? Four. Okay, good.
People have actually
seen this in XV six.
You do need to look at
this in X six code.
There are some slides
at the very end,
which I already posted
on Canvas, right,
that actually point you
specifically to the
code that does this.
So make sure that you
reference it because it's
unlikely that we'll get to
those slides in this lecture.
Given the progress we're making.
I'll try to go faster.
So in other words,
the interrupt enable
disable here
actually establishes
atomicity for the
critical section
around which you're
doing this, okay?
And atomicity is going to
be this very
interesting and very,
very nuanced concept in
this class that's going to
come up in a couple of places,
including this
lecture, but also in
the file systems and
concurrency lecture at the end.
And atomicity is a
relative construct,
because is it atomic
from the perspective of
the CPU executing
those instructions?
Yes or no. It's not, right?
The CPU will still see
those instructions as
separate instructions.
It's not atomic relative
to the CPU's viewpoint,
but it will be atomic relative
to another thread of execution,
such as an interrupt handler.
Okay? So we've established
this relative atomicity between
these two blocks of code by
disabling the interrupts.
So atomicity, again, is
not an absolute concept.
It is a relative concept.
And in this particular case,
we've established
atomicity relative
to an interrupt handler
by disabling interrupts.
And by the way, since I'm
talking about relativity here,
the slapping locks the access
to the shared variable
actually also established
atomicity relative to the
other user space threads
attempting to access that same
shared variable
at the same time.
Okay? So in both cases,
atomicity was achieved,
and clearly that atomicity
that we achieved with just
slapping locks around
the critical section
was insufficient for us
to ensure atomicity relative
to the interrupt handler.
Guys, this is cool stuff, right?
I'm breaking your
brain right now
because you thought that
atomicity means just one thing.
Yes. Can you repeat
what she said? No.
Don't think I can.
It's recorded.
You can go back to that
and watch the recording,
and we are already 18
minutes past the hour.
I want to keep going with this,
and I think you'll
actually appreciate
that in subsequent
examples on this slide.
Okay? So we've established
order as a result of
establishing this
relative atomicity.
In other words, the block
A on the left hand side
will be ordered in its totality,
relative to the block B on
the right hand side, okay?
So the mechanism of
delaying the interrupts has
actually established some kind
of ordering between A and
B in an atomic fashion.
And so this is exactly
what XV six does.
If you look at the
implementation of XV
six of a spin lock,
for instance, right?
It looks like this. You disable
the interrupt on a quire,
and you re enable
in the interrupts
after the unlock
on release, okay?
So this is actually not a
conceptual thought exercise.
This is something you'll
actually see in X six code.
So when we program in an
interruptive environment,
we really need to think
about safety in concurrency.
And in EV six, we avoid
interrupt deadlock by disabling
interrupts when a
spin lock is held.
A mutual exclusion with
an interrupt handler is
achieved with an
interrupt disable.
That's when we established
this relative atomicity
that was necessary in
order for us to impose
ordering between the
two critical sections,
including the ones with respect
to the interrupt handler itself.
So building locks with
only an atomic load and
store is very hard.
Very, very hard.
There have been
people that receive
touring awards trying to
come up with
algorithms for this,
including Dykstra himself, okay?
How many of you are familiar
with Too Much Milk example?
Another one of those
things that seems,
why am I in this class
thinking about milk, right?
But it turns out that this is
actually a canonical example in
distributed systems and in
any including operating systems,
where concurrency can happen.
So no one has heard about
the too much milk example.
It's actually a
graduate level thing
that people talk about
in graduate classes.
I'm going to introduce it kind
of very briefly in this class.
So you have not covered the
basics of this. Okay, good.
So this is a classic
motivating example,
and it sort of showcases how
difficult it is to provide
mutual exclusion with concurrent
memory reason rights.
And jumping ahead a little bit,
where I'm trying to
get to with all of
this is to motivate the need
for hardware support for
transactions or for sort of
atomic operations that achieve
multiple reason rights in a
single atomic fashion, okay?
Like a compare and
exchange, for instance.
Or just an exchange itself.
So that's sort of
jumping ahead where
we're heading with all
of this stuff, right?
As we're writing
concurrent programs,
we need to ensure
universal correctness.
So that means, what
does that mean?
You know, sometimes you look
at your code and you think,
Well, in my mind,
it seems correct, right,
because if I go through
this sequentially,
it has to do this
and this and this,
and it seems to work fine.
But what this implies is
that the code must
work all the time,
not just most of the times,
or the majority of the times.
The concurrency bugs are
very hard because they occur
only for some of the execution
interleavings, okay?
And it even gets worse than
that and hopefully
we'll get to it by 250.
So when you're thinking about
mutual exclusion design,
the mental model for concurrent
updates needs to be this.
You need to be the
way you need to
think about it, what do
you want me to do, right?
What's the action item for me?
From your perspective,
you should be mindful
of what is being checked
and what is being updated.
You should be mindful of
the shared data struck
access between the check
and update because
something can slip in and
actually modify state while
we're performing action that's
sort of dependent on the state
that we have just checked.
And we'll see a very, very clear
example of this ultra simple,
the too much milk example.
What is it, right?
So you have a fridge,
and there are two,
let's say, partners
sharing a flat, right?
Let's say I forgot how I called
them Allie and Bob, okay?
And Bob checks the fridge,
and if there's no
milk in the fridge,
Bob goes to the store
and gets some milk.
Okay? And then Bob comes
back and puts that milk
in the fridge, okay?
But he is not the only one
who shares access to fridge.
You know, apparently,
there's also Alice.
And Alice also
checks the fridge,
and it just so happens
that the fridge is empty,
and if the fridge is empty,
Alice is also going to go
back to the store and she's
going to get some
milk and come back to
the fridge and put that
milk in the fridge.
What's the problem? Seems like
a reasonable thing to
do with your flat mat.
You just want some milk
in the fridge. Yes.
Now they what? Yeah.
Yeah. So basically,
they essentially ended
up having there's a
possibility, right?
There's a possibility
that they ended up with
having more milk than they
wanted with two cartons of milk.
Okay? So what can you do
in this particular case?
How can we fix this problem?
Yes. He can what?
Log the French.
So there's a problem with that.
Like, I like where you're
heading with this
line of thinking,
but the problem is that he
checks for the
fridge being empty,
and then there's
a period of time
until he actually puts
a lock on the fridge
where she can also
check the fridge before
he's able to get the lock
on the fridge, right?
Dang it. We haven't really
solved the problem.
Yeah. Anybody else? Someone.
Sorry, again. Okay.
Okay. Okay, so in some sense,
actually it provides
you even with
a weaker semantics than
what he suggested because
you're basically introducing
an additional variable
to which you're going
to be writing that I
am going to the store,
Alice, can you please
not do that as well?
And again, the problem
is that the read on the
state of the fridge and
the writing of that message
are happening outside of a
critical section, right?
And so they're not atomic
relative to Alice.
Back to your earlier question,
can you repeat that?
Again, this is another example
of relative atomicity.
An atomic instruction to
check if the milk is there
and lock the fridge.
So an atomic test
and set function?
Yeah. Yeah. So you pretty
much ended my fan here.
So basically, that's what we
are heading towards, right?
We're trying and by the way,
by the way, this is actually
not strictly required.
You don't actually need an
atomic transaction
or instruction.
It is actually possible
to do it with atomics
reads and writes.
And there was lots of research
done on this in, I think,
70s and 80s when
distributive systems became
popular and concurrency became
a huge headache for everyone.
And people actually did come
up with algorithms for this.
But let's formalize this
example first, right?
So, so that you actually
have it in your notes.
So, Bob, what does he do?
He checks the fridge.
There's no milk,
goes to the store,
buys milk, arrives home,
milk goes to the fridge.
That's sort of a sequence
of your instructions,
just being very
explicit about it.
Alice, same set of same
set of instructions.
So basically, two threads,
kind of attempting
exactly the same thing,
right? But here's the problem.
Here's the interleaving
that's problematic, right?
So Bob checks this fridge,
goes to the store,
buys milk, and then
Alice goes in,
checks the fridge, goes
to the store, buys milk.
And, of course, as
we've established,
that's going to give us
too much milk, right?
That's sort of what's
going to happen.
Now, formalizing
this a little bit,
how do we land this in something
that we can reason
about in this class,
formalizing this a little bit.
So you have a couple
of shared variables.
In this case, checking
the fridge is basically,
in case it wasn't obvious,
reading a shared
variable, right?
And then you put
milk in the fridge,
that's updating the
shared variable.
So you're reading fridge, you're
writing to the fridge, right?
And what we need
to think about in
this particular case is
two key properties that
guarantee correctness.
And as a first year PhD student,
I actually had to prove
correctness for something
when I was interning
at Microsoft Research.
So I still remember
some of this.
There are two things
safety property
and liveness. Now, safety here.
Actually, I want to start
with liveness first.
Liveness guarantees progress.
Liveness says that some
progress in the
system will be made.
In this particular case,
someone is going
to buy the milk.
That's what we want
to happen, right?
Because if that is false,
we know that it's
incorrect because
the whole goal of
this multi threaded application
is to produce milk
in the fridge.
Okay, so we need to
guarantee liveness.
Was liveness Can liveness be
achieved in the previous example
without us doing anything else?
Will liveness be achieved?
Yes. Yes. Because if
both of them go by
milk, it's still live.
Yeah, they make progress.
Milk will show up in the fridge.
It's life. The system is life.
Now, the safety property in
this particular case is
that at most one person,
so less than or equal to one
person must buy the milk.
And by the way, the combination
of those two things,
because liveness
is greater than or
equal to one person buys milk,
safety is less than equal
to one person buys milk,
makes it that exactly
one person buys milk.
And so that's why you need to
make it mutually exclusive.
Yeah. Okay. And so the naive
threat coordination here.
Okay. What did I want to say?
Ah, the naive
threat coordination
here is basically leave a note.
I actually didn't animate
the living note part.
Someone suggested
leaving a note.
You know, we can
walk through this
why this doesn't solve
the problem, right?
Really briefly, it doesn't
solve the problem.
Now, but why, right?
You need to prove this to me.
You know, I can
sound like a joke,
but you need to
prove this to me.
How do you prove this to me?
Well, you prove this
to me by looking
at the safety and the liveness.
Is blindness still achieved?
Is liveness still achieved?
That's the easy one, right?
If you know, if you
go through kind of
mentally through all
possible interleavings
of these treads on the left
and the right hand side,
I think there's going to be
milk in the fridge, right?
So liveness will be achieved.
I'm not going to spend time
on proving this right now.
Is safety still achieved?
Yeah. Oh, no, because
before Bob leaves the note,
Alice can check fridge.
Yeah, exactly. Because we can
still have an interleaving.
As a matter of
fact, they could be
leaving a note at exactly
the same time, right?
And then so let's say
that we got to the point.
You can imagine a virtual
pointer right here where
Bob checked the fridge and is
leaving a note right
here. Bob is here.
Is also here, also
leaving a note, right?
And then one of them is going
to succeed kind of
posting a note first.
Okay, fine. It doesn't
really matter what
the order of that is.
Now we'll end up with two
notes on the fridge, right?
And both of them go to store.
Both of them buy milk,
and we get too much milk.
Okay? So the safety
here is the more complicated
property to ensure,
and that's what we need the
more sophisticated
concurrency primitives
that we're going to
talk about next.
But before we even jump to
that thing that you suggested,
which is the exchange operation,
the atomic exchange operation,
it is possible to
do this without it.
And it's called the
Peterson's algorithm.
How many of you looked at
the Peterson's algorithm
before? Yeah, yeah.
So definitely take a look at
the Peterson's algorithm.
It's a very interesting
piece of code, okay.
And especially if you're
going to study
distributed systems,
and I encourage you to study
it in your spare time.
So this is where we sort
of declare intent, right?
So the flag variable right here.
So zero corresponds
to thread zero,
one corresponds to thread one.
The flag variable right here is
where we're going to
declare intent that I
intend to get into the
critical section, okay?
And then after that, we
have an additional variable
here that's sort of denoted as
P zero gate and P one gate,
where we set the
turn to one, okay?
And that's basically tries
to impose some sort of
order in which they're
going to access the
critical section.
And the wild condition is
basically busy waiting, okay?
So if you look at
the wild condition,
it's like an empty loop
here or empty body.
It's a busy weight
that is going to
busy wait for as long as
this condition holds true.
And what is the condition?
While it's still
my while I'm still
intending to get into the
critical while I'm still sorry.
Let me while the
other person is still
intending to get into
the critical section,
and it's their turn.
I'm going to wait for
them to complete. Right?
So Wil flag one is true
and turn equals to one.
So let me get this
one more time.
While the other person is still
intending to get into
the critical section,
and it's my turn,
I'm going to wait.
And then after that, you get
into the critical section,
and then you reset
the intent because
you no longer intend to get
into the critical section.
So it gets really
complicated because
you actually have to
introduce an additional
variable for
every single thread
that attempts to
participate in this
concurrent operation.
And so it turns out that this is
completely impractical in
realistic scenarios, right?
And we really want
something that's much
better than that,
that's much more efficient.
In other words, we need a
better concurrency mechanism
that in a sense,
does an atomic read and
atomic write in a single
operation, right?
So Cen plus plus
11 standard does have
some atomic primitives.
I just wanted to make sure that
I mentioned them here to you.
We have an atomic load,
an atomic store, an atomic
fetch and d, atomic exchange,
and this is basically where
we are doing a load and store
at the same time in a
transactional fashion,
and even more
sophisticated variant
of that atomic compare exchange.
So sort of even fancier
where there's a condition,
which must hold true in
order for the exchange
to take place.
Question?
Why do we need an atomic
load and atomic store?
So in some sense, actually,
this is syntactic sugar
to communicate to
the compiler that this load
and store actually
has to be atomic.
So in a sense,
it's a declarative
way of specifying to
the compiler that you want
this read to be atomic.
And it has some implications
from the perspective of
which optimizations the compiler
is actually able to do.
Right.
So that's an interesting
question because if you think
of also just in case, right,
just in case an
atomic load is not
actually atomic
from the assembly
instruction perspective,
because it is possible
for you to, let's say,
get something from
memory and put it in
a register and then maybe
for whatever reason,
put it into a separate register.
So it is possible for it to be
a multi instruction operation.
So that's sort of another
answer to your question.
Okay? Alright, so
now the question is,
we made a big deal about getting
too much milk in the fridge.
Can we actually
solve too much milk
with a sea lemon
atomic exchange?
And just to throw it out there,
here's what an atomic exchange
is going to look like.
You have a function exchange
that is trying to
perform a swap.
And so it's going to store into
a temporary variable the
contents of Y, right?
You're passing Y and
X, the contents of Y,
and then it's going to
star Y equals to X,
so it's going to save
X into Y and it's
going to return whatever
was there previously.
It's going to return T. So
the original contents
of Y that were there in
Y are going to be returned
out of this function.
Okay? And we're trying to do
this with hardware support.
This is going to be
an atomic operation.
So that means that
nobody can get in
anywhere in between these
statements anymore.
That was the problem that we
had with too much Milk example.
And that was the
problem that we had
why we can't just
leave a note, right?
Because it wasn't sort
of an atomic operation.
Okay. And so how do we do this?
Let's say that we start with
an initial condition
where lock is held.
Okay? We're going to set R,
which is our result to one,
and then while is not zero,
we will attempt to
perform the exchange.
And so when the exchange
actually took place,
right, R should be set to zero,
which is going to make
this wild condition false.
It's going to make
this wild condition
false and will break
out of the loop.
So does everyone agree that
this solves the problem?
Let's do it one more time.
Okay? So lock is set to one.
Let's say that this is
our initial condition.
There are only two
possibilities.
We can cover both
possibilities right now.
Let's start with
this one. Lock is
held by somebody else, right?
And we set R to one.
This is our result.
And then this allows
us to execute this Wild
statement at least once.
We know we're going to get
in. You guys see that?
We're getting into
the wild body.
And then we're
performing an exchange
of whatever's there in
the lock with a one.
We want to put one
into the lock.
Now, if it's already held,
what is this exchange
going to return?
This kind of stuff
will be on the test.
So what is exchange going to
return if lock is already held?
No.
The lock is already held, that
means that the lock
is set to one.
The exchange is attempting.
Basically, the exchange
in this particular case
is attempting to
replace one with what.
So what is it going to return?
What's going to be
the result of calling
this operation on the
left hand side with,
you know, Y pointing to one
and X equal to one. Come on.
One.
Yeah, you're going to
return one, right?
And so if you're
going to return one,
that means that the lock is
still held by somebody else,
and we were unsuccessful
at acquiring the lock.
And so we're going to execute
the wire loop again because the
condition will still hold true.
Do you see that? And for
as long as that's true,
we're going to keep
executing this wire loop.
Whoever held that, let's
say that they finally
released the lock,
and I should mention that
when they release the lock,
the lock is going
to be set to zero.
So we got into the
body loop right here.
The exchange is now
passing a pointer to
the memory location
that holds a zero,
and we're trying to
put a one into it.
Now, what will be the return
of this exchange? Zero.
And so what's going
to happen with
a zero return? What's that?
It's going to let us break
out of the a loop, right?
And so it can some people
can sort of conceptualize
and visualize these things.
Some of them are sort of think
in a very different way.
And so in order for
us to actually,
let's go through
the lock equals to
zero example because I'm
going to build to something I
want to give you a conceptual
framework for this.
So if lock is zero when
we start this operation,
so we set R to one, one
does not equal to zero.
We get in. We're trying to
exchange basically a lock
that was freed with the one.
So what's going to happen?
The return value will be
If lock is now, we're
discussing this
initial condition
when lock equals to zero.
The return value of this
is going to be what?
Zero. And so if it's zero,
while zero not equal to zero,
is going to cause
this to be false,
we break out of the wire loop.
We've completed this with a
lock held in our hand, okay?
Because we were successful at
putting one into it ourselves.
In other words, as you can see,
we're going to spin
for as long as
necessary until we are actually
successfully able to get
the lock in this
particular case.
And that is exactly how the
spinlock idea was born.
And that's exactly what you do
in your explicit implementation
of an acquire. Data.
Now, when you look at that code,
it's like a single line with
some additional
things at the top,
like if I'm already holding
a lock and I'm trying to
acquire a lock, panic.
Right? But then there's
this one line that sort of
executes this with just a
single wild condition, okay?
Which is exactly what
I have on the slide.
And that's the implementation
of a spinlock,
which is used for
acquire in X six.
Alright. But here's a
conceptual framework.
Here's where you're actually
learning something,
a skill that is going to
help you beyond this course.
Let's think about this from
the perspective of a
finite state automaton.
Now we have two
variables to worry
about in this finite
state automaton.
And correspondingly,
their state, right?
We have a lock
variable that changes,
we have R that changes.
Okay? And so because both of
them are binary variables,
how many possible
states can we have?
Four, 00011011.
By now, everyone can
count in binary, right?
So we can at least
enumerate the states.
So if I ask you guys,
please enumerate
all possible states
for a tople will you
be able to do that?
Yes. Awesome.
Okay, now, let's see
what's the way to do this?
Let's see what we've
just discussed, right?
So let me ask you first,
what is what's the state
that you want to end up in?
What is the successful state
out of these four states?
Meaning that we successfully
acquired the lock.
Yes. Zero. Why? Because 10
means we have acquired
the lock and R
zero means we have
exited the y loop,
so we have the lock.
Right. And so how do
you get to that, right?
Let's break this down.
We've successfully
and I'm trying to help you
actually think through this.
We've successfully
acquired the lock.
That means that one of
the necessary conditions
for this state is that
the lock variable must
be set to One, right?
That's obvious. So that already
eliminates half of
the possibilities.
So if it's a multi
choice question,
you already have 50%
of success. Okay?
Now, we still have two
states to worry about.
It's either 10 or one.
Why is it not 11?
Yeah. 11. The thing you're
trying to exchange the lock.
The lock has a value of
one. So it's still held.
You're trying to exchange
the value of one into
an empty los alum
so if you see 11,
that means you're trying
to acquire a lock
that is currently
acquired by enemy?
Yeah, basically, that means that
our R value is still
one after we've performed
the exchange operation,
which means that the lock
was held previously,
and we were unsuccessful
at acquiring the lock.
We're going to go back
to the wire loop,
and that condition is still
going to be true and we'll
evaluate we'll still attempt
an exchange operation
next, right?
So this 11 state is
very interesting.
And let's get to
that in a second.
So basically what we
want is and what we
discussed with the example where
the initial condition
was lock equals to one,
is we discussed this
transition right here.
We want to transition
from a state that was 11.
It was constantly 11.
The lock is still held, 11,
the lock is still held, 11.
The lock is still held, 10,
we've acquired the lock.
That is our successful
state transition
in this finite state automaton.
Do you guys agree
with me? Okay, and I
mentioned that there's this
self edge on the 11 state,
which is obviously possible.
And this happens when what?
How would you describe?
What description would
you give to this state?
When does this state
transition happen to itself?
It is possible, right?
We just talked about it.
Yes.
That's already held
by someone else.
When you try to
acquire lock that's
already held by
somebody else, right,
in this exchange operation,
the lock or the lock
pointer is pointing to one,
you're attempting to
write one into it.
So basically, R is
going to be one, right?
And your lock is one.
So basically, you
keep spinning in
this state until you're able
to successfully
transition to state one,
zero, which is our
success state, okay?
So this is where you spin.
You spin a lot on this vertex
right here in this
finite state automaton.
Is this the only state transition
that gives us success?
That could be a trickier
and a harder question.
Is this the only
state transition
that gives us success? Yes.
You can have another one 01-10.
If no one else is holding the
log and require it first.
We can have this state
transition, right?
And what does this state
transition represent?
First of all, you know,
it still leads to
the same success state that
we've already identified.
That's why you need to
approach this by thinking
through exactly in the
order that I'm giving
you right now.
What is the success state?
And then which edges
can I take in order
to get to the
success state, okay?
This is a second
edge that we can
take to get to the
success state,
and it sort of corresponds
to the situation where
the lock was not
initially held, okay?
And it's sort of the most
obvious and the easiest
case when the lock was
not initially held,
it was set to zero.
And if it is set to zero,
our exchange essentially
is successful
immediately because it
replaces zero with one, right?
And so R is going to become one.
Make sense? So this gives
us lock success as well.
And what is this state
state transition?
Is this state
transition possible?
The one with the question mark
for those of you who
missed the animation.
If I were to ask you,
right, give me the states,
and then which state
transitions are possible,
which state transitions
are not possible,
you should be able to provide
that answer to me, okay?
We're running out of time,
so I'm not going to ask you,
so I'm going to leave
this kind of as
a thought exercise for
you to think about.
Now, I want to get through this,
which is also something
that's mind blowing.
Okay. Here's the question.
You have two threads.
One of the threads is
performing a move of
an immediate value one
into memory location X.
And then it basically
moves the contents of Y
into the register EAX.
And on the right hand side,
you're trying to perform
an immediate value move
on immediate value one to Y.
Basically, you're
writing one to Y
to memory pointed to by Y,
and then you're trying to
extract the value of X
and put it into IBX.
Okay. And the initial condition
here is X and Y are set to zero.
And how many different.
The question is the following.
What values can EAX
and IBX end up with?
I just copy pasted the code
right here so that you
have it as a reference.
This basically
means X assign one.
Let me just go ahead and maybe
write that on the board.
This is X assign one, right?
The second is register EAX
assign Y. This is T one.
F T two, for T two, we have Y,
assign one, and we
have EBX assign X.
The question is,
what is the value of
EAX, EAX, question mark.
What is the value of
EBX? Question mark.
Answers.
Yes.
Sorry? PC and D. Okay.
BCG. Anybody else?
Yes. Ooh. How's So
G implies that basically all
states are possible, right?
I I'm going to
give you a minute,
because it takes some
time to think about it.
Yes.
Okay. Any more ideas?
What's the correct
answer? How many of you.
F. Okay. Any. How many
of you think it's F?
Wow. See, that's why
I told you that your mind
will be blown today.
I don't know if it's 98%,
but maybe 90%, right?
How many of you think
it's A through E?
Okay, that's good. How
many of you think it's G?
Ah. Did you see the
slides before the class?
No. All right. Why
do you think it's G?
If I both threads are
executing
simultaneously and they
get these instructions
at the same time,
then Mable is not
necessarily guaranteed
to be atomic here.
Yeah. And so even
if T two has executed
that first instruction,
it's not guaranteed that that's
the same Y that the
other thread is looking.
So in other words, just
to make it very clear,
we're discussing the
possibility of A here, right?
How is it possible to get A?
So give me the interleaving of
these four instructions
that makes A possible.
As a possible? Yeah.
That makes zero, zero possible.
Because that's the way to
answer this question is,
what are the possible
interleavings, right?
And while you think about that,
I just want to go through
the other ones really
quickly so that everyone
is on the same page,
how we get B C and D. Or
does everyone understand
how to get B C and D?
Yeah? Okay. Well, so
just so that you feel
good about yourself,
this is what the previous
class also answered.
They also said that
the answer is BC and
D. How do we get that?
How do we get B?
This is the interleaving.
You execute T one first
and T two second.
If you go through the code,
you can convince yourself that
executing the T one set
of instructions first
followed by T two
set of instructions
second is actually going to give
you zero in EAX and one in EBX.
Everyone sees that?
Okay, good. Thumbs up.
Thumbs up, everyone.
Okay, thank you.
Thank you. Now, C
is the opposite.
Basically, if we take
the entire T two block,
right, followed by
the T one block,
it gives us the interleaving of
these four instructions
that make C possible,
which is ending up with
essentially symmetric.
These are symmetric
instructions.
So we end up with the opposite,
EAX being one and
EBX being zero.
Everyone sees that Okay, good.
Now what is the third one?
The third one is a little
bit more interesting, right?
This is where some
finer granularity
interleaving is actually
taking place, right?
The final granularity interleaving
we still have one CPU,
by the way, it's not
like they're being
executed on two CPUs.
Still have one core executing
those instructions.
So I'm not sure whether you were
going with two separate cores.
But the interleaving
here is basically
taking one instruction
from T two,
followed by one instruction
from TO and then again,
one instruction from T two,
followed by one instruction from
TiO, it doesn't really matter.
You're going to end up with
a situation where both EAX
and EBX are set to
one. You see that?
Now, how do we get A?
So the question that I posted
earlier that I phrased
earlier is what
interleaving is
possible that will
actually give us AAX
and EBX both set to 00.
Give me that set of
instructions. Yes.
Statements before either
variables are assigned.
So you have to run
the second line
of Team one and the
second line of C two.
Okay. The first.
So that's the thing.
You're correct, right?
The interleaving
that's necessary here,
in order for us to get zero,
in order for us to get
a 00 tuple, right,
we actually have to execute
the second lines first,
followed by the first lines.
And so he's saying
it can't happen.
Yes.
St Yes, exactly.
It turns out that this
interleaving is actually possible,
and that's where you
should be mind blown.
It is actually possible to
rearrange instructions
within the context
of a given thread,
and the reason for this
is because there are
no data flow dependencies
between those two instructions,
and the read write dependencies
are not guaranteed.
The read write ordering
is not guaranteed.
So you think when
you write your code,
so the correct answer, by the
way, is all of the above.
You can actually get
all four possible states
with this example.
All of the above is
the correct answer.
And the reason for this
is because there are
no data flow
dependencies between
the two instructions in
either of the threads.
And so the compiler will
think that I can
rearrange them in
any order because there
are no data flow
dependencies between them.
Yeah, now everybody
is mind blown. Yes.
Well, the compiler and
actually the processor
can actually,
sorry, I have to correct myself.
The processor can rearrange
them in any order,
especially the out
of order processor,
but also possibly the compiler.
Yes. Sorry, I can't hear you.
Even if you execute the charged
order, it'll instruction.
Well, but from the threads
perspective, right,
actually it doesn't matter
what it doesn't have
any data flow dependency
between those two instructions.
So let me try to move to the
punch line really quickly.
So what happens here, right,
at a higher level is
that X 86 actually
uses a memory model that's
called total store order.
So the only thing
that's guaranteed is
actually a store
order or write order.
And this makes it possible for
our loads to be reordered.
So we'll probably cover this
in detail sometime later.
But essentially, only
the stores are ordered.
There isn't a guarantee
overload orderings.
So the TSO respects
the right orderings and
read write dependencies,
but it does not respect
the right read
dependencies, right?
And so what happens here
is that you have a right
here in the first line and
a read here in the second line.
And so what happens
oftentimes with
software developers
is that we naturally
assume sequential consistency
when programming, right?
But this is actually not
a correct assumption.
We are not promised sequential
consistency by our CPU.
We're not promised the
sequential consistency
by our programming language.
We're not promised sequential
consistency by the compiler.
Instead, X 86 only
promises total store order
with ambiguous semantics,
and the only way to
write correct code
is if it's data raise free.
Or DRF zero.
So in Ci plus plus
as a version 11,
there's a DRF zero
semantics being offered,
which basically
means the following.
If you don't have any explicit
databases in your code,
then your code will
behave in a sequentially.
Then and only then
your code will
behave in a sequentially
consistent manner.
That's the only way to guarantee
sequential consistent
semantics is if you
have data base free code, okay?
So the takeaway from
all of this is that
RF zero means that
you should have no data
bases in your code,
and that's the only way that you
can actually maintain
your sanity.
That's the only way
that you can assume
that the code will be
committed or behave in a
sequentially consistent manner,
okay? So what do I do?
What are the takeaways from
this mind blowing
exercise, right?
Well, make sure that
when you write the code,
you introduce proper semantics,
the relative atomicity
that I talked about,
remove all the data bases,
use locks, semaphores,
condition variables, right?
And they all rely on
special operations.
They build up ordering and
atomicity abstractions,
just like other operating
system concepts.
And this is going to come up
in lab two when
you're implementing
your ref counting exam.
So make sure that's why I keep
telling you submit
your stuff tomorrow.
You will be surprised
that there will be
some race conditions that
you've introduced in your code,
which will take
another week to debug.
So make sure you spend the next
24 hours working on lab two.
Okay, I'm going to end my
lecture here, lecture here.
Thank you so much, and
I'll see you on Tuesday.
Yeah.