A
s
good
All right, everyone.
Good afternoon. We have
a big day ahead of us.
Today we're talking about
midterm exam preparation.
We also have a big
week ahead of us.
And, of course, as you all know,
next week is going
to be all about
the midterm and your
checkpoint one due on Friday,
next week as well, right?
So pretty big and
heavy week ahead.
And hopefully this lecture
is going to give you
helpful tips for
you to be able to
approach the kinds
of questions that
we're going to be
asking on the exam.
Let's go ahead and get started.
A few reminders, lab
three Checkpoint
as I mentioned, is
going to be on Friday,
the Pi Day 314,
the full lab is going
to be due two weeks
afterwards on 28 March.
And the office hours
basically are going
to be affected
by whatever's going
to happen next week.
So typically, when there's
only one section, historically,
there's only been one
section in this class,
we would cancel the office
hours on the day of the exam.
And so I'm planning to
not have office hours
on Tuesday the 311.
The reason for this
is because there's
a withdrawal deadline
on Wednesday 312.
And as I mentioned previously,
we want to make sure we grade
the midterms for you guys
before the Wednesday 4:00
P.M. Withdrawal deadline,
which is a 24 hour
turnaround time.
I hope you appreciate
the amount of effort and
coordination this is going
to involve across 12 people.
So we'll be busy doing stuff.
And so we're going
to try to figure
out how that's going
to work logistically.
And so we'll make
announcements in terms of
how that's going to affect
office hours next week, okay?
So, you know,
whatever questions you
have about your labs,
especially the ones that are
targeting the checkpoint,
your tests one through 21,
you know, make sure you
ask them not on Tuesday,
next week and possibly not
on Monday after 6:00 P.M.
Next week, okay?
Alright, so the exam for
the Section Section C is
going to be on Tuesday,
March 11 here,
regular classroom.
Okay. The exam instructions.
So I've already included
them in the practice exam,
and I'm probably going to copy
paste them into the actual exam.
You will see them also
posted on Paz and Canvas.
I want to remind
everyone that we
cannot allow the use of
Internet in general.
And specifically, we cannot
allow the use of GII.
It has become way
too powerful to
the point that it
can pretty much
solve a lot of the things
that we're asking.
And so, you know, we want to
figure out how you
guys are learning,
and to what extent,
we've been successful
actually teaching you something
in this class, right?
Um, and also, frankly,
you don't want to GNAI
yourself out of the
marketplace completely, right?
You want to be able to
think for yourself.
Otherwise, you'll be one of
those programmers that
will be displaced.
So try to be better than GeneI.
The only way to
achieve that is to
actually do stuff on your own.
Okay, and as I
mentioned on Piazza,
we did post the practice
questions on Canvas.
How many of you
have had a chance
to actually go through
those questions?
You raise your hands
higher? This is
better than the previous
section. That's good.
I'm proud of you
guys. It's very nice.
So just to give you a sense.
So this was a typical
length of the exam,
targeting an hour
and 15 minutes.
So don't worry.
This is not a 50
minute exam, okay?
It's a lot for a 50 minute exam,
but I wanted to go
ahead and give you
all of those six
questions anyway,
so that you actually
have more practice
than what we would
typically share in
the practice exam.
And okay, so you know, I
have to get through this.
It's also going to
be on the slides.
The slides are
going to be posted,
and this is essentially
a formality,
but I think you all know what
to expect at this point.
In case you don't follow
this please go back
and refer to this slide
at your convenience.
It'll be in person, in
class, on your laptop.
Make sure your
laptop is charged.
As you can see,
there are no charging
stations at the desk,
which is somewhat concerning,
but we do have charge stations
on the side if you need one,
but please don't need one.
And you cannot expect
the course staff to
provide you with lone
laptops or adapters.
They're all different. We do
not have the
capacity to do that.
The exam will be released,
I E visible on Canvas
precisely at 1,400
Eastern on Tuesday
of the exam, okay?
And the access to the exam will
cease to exist at 14:50 Eastern.
Please do bring your bus
card. It's a proctored exam.
We'll be walking around and
checking your bus cards to make
sure you is you
and you are here.
I like to summarize
this as saying,
You are here and you are you.
I think that pretty much
captures it, right?
Answer all of the questions
to the best of your ability.
As you can tell, it's
actually pretty hard
to navigate around the rows.
So if someone right there in
the middle where three
of you guys are sitting,
that's a pretty bad place to
ask any questions
during the exam.
It's going to be pretty
hard to get to you.
And so, you know, if you
just want to double check if
the assumption you're making is
correct or anything of the sort,
just write down any
reasonable assumptions
you were making, okay?
And then we'll try to work with
those assumptions when
we're grading the exam.
And this is going to save
you time because
as you can tell,
50 minutes passes by super fast.
And, you know, in
a blink of an eye,
you're going to be finished
with question one,
and I can guarantee you that
you'll be staring at the clock.
I'll say 30 minutes.
This has happened in the past,
and that's I'm speaking
from experience, okay?
So, make sure that
you just don't
waste your time
waiting for the TAs to
stop by and answer
your questions, okay?
Do not block on that. Do not
take a dependency on that.
Okay, all use of Internet,
other than to access the
exam through Canvas,
is going to be disallowed.
So I E, this is an open
notes, closed Internet exam.
I've been told that
people through
the first two years of Georgia
Tech know what that means.
Open notes, closed
Internet exam.
Okay? Um, No CGPT,
Jim and co pilot grow
Claude, Deep Seek,
okay, and other generative
AI technologies, et cetera.
I've already explained
the reason for this,
we're not trying to
be hard on purpose.
We're trying to help you
and foster learning.
Let's see. You know,
don't watch lecture recordings.
While I appreciate you watching
the lecture recordings.
This is not a good use
of time during the exam.
It's also going to
be logistically
complicated and distracting
for your neighbors.
So we're just going to,
as a matter of policy,
just kind of declaratively
specify, don't do it, okay?
It just doesn't make
sense to do it.
I would survive if you did it,
but it would be distracting
for other people,
and I don't think it
will be helpful to you.
Yeah, let's see.
And any questions about
this set of Exam
one instructions?
Yeah. Like paper or They can
be on your laptop. Yeah.
So any static content
on your laptop,
static content, okay?
No interactive.
No Lama 37 billion running on
your laptop with a huge RTX
28 TI mobile. Don't do that.
You know how it's done. My
students are doing that.
So don't do that
during the exam.
Like, that's why I
specifically called out
GNAI because even if
it is closed Internet,
you could theoretically use
GAI in your local laptop.
Don't do that either.
That's disallowed.
Any other questions? Yeah.
Yeah, it's local static
content, that's allowed.
Yes.
Any other questions?
Okay, let's see.
Yeah, and it's going
to be individual.
Some people a handful of people
sometimes finds that surprising
because you guys are now working
with the partner, whatnot.
But of course, the exam is
going to be individual work.
Nothing can be discussed.
Except with the course staff
in any format whatsoever,
everyone must turn
in their own exam.
Do not expect your partner
to turn in your exam.
I'm just saying the obvious,
but I have to do this because
one person will
come back and say,
You didn't say that, and
therefore, I'm correct.
Okay, so goals for
today is to help clarify the
questions about the exam.
I believe we've
gone through that
and to go over the
practice exam.
So, actually, how many
of you have gone through
the exam in its entirety and are
feeling comfortable
at this point.
Like, you feel like, nice.
So we have any other people
feel comfortable with the exam?
Go ahead and leave
now. I'm kidding.
I think this is still going
to be useful for you.
So this is a set of topics
of particular interest.
I've already mentioned
this before.
Isolation and protection.
You know, we keep coming back to
these two operating
system functions in
the context of different kind of
verticals in the kernel,
how they are provided.
What are the
mechanisms for them?
What are the policies that
govern the use, right?
So we really want to
make sure that we ask
kind of interesting
creative questions
about isolation and protection.
The trade offs
associated between
different mechanisms of
isolation and protection.
We talked about, for example,
segmentation versus virtual
memory management, right?
What are the pros and cons?
Would you ever use
one versus the other?
Always think about the extremes
of the continuum, right?
X 86 and low level hardware
and protection interfaces.
We talked about rings of
power and other things.
In that context,
kernel organization,
one of the questions actually
has to do with
kernel organization,
so we'll get back to kernel
organization in a few minutes.
Virtual memory management
was huge, right?
We covered two weeks
worth of VMM material.
So you would expect
that to be fairly well
represented in your exam, right?
That would be a natural
assumption to make.
And, of course, also
reinforced by your lab, too,
which was also a
fairly hefty fraction
of the time you spend
between now and the exam.
So quite natural to assume
that this is something
that the exam is
also going to try
to test, right?
Concurrency and scheduling,
super important.
And we covered that. We talked
about the mechanisms
of concurrency.
We talked about happens
before relationships, right?
We talked about
database conditions.
We talked about just in
general race conditions and
how to avoid them, right?
And what are the complications
associated with avoiding them?
What happens if you
don't do it, right?
If you expect
sequential consistency,
don't expect sequential
consistency if
your code is not database
free. Remember that?
So all of that is kind of in
the context of what we can test.
And of course, user
and kernel threading,
which is something we
covered right before
the discussion of operating
system and network.
Okay, so let's get into it.
Practice exam, Q one is asking
us about micro kernels.
Microkernels provide additional
memory space isolation
by separating not only the
kernel from user space,
so there's this
natural separation
between kernel and user space,
but also subsystems within
the kernel from each other.
So basically, you can have
different operating
system functions
kind of factored out as user
space processes, right?
So the question is asking,
what are the costs of using
a micro kernel over
a monolithic kernel,
and please explain
why these costs are
fundamental to a
microkernel. So any ideas?
This should be a fairly
straightforward question
just to ease you in, yes.
If you're using a microkernel,
you'd have to do more
context switches
to kernel space because you
have user level processes
doing things in a
monolithic kernel,
you would generally
have the kernel quien.
Yeah, so more contact switches.
So this is one of the costs
of micro kernel is that now
your operating
system services are
actually kind of user
space processes,
and you guys are doing
your lab three now.
You've already seen
the switch function.
You've seen the scheduler code.
It's going to be one
of those things for
which you need to roll
contact switch, right?
It's no longer
part of the kernel
proper. Anybody else? Yeah.
Why the context
switch is expensive.
Can we just say it's expensive?
I mean, in this particular case,
I think if you just say that
it's a user space process and it
would require more context
switches, I would take that.
Yeah, I don't think in this
case, you need to explain it.
Sometimes the way the question
is phrased, remember,
we had that moment where
the context switch was
actually a smaller overhead
compared to some other
overhead, for instance.
So if the question is
specifically asking,
then you should specify.
Okay? But this one doesn't.
Great modularity and control of
each individual casi perform.
And so that's an
advantage, right?
Okay. And the question is
asking about costs. Yeah.
But yeah, you're right.
If the question is also asking
most likely about
the advantages,
that's find that. Yeah, good.
Anybody else? So yeah,
basically, think about
examples, right?
It's always good to think
about some specific
concrete examples.
So let's say the kernel
actually wants to
use some file system
functionality,
which decides that it
needs to interact with
page cache and Pagecach
now is trying to
touch disk service,
and disk service is now kind
of blocking on block cache.
And that goes back
to the file system.
Imagine all of these context
switches that you
have to do, right?
And how many times you actually
cross the kernel
userspace boundary,
which in itself is
also quite expensive.
So we talked about
contact switches,
and then why are the
contact switches expensive?
You can elaborate
on that, right?
So what happens when
we switch context?
Yeah. You flush the TLB
because you're changing
something, right?
What are you changing
on the contact switch.
What triggers a TLB?
Address space.
Yeah, you're changing
address spaces, right?
And there are all
sorts of things that
happen when you're changing
address spaces, right?
TLB flush is one of them.
Okay. So that was and
this is an example
of kind of what
a microkernel architecture
would look like.
So what you're looking at
is a man core architecture.
It's sort of a two
dimensional grid of course,
each of which is
running something,
right? And it's color coded.
So you have Ido cores
are in red, so don't
worry about those.
The blue ones are
the application
that you actually want to run,
and the black ones are
the memory allocation servers
which are now user
space processes, okay?
And the green ones are
the file system servers,
which are now
userspace processes.
And so we discussed
what can possibly
happen when you
actually try to get
something done in this
type of architecture.
Okay, so what benefits
does a system get
from the isolation provided
by a micro kernel?
So one of the advantages
that we believe
the microkernel is giving us
is the advantage of isolation,
right, or failure
isolation in particular.
So what are the
question is asking,
What benefits do we get from
the isolation provided by
the micro kernel? Any ideas?
Yes. 16 compromise
the entire Yeah,
you basically establish
very natural security
boundaries, right?
If one of the services
is compromised,
that doesn't mean that the
kernel is compromised,
for instance, right? Let's see.
So isolation is already kind of
naturally following
from the statement
of the question itself,
fault protection, right?
So that's a big
one. Anybody else?
Can somebody elaborate
on fault protection?
Are we getting better
fault protection? Yes.
If one process crashes or goes
out of bounds or whatever,
it doesn't take down
the whole kernel.
I'll just isolate that process.
Yeah, so one user space
process, if that crashes,
it doesn't take down
the entire system,
which is also the case with
the monolithic kernel, right?
But then in this
particular case,
what benefit do we
get specifically
from a micro kernel that's
related to what you said?
Yeah. Some of the what might be
traditionally monolithic
kernel operation
would be done as
a user service typically from
base kernel so that that
can detect a fault in,
if it's a disc driver that
fails that would
run in the kernel,
the kernel might panic.
It panics, yeah.
The kernel panics.
Whereas, if it's separate,
then the kernel could do
something to clean
that up or restart it.
Yeah, exactly. And basically,
you're kind of isolating failure
to a specific user
space process.
And I'm pretty
sure this is where
you were heading with
that answer, right?
That if some of the
operating system services
are encapsulated as
user space processes,
their failure is not catastrophic
to the system, right?
As you mentioned security,
kind of, and this is where I
like to bring in
the SPARTA analogy.
Because a narrow
attack surface is
always beneficial for Defense.
Because this is Sparta.
Do you guys know about this
famous Spartan battle,
how they won with 300 people?
Yeah. Oh, I go ask for
narrow service So for
multiple reasons.
One of them is actually that
there's less code, right?
In a specific operating
system service,
there's typically
kind of some kind
of monotonically
increasing relationship
between the number of lines
of code that are
being affected and
how vulnerable or the
probability of security
violations in that code, right?
So this is, in some sense,
related to modularity.
But that's one answer.
The other answer related to
security is that as I
think he mentioned,
if someone compromises
your user space process,
they still don't have access
to the entire system, right?
They've just compromised
that process.
They don't have, for instance,
access to the kernel space
or anything that's
happening in the kernel.
And therefore, they
might not have access to
the other operating system
services running, right?
So those are the two
answers to your question.
Modularity, right?
And this is sort of a software
engineering benefit that
you get from micro kernel
is because in some sense,
it's sort of easier to
manage from a project
management perspective,
it incurs less technical debt.
And the smaller the
individual components
are that you can deploy in your
what now becomes sort of a
distributed operating system
on a man core architecture.
The smaller those
components are,
the easier it is to
iterate on them,
upgrade them, right?
The easier it is
to actually patch
the security vulnerabilities
and all that good stuff.
So there are multiple advantages
that the micro kernel
actually provides.
Even though it does have all of
these disadvantages that
we started with, right?
Yeah.
So I talked about software
engineering perspective here.
So it's easier to develop.
It's easier to deploy,
easier to test.
And so the entire kind of
pipeline becomes
quite a bit more
agile and you sort of incur
less technical debt for all
of those reasons, okay?
But the counter argument here,
especially to the isolation
is how much isolation do
we really get, right?
And we discussed
this during lecture,
because sometimes we feel like
we're getting fault isolation,
but this could be kind of a
false sense of isolation.
So can somebody comment on that?
Yes. These tend to
rely on each other.
So if one goes down, and all
the other processes won't
be able to execute
as yeah, exactly.
Did everyone hear
that? So basically,
there's a possibility
that processes have
such an intertwined
dependency on
the other user space
processes that a failure of,
let's say, a file system server,
even though it's a user space,
it has so many dependencies,
so many tasks,
so many other user space
processes depending on that,
that it doesn't really
matter that we sort of
factored it out into
user space, you know?
And so I think I have so
this kind of leads me to
the discussion of
failure closure.
So I'm going to try to get
through this fairly quickly.
Um but this is
the picture that we had
in the slides, right?
On the left hand side.
So yeah, on the left hand side,
you have a monolithic
kernel and life is good.
When user space processes
are failing, it
doesn't affect it.
On the right hand side,
what we've tried to do
is we've tried to factor
out these services as
user space processes.
But our user buys, right,
our use of buys
takes some form of
dependency on releases services.
So, for example, one
could have a set of services
that it depends upon.
You two can have a different set
of services that
it depends upon.
And so if any of these
Subjs basically fail,
then this is going to
affect use of B, okay?
But if any other SK fails that's
not in the failure closure of
usabi then use Bi survives.
And so that means that for any
given vertex thus defined,
okay, we can actually construct
a failure closure set.
Meaning that if anything
fails in that set,
then this is going
to affect my use Bi.
And this can be
done declaratively,
imperatively, it's sort
of less important.
Sort of more of a
research insight.
And so on the right hand side,
we know that these
are fairly sparse,
so they can be sparse, right?
So if you think
about this as us by
SJ as an adjacency matrix,
right, you can imagine
this adjacency matrix
being fairly sparse,
which is a good thing for
failure isolation, right?
And so if I ask you if
an adjacency matrix
that represents kind of
these failure dependencies
is sparse versus dense,
you know, how much failure
isolation we're getting,
you should be able
to get that, right?
Because if it's dense,
what does that mean?
Yeah. Lots of dependencies.
And so what does that mean?
Is not really true isolation.
Yeah, then you're
getting fall isolation.
Specifically, that's how
fall isolation is defined
is when this adjacency
matrix is dense, okay?
Alright, so what about the use
of bites on the left hand side?
Yeah.
Yeah, the kernel and, you know,
all of the services that
the kernel provides.
So the dependency here for each
of the user buys on
the left hand side
is if you were to
write it pseudo mathematically,
what would that say?
Anyone?
As a function of SJs.
Yeah.
So basically, I'm asking,
kind of what are the user Bes
depend on on the left hand side?
They depend on all
the services, right?
Because they're all
part of the kernel.
And so if you were to write
down the failure
closure for use,
it would basically be a
set of all Subjs, okay?
That's the only point that
I'm trying to make here.
And so on the left hand side,
all user space
processes depend on
all I'm calling them
usabes here, okay?
Depend on all Subjs
because they already
part of the kernel,
and everybody depends
on the kernel.
You have no choice with
monolithic kernel.
So if you were to represent this
as an adjacency matrix,
what would it look like?
Say it again.
Huh? Very dense. Very dense.
I mean, more concretely,
it would be a matrix
of once, right?
It would be a matrix of ones,
and that's the important thing.
Because usabtes go vertically,
Subjs go horizontally, for
each usabte depends on all Subj.
So it's a row of ones,
another row of ones,
another row of ones.
So you get a matrix of
one, okay? Super dense.
And now you can start
to reason, you know,
about the density of
this adjacency matrix
and what that means in terms
of whether you get
isolation or you get
fall isolation, okay?
Alright. Now, C is asking
one concrete use case where we
still want the micro kernel
over a monolithic kernel.
Oh, sorry, where
the advantages of
a micro kernel over monolithic
would not benefit
the overall system.
So what are some of the examples
where we would still want
a micro kernel? Yeah.
About a code that means
a lot of privileges.
It's just better
to stay in time.
Okay, so you're sort of claiming
that fall isolation is the
reason for this, right?
Okay. Okay. Any others?
Yeah. Tolerant. Mm hmm.
So basically a trusted
environment, right?
So basically, if we don't
have to worry about security,
for instance, which maybe
sometimes happens, right,
if there's an air gap
system, which I mean,
we just had a
security lecture that
air gap system can
still be broken, right?
Because something
was installed on
an Iranian nuclear power
plant via US Bistik, right?
So air gap systems are
not necessarily secure.
But anyway, let's take it.
Somebody thought
that air gap systems
are secure and it's a
trusted environment,
so you may not
necessarily want to
have a micro kernel
overhead, right?
Any other reasons why we
would want to have
a micro kernel?
It's sort of how
to approach this question
in general, right?
You might think, how do I
even approach this question?
We'll start thinking
about the advantages
of micro kernel that
we've just discussed,
and we usually
build this up over
the several sub questions
like what are the advantages?
What are the disadvantages?
What are the trade offs?
And then here's a specific
use case or give me
a specific use case that
would benefit from
one or the other.
That's a typical
structure of a question.
Yeah. Yeah, performance
critical, right?
Something that and
more concretely, yes,
you might want the
performance here,
but you might also
want predictability.
Maybe it's a real time
operating system, right?
And all of these
context switches,
you know, how does that
affect predictability?
Pretty bad, right, because
you all of a sudden kind of
lose control because you
have to go back and forth,
back and forth between
the different contexts,
and you don't really know what
the schedule is doing or in
what order it's actually
going to schedule
my operating system
services, right?
You may or may not know.
The bottom line is that
it probabilistically
lowers predictability.
Um situations where you
want tight control over what's
happening in the system,
which is related
to predictability.
Other examples including
better microcontrollers,
situations where you have
a trusted environment
or an air gapped
environment, right?
And, you know, those
are the use cases that
would benefit from
micro kernel advantages
that we have discussed,
okay? All right.
Any other questions
about ir quarter?
Shall we move on
to third quarter?
We still have five
more questions to go.
And let's say 30 minutes.
All right, let's go with
cuter. We have a friend.
His name is Harry, and he's very
concerned about the
isolation on his system.
And so he wishes to provide
a perfect CPU isolation
between processes.
So this is a question
about isolation,
right? And what that means.
More specifically,
right? We're trying
to define what we mean by
isolation perfect by perfect
isolation between processes.
He wants to guarantee that
a given process cannot
determine how many
other processes
are running based on its
own CPU utilization.
In other words, if I run,
I really want to feel like
I'm the only one in the system.
And we started talking about
this from the first week
in this class, right?
That's kind of like
the perfect isolation.
I really want to feel
like nobody else is in the
system other than myself.
And so what Harry
wants is that he
doesn't want the process
to have the ability to
determine how many other
processes are running based on
its own CPU consumption.
And he's asking you about
your opinion and doing so.
And the question is, I'm
going to skip the assumption.
That's fairly obvious.
The question is,
please explain how perfect
CPU isolation between processes,
how is that incompatible with
an operating system abstraction
of having infinite
processes available?
What's the incompatibility here?
Yes. It's kind of
like it's the idea
that if you want every
single process going
back to the dependency vectors,
what you want is you
want every single one of
those dependency vectors to
have the only instance of
that dependency belonging
to that process
so that no other process
can fail if that one
dependency goes down,
which means every single
process that on I don't know,
like a file system term and to
have its own version of
a file system service.
Okay, so we're done talking
about micro kernel.
This is just an abstract
question about in general,
an operating system
and its ability
to provide the
perfect isolation.
So, you know, try to swap
out the context that has to
do with dependencies between
different processes.
So is there some other
reason why, you know,
the achieving perfect
CPU isolation
can be incompatible with
our abstraction of having
infinite processes. Yes.
Well, the whole point of
infinite processes is that we
have to multiplex the
infinite processes on,
like, you know, a
limited number of
Cs. Yeah, yeah, exactly.
I really, really large number
of processes and only,
like, you know, a handful Cs.
It's like,
inevitably, we're going to
have to be swapping out,
and the process
could detect that.
Like it CPU usage would change,
so it could detect that.
Yeah, exactly. So basically,
if you do have an infinite
number of processes,
imagine, you know, what is
going to be the quantum
of time that you
should be allocating
to that process, right?
It's finitely large T
divided by infinitely
many processes M,
and if you take
the limit of that,
you're going to get a zero.
Okay? And so no matter
what scheduling policy
you employ here,
it doesn't really
matter because over
a sufficiently large
amount of time you know,
if you want to be
able to provide
support for infinitely
many processes,
you have the expectation of
the time allocated to
any given processes,
T divided by N with
a limit N approaches infinity
is going to be zero.
And so we achieve the
impossibility result.
We're not system is not
going to function if we're
allocating zero quantum of
time to each of the
processes, right?
So that makes it incompatible.
Okay? And so if that
doesn't make sense,
yet hold that thought
because it will
become more clear when we
discuss the other subquestions
of this question.
Because here, Harry
was convinced all of a
sudden that it is impossible
to achieve perfect isolation.
And by the way, let's
make it more concrete.
It sounded super
abstract, right?
Alright, some people don't
like things that
are super abstract,
take a fork test, which is
a very famous Linux
benchmark, right?
And what happens to
the performance of
fork test when you increase
the number of processes
you are forking?
Does it stay the same?
No? What happens?
What? The performance is
starting to go down, right?
And the reason for
this is because as
the number of processes
in the system increases,
you know, inevitably the
system starts to slow down.
And so, of course,
each individual process
will be able to
notice that kind of based
on how much progress
that application or that
process is able to make
over some period of
fixed time, okay?
So that's another way
to think about it
as the number of
processes increases,
kind of the perception of
progress that each
individual process
has changes and gets
worse and worse as you increase
the number of processes.
Alright, so let's say that
we've convinced Harry,
and we can come back to that
if you have any questions.
I just want to get through this.
He's willing to provide
an upper bound.
You know, he says, Okay, fine.
If the infinity is not possible,
let's put an upper bound.
In other words, from the
perspective of the system,
we are going to do
admission control
on the number of
processes we can have.
And we know that the upper
limit is N, constant N, okay?
So how might Harry leverage
this fact to allocate
processes CPU time in
a way that does not leak
any information
about the number of
processes running
in the system? Yes.
So you can use round
ramen scheduler
then always pretend that
they're in processes running.
So each process is going
to have the same amount of
scheduler time regardless of
how many processes
are actually running.
Yeah. Yeah. Exactly.
So basically,
you can kind of
allocate slots, right?
And they're going to occupy
a finite amount of time,
so no infinity business
here anymore, right?
Allocate slots, and you have
a maximum of end resources,
and you basically
say that slot zero,
process zero is going to run.
Slot one, process
one is going to run.
And if there's no process one,
nothing runs. Okay?
Nothing runs.
But from the perspective of
any given process
that is running,
they always get the same
allocation of time,
and they always make the
same progress over time.
And so no information
about the existence or
the count of other tenants in
the system is ever leaking
to any given process.
And so this allows us
to achieve isolation.
This is the kind of
perfect isolation
that we want, but in
order to achieve it,
we have to break
the abstraction of
infinite number of resources
supported by the system. Yes.
Using a pod scheduler
also work out.
Well, any scheduler would work.
Because remember,
we're talking about
sufficiently large
amount of time T,
if you uh the five F scheduler
would the five F
scheduler work, hold on.
What do you mean by
the FFO scheduler?
Like, I just like
what are you looking for us
to specifically
say this question?
We have to explain, like,
how, how this would work,
I guess, in terms of,
using a scheduling?
Well, concretely kind of
describe what you would
do from a scheduler's
perspective.
So the round robin answer
was actually a spot on,
where you would divide
time into Quanta,
and you would allocate Quanta
to the set of runable processes.
Okay. And so the set of
basically you have slots,
zero through minus one.
When you admit a process,
it gets this process ID
from zero to N minus one.
So that's the way the
system would work.
You'd have to describe how
the system works in
order to achieve this.
So you get slots that you
have N possible process ID,
zero through N minus one.
When you admit them, they
get that process ID.
And the way the
scheduler would have
to execute is that it
would perform some sort of
Round Robin scheduling
where now slot zero runs,
now slot one runs,
now slot two runs.
And if there's a process
that matches the
number of the slot,
that process only would run.
If there's no process,
nothing runs.
So I take that back.
The FIFO scheduler
would not work here.
Because the FIFO scheduler would
leak the amount of
information, right?
Because if you have
two processes,
the FIFO scheduler would do one,
two, one, two, one,
two, one, two, right?
Yes. When you
allocate end slots,
let's say there's
not end processes.
It's like an empty slot,
you just sleep or you
just don't execute.
You basically do nothing.
Yeah. You don't
execute any process.
Maybe there's a dummy
process that you execute.
You sleep. Well,
that's exactly right.
It wouldn't. And that's
what we're trying
to achieve, right?
So any process that actually
does get one ninth of that time,
right, it always gets
one ninth of the time.
So let me try to
advance the slides.
Maybe this will help explain.
If you think about
the amount of time
that's allocated to
a specific process,
the fundamental
question you should be
asking is whether or
not it's a functional.
In this particular
case, it would
not be a function of
N. It's constant.
Right? Because you always
get the same amount of time.
Let's say ten milliseconds.
It doesn't matter
how many processes there
are in the system.
If it does depend on
the number of processes
that are in the system,
then you have a
problem, then you're
leaking the
information about it.
And then is it a constant or
a variable function of M, right?
So that sort of determines
whether or not you're leaking
information about other
processes in the system. Okay.
We're still question
two. What are
the inefficiencies
in this design?
I think that should be
obvious, right? So yeah.
Yeah, you end up
wasting time when you
allocate those slots to non
existent processes, right?
And again, trade off, right?
If you want perfect isolation,
you have to pay
something for it.
And what you're paying
is the inefficiency
in the system, but
you can achieve.
Okay. So yeah, the problem
here is that if there are
fewer than the constant
N number of processes,
right, then you're
inefficiently using the system.
You're literally just
sleeping, right?
The resource utilization
is going to depend on
however many processes
or what fraction
of N number of processes
you have in the system.
Any other questions about this?
Okay, let's move on
to question three.
This is the one where
we're kind of asked to
construct a new 32
bit CPU architecture,
and we're considering making
the virtual memory page
size on this architecture.
30 bytes, okay? 32 bytes.
So remember that number,
32 bytes because
that's important,
which of course is
much smaller than
four K page four kilobyte
page that you're
all used to from 2,200
from this class, from
wherever, right?
Due to the power of 12 bytes.
And so the first
question is asking,
would you expect a kernel
running on top of Robert's
architecture to be
more or less memory efficient
than a classic four
kilobyte page architecture?
Pool, people know how to
approach this question.
Let's ask someone I haven't
asked yet. Yeah, maybe you.
Mm hmm.
Okay, so basically your
argument is that for
very small processes that are
only very small in
terms of their memory
footprint, right,
the code data stack and heap
and all that good stuff,
you don't need to waste
the memory resources in
order to allocate finer
granularity pages, right?
And so you're arguing that it's
going to be more
efficient, right?
So that's one side
of the argument.
Now, let's see if there's
another side of the argument.
Yes.
I
A lot more
of the page table pages, right?
Okay. Okay. Yes. Anybody
else? Yes, in the middle.
I was thinking too
along that line,
you want to have the same
amount of memory, like,
given to like that
a process with
four kilobyte pages
could have or
like a system four
kilobyte pages could have.
You're going to need
way more, you're
going to need way more
storage for all that.
Like, you're going to
need more entries in
your page directory and more
entries in your page tables.
Yeah. So remember,
it's asking about
memory efficiency
or memory overhead.
So think about what
that means, right?
And in general, how do you
approach this question?
So, uh let's see.
How do I have
anything useful here?
Okay, yes, how do you
approach this problem, right?
You have to analyze
first of all,
you have to start with analyzing
the linear address breakdown
because once you start there,
it already gives you quite
a bit of information.
So we have a 32
bit system, right?
We have a 32 bit system.
And we said that our pages
are going to be 32 bytes.
So How many bits do we need
for the page offset in
order in order to address
into a 32 byte page.
Yeah. No. Five,
what? How many bits?
Five bits, you need five bits.
So five bits, the least
significant five bits of
your 32 bit linear
address are going to be
addressing into
your 32 byte page.
That's fine. And
how much is left?
27, 27 plus five.
Yeah, 27 bits are
going to be your PFM,
your physical frame
number. Or VfN.
So V PFM, depending on what
we're talking about here.
Of course, in the linear
address, it will be a VN.
So that's a good
starting point, right?
We are using five bits
for the page offset.
We're using 27 bits
for the PFN and VFN.
So what is going to
be the PTE size?
So we know how much
this page is, right?
We know how many bits we're
using to address into it.
And now let's start
thinking about
the last level page table page.
This is a page table page.
It consists of page
table entries, PTs.
First of all, how wide are
the PTs on this system?
Yeah, there are four bytes
because it's a 32 bit system.
Remember, when we
switched 32-64,
our PTs also became
64 bits, right?
So whatever the system is,
that's going to be the
size of your PTE always.
So our PTs are
four bytes, right?
Okay, let's say four bytes
or 32 bits, 32 bits.
And so for every at
what granularity are we
addressing physical
frames of memory?
In other words, how
many PTEs does it
take for us to address a
single frame of memory?
Zero, one, 0.52 100.
One. It takes exactly one PTE
to address a physical
frame of memory.
So let's say we have a PTE right
here that I should
be more careful,
that addresses the base of
this physical frame
of memory, right?
And this PTE is four bytes.
This page is 32 bytes, right?
So you're paying the
overhead of four bytes.
Divided by 32 bytes, right?
So one eighth, which
is approximately 12.5%
overhead in order to
address the 32 byte
granularity pages.
Now, how does that compare
with four kilobyte page?
Four kilobyte, it changes
the denominator here.
On a 32 bit system,
your numerator is still
four bytes because
the size of the
PTE, so size here.
Here, this is the formula,
size of PTE under squat, okay,
divided by the size of
the physical frame.
Basically, for a typical system
where our size of PTE was
four bytes and the
size of the page
was 4 kilobytes, right?
I don't know. It's going to
be something much better.
1/1000, something, 1/1024,
a much smaller overhead
associated with addressing
a single frame of memory.
And we need one PT
per page, right?
You cannot get around that.
So even though you do get
the benefit for very,
very small processes
that might only use
64 bytes of memory,
overall, right,
for regular sized processes,
you're paying a
lot of overhead in
order to address
into 32 byte pages.
Does that make sense? As
a matter of fact, it's,
you know, approximately 12.5%,
and we're only counting
last level pages here.
This is actually a lower
bound. It's higher than that.
I could ask a question for
why it's higher than that.
Because these PTs do
not exist in isolation.
They exist as part of a page
table page and you need to
allocate the entire
page table page
in order to hold these PTs.
So the amount of memory overhead
you have is actually
strictly higher
than the sum of
the sizes of APTs
require you require in
order to address your
physical frames.
Does that make sense?
So think of this
as essentially the sum of
all the size of PTEPs
that's a lower bound,
again, because they're held by
page table pages that you
also need to allocate.
Makes sense? So for instance,
what the hell did
I just say, right?
For instance, if there's
a single PT here that
you need to address
into your, let's say,
your code segment, second PT
that you need to address
into your data segment
and you don't need
anything else.
Like, to his point,
if this is actually a very,
very small process, right,
even though you're
only using two PTs,
you are going to allocate
a huge page for the
PFN for the PTP,
the page table page in
order to hold those PTs.
Anyway, that's what I meant by
the fact that this
is a lower bound.
Divided by the sum of the
sizes of the physical frames.
So this is essentially a formula
for determining what the memory
overhead is going to be.
At the lower bound
on the memory overhead,
this is going to be.
I should be more precise.
Okay. Yes. That's correct. Yeah.
The size of a PT is always
going to be whatever
architecture you're building.
If it's a 16 bit architecture,
and I ask you questions
about 16 bit architecture,
the size of your PT is
going to be 16 bits.
Okay? And I may
even ask questions about an
eight bit architecture. Yeah.
You have to say that since
each page is so small,
you're going to have
many, many pages.
So that means we also
need to have lots
of PDEs and page dictor that as.
Oh, I guess it's already deal.
Yeah. Yeah, I said that
this is a lower bound,
and then there's
going to be some
more overhead on
top of that that
we can also quantify.
You're right.
But then it sort of
depends on the details
like do I want a one
level paging system?
Do I want a two level
paging system, right?
Because if it's a one
level paging system,
this is going to have some
additional additive component
here that's going
to be different
from a two level paging system.
So I need to give
you more information
to quantify that
kind of overhead.
And we're not given this
information in this question.
Okay, um Wow.
This is an easier one,
much easier, right?
So you have Robert wants
his hardware to have a robust
tracking and permission system,
and the permission bits that
he wants is for reading,
writing, user super user,
so that's zero, one, a control
bid to disable hardware
caching and some
hardware monitoring bits
for accessed and dirty.
So how many bits does he want?
Six. So what's the
problem with that?
Can we support it six
permission bits in
this system thus
designed? Why not?
Yeah. Yeah, remember,
that's where I started by always
start with the breakdown
of linear address.
This should be number
one step that you
should always do
because now it gives
us ready to go information
that we have 27 bits for VFNR?
And then we only have five
bits for permission bits,
and Harry Robert 16, right?
This cannot happen. We don't
have enough bits
for that, right?
So we cannot support it.
Okay. The next question is,
so we already at 2:52.
Is there a specific
question you'd rather
me jump to or do you
want to go in order?
Is there some sort of a
preference between four,
five and six that you
want to prioritize,
especially in case
you have to leave?
You want to do four? I
want people. Get excited.
Like every single time I do
the midterm practice exam,
I always get really excited.
Because it's very different
from a lot of the questions
you used to get in
previous classes, right?
It sort of makes you
think. It makes you
apply your knowledge
in non intuitive ways.
Okay, so question four is
asking for the following.
We have modern architectures.
They have a third
protection bit,
specifically the
execute bit, right?
And this bit determines if
the virtual address space can be
used to execute from a code.
And so we just had
a security lecture
where you were overwriting
the stack, right?
And do you remember
what happened
on the stack when we did a stir
copy with an arbitrary buffer
taken from R V, right?
R V one? What happened there?
We overrode the
EIP and then what?
What can we make
this EIP point to?
Milicious code.
Malicious code, where is that?
That malicious code
is code, data,
heap, stack, stack, right?
And so the only way this
attack will work is if we can
actually execute code
on stack, right?
And so, please give and explain
what advantage there
may be for marking
Xpix userspace stack
as non executable.
I think I just gave
it to you, right?
So what's the advantage?
If we went with Mike's
stackoverflow example,
would you be able to mount
a stackoverflow attack if
you have the X bit set to zero?
Yes or no? No, why not? Yeah.
Yeah, because you cannot execute
anything on users stack.
It's protected with the X
Bit set to zero, right?
So that's an easy one, right?
So security, stack overflow,
let's go to the next one.
Imagine you wanted
to modify X six.
Okay, now we're asking
about XV six to set
the execute bit on the user
space binary code space,
but clear it for the
binary data space, okay?
So, what would you have to
do what would you have to
change about the exact call
in order to make this
work within XV six?
Yeah.
Am specific functions
or for example, you,
you might just modify BM
to accept different
blacks or square,
it's like it's asking to sort of
give a description a
high level description
of what changes to the code
you would have to make without
actually writing code or
referring to specific
functions, right?
So it's a bit higher
level question, yes.
Exactly when you allocate
first few pages,
when you allocate
the first page,
you have to set to execute
it, you have to turn it on.
Is that's where the
instructions are stored?
Mm hmm. Then you turn it
off for all the other.
Okay, but what
happens right now?
Well, right now,
it doesn't set the
critical where's the
code and data allocated?
Are they allocated on the same
frame or in different frames?
Yeah. Right now,
the code and static data
are in the same page.
Or they could be
in the same page.
So we need to in the same page.
I know that the code isn't
in a different page,
and static data isn't
a different page,
and then we only have to execute
permissions on the code page.
Right. Does everyone get that?
So there's a possibility
that your code and data
today in Xp six can actually
be in the same page.
Now, at what granularity
do we control
permissions on the
physical frames of memory?
That granularity
is a single page.
If we want to set
our permissions
differently for different pages,
naturally, you want your
code to go into one page
and your data to go
into a separate right?
And so that's a thing number
one you want to do in your exac.
Without really talking about
specific code or functions
that you would call,
you should be able to provide
a description of this.
And the second thing
you want to do is
you actually want to sort of set
the X permission bit and reset
the X permission bit in one case
versus the other. It
has to be different.
So one for code
and zero for data.
So how do you approach
this question, right?
If you're completely
lost, right?
You know, the way
to think about it
is where do I get started?
You know, how do I start
thinking about this question?
You know, you should
start by asking yourself,
Okay, the question is
asking about code and data.
Where is code and data, right?
Where are they located in
the virtual address space.
You have to kind of have an
idea of where things are
in your virtual address space
before you even start
answering this question.
If you don't know that, there's
no way you can answer
this question.
So that's your
starting point, right?
And then what is the granularity
of the page table
protection mechanism?
What does that mean? It
sounds fancy, right?
If you don't get the
question, raise your hand.
Really? Okay,
that's fine, right?
That's fine if you
don't get the question.
The question is really asking.
I provided the answer
for you, right?
When you set your
permission flags,
how much and what
memory do they protect?
That's what the question
is asking, right?
And so at what granularity
do the PTE flex work?
They protect a single
physical frame, right?
And so what's the
next logical step?
The next logical step is
combine the two
observations above,
and so that's how you
arrive at the answer
that you need to put them
into separate frames,
and need to control because
you need to control
them with two separate
sets of permission bits.
And the permission bits
will have to be set
differently depending on
whether or not it's codo data.
And that sort of
implies the code,
you actually have to go
and write in the exact.
That becomes an
implementation detail
that to some extent is sort of,
you know, formulaic
at this point, right?
But that's the part that
you need to understand.
Yes. Aren't I might be
understanding exact rounds,
but aren't the coded dated
pages already separated? Six?
Well, they can end
up in the same page.
So somebody said that they
can end up in the same page.
It is possible. So you
just have to make sure
that it doesn't happen.
If that is the code,
larger 4 kilobytes.
What does that happen in
the case for the code
is larger than 4 kilobytes
or it is happening.
Okay, so if the code is
larger than 4 kilobytes,
let's say it's 6 kilobytes
and the data is 2 kilobytes,
can the code and data
still be on the same page?
Does it matter how large
your code and data are?
Only if you actually
explicitly allocate them at
page granularity and separate
them out into two
separate frames,
will you actually
ensure that there's
no sharing of physical
frame between
code segment and data
seg? Makes sense?
Yeah.
Okay. So no matter
how big they are,
if you don't do
something specific,
you may end up with
one frame that actually
shares code and data.
And then you cannot control
the code and data
in a single frame
differently because they have
one PTE pointing to it with
one set of permission bits.
Everyone got that? Okay. Um
Oh. What are we doing here?
Okay. Jesus. So basically,
we've been building a disc
swapping algorithm, right?
And I actually already
covered this in the lecture.
So let's go through
this quickly.
We had this finite state
automaton with trying to ask,
at what point and what are
the mechanisms given to us to
be able to set the access
bit zero back to one.
So the architecture you're
building in the system has
a very primitive
hardware paging system.
You know, how primitive?
What does that mean? The
only mechanism we have.
So the only permission bit we
have paging system is
a present bit, right?
We do not have a write bit,
so all pages are writable,
and there's no automatic
hardware tracking
of page accesses or writes.
Wow. So all you get
is a present bit.
Go and implement this
page swapping algorithm.
So the architecture does
not have an access bit.
Although you need to track
the access state to
manage a clock algorithm,
so you are tracking
access state logically in
a data structure as we discussed
in that lecture, right?
So please explain how
you can efficiently
track the access state
using the page system.
Okay. So remember the
clocking algorithm.
The clocking algorithm gets
triggered when you ran out of
space and you want to evict
the page in order to put
in a new page, right?
So it starts going
around the clock.
And the axis bit if the axis
if access is set to one,
you set it back to zero,
and you proceed to the
next vertex in this,
in the circular queue.
Now, as soon as it finds zero,
it's going to basically
swap out this frame two,
and it's going to
swap in the frame
five that you're
trying to put in.
And the axis bit is set to one.
So that's just a
refresher reminder of
how the clock algorithm
is working, right?
Okay, so now we have frame
five and we swapped
out frame two.
So given this clock algo,
when do I need to trap
on the page read?
When do I need a
notification that
a process has access
to page, Yeah.
Your access bit.
With zero with access
equal to zero,
let's call it that because we
don't have the zero access bit.
But very good, right?
We need a trap
when access is zero, okay?
And so if you remember back
to that lecture that I had
on the clock algorithm,
make sure you go back
and watch this, okay?
And I'm going to remind you of
the very important
finite state automaton
that I drew during that lecture.
Nobody else does it, by the way.
But it's very important to
understand what's happening.
You have two states for
the axis bit zero and one.
This is a very simple
finite state automaton.
Remember that the
most inefficient but
perform the most
inefficient way to
do this is to just set
O present bis to zero,
take a trap every single time
on every single read and write.
This would work, but
it's a very bad design,
but that's your baseline, right?
So what do we want instead?
How do we want to improve
on this baseline?
We want most of the reads and
writes to actually not give
us a page fault, right?
That's what we want.
How do we achieve this?
So remember this
finite state automaton
is for the accessed bit.
This is specifically
for the access bit.
Access bit sorry,
accessed variable.
We do not have a bit in
this architecture,
accessed variable.
So access variable can
either be zero or one.
So what are the state
transitions that we
have in this finite state
automaton? Here's one.
This is the most desirable one.
Because it's set to one,
we're performing
a read or write,
so we're accessing a page.
It's still set to one,
no page trap is happening.
The read and write goes through.
So this is what this edge
is corresponding to, right?
Now remember, I told
you that there's
a second transition
from one back to zero.
Who is doing that transition?
Yes, clock algorithm, and
clock algorithm is
already running where?
Running on a trap
handler, right?
So that's not the
mechanism that we can
interpose on because
we're already
in the trap handler
and something
else must have triggered
the trap handler in
the first place,
and it cannot be this thing
because this is the
clock algorithm.
So this is clock. What else do
we have in this finite
state automaton
in this state
transition diagram?
Yes. We have a
transition 0-1, right?
And this is the transition
we can interpose on.
This is what we want to be
able to achieve, right?
If axis bit is set to zero,
we need to have a way of
setting the access
variable to one.
And the only
mechanism we have in
this system is one
bit, the present bit.
And so the solution
to this, guys,
is to basically just mirror
the state of access
with the present bit.
So if your PTP mirrors access,
in other ways, in other words,
if it's set to zero here,
you're going to take a trap.
And then on the trap handler,
you will update the axis to
one and you will set
your PTEP to one.
Okay? So that's the solution.
That's how you do
it in this system.
And the way to get to the
solution is by reasoning
through the finite
state automaton
for the access variable.
Because you know that this
is not the mechanism.
You know that this mechanism
is already done by the clock,
and it's already running
on a trap handler
that somehow was triggered
using another mechanism.
So the only possible solution
is this mechanism. And
how do we achieve this?
Transition between state
zero and state one,
we can achieve this by making
our PTP mirror the
accessed variable.
So if it's set to zero,
we take a trap and on the
trap handler, we transition.
So this is a trap handler.
We transition 0-1 and set
the axis variable to one
and set PTP to one. Yes.
Does this mean every time you
invoke a clock algorithm,
use a page sets the
page to not be present.
In this system, the only thing,
the only entity in
our universe that sets it back
to zero is the clock algorithm.
Nobody else sets it to zero.
That means that it
will only be set to
zero as often as the
clock algorithm runs.
If you don't run out of
memory, it will never run.
I will always be set to one.
Yes. Now, whenever there's an
interrupt caused by a
page not being present,
how do we know that this
is because our present bit
is simply mirroring
the access bit,
and we should just set the
present bit and move on.
How do you know we should do
that, or if it's actually
some malicious thing where
we're actually trying
to access memory,
which hasn't been allocated yet,
and we should kill the process.
Well, for that, you hold the
metadata per frame, right?
So basically, if you
already hold some logical.
So for example,
this excess state
is not a bit in this system.
It's metadata in your data
structure that you
are keeping track of.
And so that's how you
would differentiate
between those two use cases.
Between a use case where
your frame already exists,
and you trapped on it
because that's part of
your kind of inefficient
design, right,
to implement the clock
algorithm in this architecture,
or if it doesn't exist,
we'll know that it
doesn't exist because
the data structure
will simply not exist
for that physical
frame. Make sense?
Dine.
Excellent question.
Okay. So I think I
covered this. You guys
want to keep going.
So you see how it's 308,
and we covered only
four questions.
So I would expect, you know,
roughly that amount of time
and that amount of material
to be on the midterm.
In 50 minutes,
you'll probably be
given something like
what we've just covered.
Four questions. Lack of
write tracking and
write permission bits
in paging system affect
the efficiency of
the clock algorithm.
Please explain why this
inefficiency exists.
So basically, this is a much
simpler question, right?
This was the hard question
because it requires you
to think harder. This is
a much simpler question.
We only get present bit,
we don't get read
write or accessed.
So we cannot differentiate
between reads and
writes. Can we?
Yes or no? The
answer is no, right?
And so if we cannot
differentiate,
what's the most
conservative assumption
you can make in this system?
That's right.
That any excess is right, right?
And so what are the
implications of that?
Because you cannot
differentiate.
And if you cannot differentiate,
you have to make the most
conservative assumption.
That's the thinking part, right?
That's where kind you have
to think a little
bit out of the box.
Yeah. Oh, but you
need to figure out if
you need to swap
something out to disc.
Oh, right?
And so if you have the
information if it's dirty or not,
if it's not dirty,
you don't need
to swap it to disc, right?
You just unmap it and you map
in the new frame because
it wasn't dirty.
But in this particular case,
kind of since we don't have
the ability to do
write tracking,
we cannot keep track of
dirty state on frames.
We have to make the most
conservative assumption,
and the most conservative
assumption is that
any frame that we want to
evict has been written to.
That's the most
conservative assumption.
So every single time you
evict something,
you need to write.
So that's the implication of
this assumption. Makes sense?
Yeah, so I wrote it here
kind of if A is set to one,
we have to assume that the
non existent write
bit was set to one.
That's the assumption
we have to make.
The implications, you have to
swap it because you don't
know if it was written to.
Okay, finally, question six.
Your friend Robin has written
some clever code to make
Singleton initialization
code more
efficient, and this is the code.
And I think the
question was asking,
basically, what's
wrong with the code?
Yeah, what's wrong with
the code, if anything?
And so, see, some
of you will see
it right away, like you, right?
Some of you may not
necessarily see it right
away because you don't really
know exactly what
the code is doing.
You're trying to read the code,
right, and understand
what it's doing.
So here's kind of how to
approach this problem.
I'm kind of trying to give
you this mental framework.
How do you approach these
problems in general?
If you're completely lost,
if you don't know
where to start,
here's the way to start, right?
So first of all, you need to
understand what is this
code trying to do?
It talks about singleton
initialization.
Does everyone know
what a Singleton is?
From 13 31. I'm hoping.
No.
And once you know
what Singleton is,
you'll immediately
know what this
code is supposed to be doing.
It's basically the kind
of class of which there
can only be at
most one instance.
That's the definition of
a singleton class, okay?
And so if that is the case,
kind of when someone is trying
to allocate an object
of a singleton class,
your constructor needs to
do something like this.
Like your constructor needs to
see or let's not even
call it the constructor.
I don't want to bring in object
oriented stuff into this.
Basically, your code
needs to verify whether
or not you've already
allocated an instance
of this class,
right? Yes or no.
And so that's what kind of
this if condition is
attempting to figure out.
If the shared variable P
so the way the singleton
was implemented
internally to the class is that
there's a variable P that kind
of holds a pointer to the
allocated object on
the heap, right?
And if it was not allocated,
we want to allow the
allocation of this to proceed.
If it has been allocated,
we want to disallow the
allocation to proceed.
So that's the high level
idea behind this code.
So now that you know
what it's trying to do,
what is the next step, right?
So we've defined a singleton.
Once you have a high level idea,
identify the critical
shared variable.
So take a step by
step approach to
these very complicated
concurrency questions,
and they are always
going to be complicated.
But there is a specific way
that you can approach them.
Understand what the
code is trying to do.
Figure out what is the
critical shared resource?
What's the critical shared
resource here? P, right?
So now that you figured out P,
kind of squint at the code.
Forget about all the details
and find all the reads
and writes to P,
because that's what matters
from the concurrency
perspective.
So what are we doing here?
We're trying to do a we're
trying to do a read here on
the shared variable, right?
And then we grab a lock
and then we're trying
to do another read,
to do a write.
So we have a read, and then
inside the lock acquired,
we have another read
and another write.
Now, can we say if there's
a problem with this code?
Yeah. Before. Sorry, before
you acquire lock initialized.
Yeah, there is a
chance. Yeah, exactly.
There is a chance
that before you
acquire lock P is initialized.
But even higher level than this,
there's a dumber
solution to this,
a dumber answer that directly
follows from the
lecture that I had.
In the first if statement P can
be if P has a value
that's not zero,
then we skip the rest,
but then it might become
ten but never mind.
Well, you're trying to
figure out why it's clever.
That's sort of a separate
bonus question is
why does Robin think that
this is clever code?
Actually, can someone
give me venture guess
of why do we think
that this code
is clever in the first place?
Like, why would I write
something like that?
Yeah, probably you don't
have to lock if you
already know that
it's initial or that it's been
initial he's trying to
alight the locking, right?
Because locking is
usually expensive.
And so Robin is trying
to say, Oh, you know,
I'm only going to lock if
I feel that I need
to allocate, right?
So I'm just going to throw in
an IF statement over there,
and it's going to
check if it's now,
then I'm going to grab
the lock and actually
perform another check,
which is very nice.
He is performing another check
with this second
If clause, right?
And then I'm going to allocate.
So it seems bulletproof.
Seems bulletproof to me.
Don't try to find the way in
which it breaks because you
won't the reason for
this has to do with
what we went through in
that lecture where I showed you
the impossible assembly code.
Because you are always assuming
sequential consistency.
Now, should you be assuming
sequential consistency
in this case?
Should you be
assuming yes or no?
Under what conditions can
we ever assume
sequential consistency?
This is a good question.
What is the RF zero?
What is the RF zero, guys?
Yes. It's the
programming convention,
that you have to follow to
ensure that there's no data as.
No, the first part is correct.
It's a programming convention,
but the second part
is not correct.
It's not going to ensure that
you don't have databases.
What a DRF zero guarantee tells
you is that your
code will behave in
a sequentially consistent
manner if and only
if you do not have any
databases in the code.
And everything here is
mathematical, define database.
Yes. I don't have a Okay,
can somebody define data?
I'm asking for a
definition of database.
Anyone. Definition of data ray.
You have to know this. Yes.
Same thing.
Yeah, you basically
if you ever have
two unordered accesses to
the same shared
resource or variable,
at least one of
which is a right.
Now, if we have two threads
executing this, do
we have a problem?
Do we have two
unordered accesses to
shared resource which
we have now identified?
At least one of
which is the right.
Do we have that? That's
it. You're done.
And you don't even
have to figure out
the interleaving for
which it doesn't work.
Because you won't be able to.
Interleaving that doesn't work
actually requires
reordering these things,
and it can be reordered.
Because there's no
data flow dependency
between the P
axises, the read P,
and then the second read P,
and then another write P,
not data flow dependencies,
so we can actually do
anything can happen.
You have a database, you're
giving the compiler
a carte blanche,
right, to do whatever
the hell they want,
and either the compiler
or the out of order
processor will
be able to reorder them
where the unchecked,
the unordered if condition
at the very top can
happen in any order relative
to the critical section.
So here's the truth.
You cannot assume
that it's going to
run in sequentially
consistent manner.
You have violated the
DRF zero guarantee. Yes.
Possibly not relevant. But would
there not be a data
dependency between
the second statement
and the malloc
because the P would
change as result of
the malloc assignment?
The first read is
a read and then the second write
doesn't depend on that read.
Because you see that malloc
doesn't take P as a parameter.
It overrides P and the
compiler will detect that.
The compiler will see that P
is actually just
being overwritten.
Right? And so,
but let's assume even if
there is a dependency
between those two,
but it's not going to be
a data flow dependency,
it's going to be a control
flow dependency, okay?
Because it's a jump not
equal or jump not zero
or something like that,
there's going to be a
control flow dependency that
will ensure that order,
and that's fine.
But it's still not
going to ensure
the order with the
first if statement.
And that can be
reordered relative to
the second one in any way,
shape, or form
because you do have
a database here in
the school. Okay?
So this is one of my most
favorite questions to ask.
So determine if
there's a data base,
that's sort of the final thing.
And then remember, DRF zero,
if you don't have DRF
zero, all bets are off.
Anything can happen. You
have undefined behavior.
And so, you know,
I provided here where
you can actually fail.
But basically, think about
the second part of the
question is asking,
how would you fix the code?
So now it's sort of once you've
done this critical
analysis of the code,
and first of all,
you understand why
Robin thinks it's clever, right?
It really is clever, right?
Because Robin is making
the assumption of
sequential consistency.
And he would avoid, he
would elide locking with
this code if we actually
lived in a world where
databases don't exist, right?
But they do exist in this code.
And so, how would you fix that?
What's the way to fix this code?
I can see people
shaking their head,
like, You're breaking
my universe, man.
It's I love doing that.
Yeah. Huh?
Yeah, you get rid of the
outer statement, right?
Have you affected the
correctness of the code?
You got rid of the cleverness,
which was buggy, right?
But you actually made the
code correct because now
you've ordered accesses
to the shared variable.
And that's it.
Thank you so much.
See you on Tuesday.