Okay. All right. Good
afternoon, everyone.
You're going to have
to forgive me to
be for being slightly
winded today as I
made my way back
from the 14th Street
all the way across
campus, pretty much here.
Just came back from the
COC awards ceremony,
which was a lot of fun, where I
happily received
the outstanding Junior
Faculty Research Award
for the College of Computing.
I This brings back
memories because, in fact,
deja vu a year ago,
I was also just
about to get started
with one of the file
systems lectures,
and I got the same award
for teaching as well.
So back to back teaching
and research award,
that's something that I was
really looking
forward to having.
And I'm not the only one in
this audience who actually
had an award from the
COC awards ceremony.
You know, there's a student here
in this class who
actually received
an outstanding undergraduate
teaching award
from the College of Computing.
So I'm not going to
put her on the spot
But I would like everyone
to give a round of
applause for the undergraduate
teaching assistants,
in particular, the ones who are
deserving of such a
wonderful recognition.
So this is definitely
something to aspire and it's
sort of a segue to make
sure I encourage you guys
to do well in this class.
Getting a teaching assistantship
position in this class is
sort of the pinnacle of the
undergraduate CSR career.
And we are going to start hiring
our next batch of undergraduate
teaching assistants
to TA in the fall.
And so we're definitely looking
forward for you to submit
your UTA applications
to the TA app.
I'm going to have a URL
for you next time I teach.
But definitely start looking
out for those emails that
encourage you to apply for
CS 30 to ten. And who knows?
Maybe a year from today,
I'm going to be
standing here and
congratulating one of you on
the receipt of
your undergraduate
teaching assistantship
award at the college level.
Okay, so back to this class.
We started talking
about ordering
ethnicity on file
systems last time,
and it's definitely a handful.
So I don't have any
administrative slides.
We have a lot of material
to cover in this class.
Chances are we'll have some
spillover into Thursday.
So let's go ahead and
get started, right?
Last class, what we were
talking about is we
were trying to get a sense of
why we need all of
this complexity.
What is file systems
really providing us,
especially as far as crash
consistency is concerned?
And I motivated
this with lots of
examples that we white
boarded together, right,
to really get a good feel
for how we have to deal with
this partial disk sector
write interface with flushes.
And how do we turn that into
something much more sane,
something much more
predictable into
this atomic multi block data and
Nde update that our file
system needs, right?
And so we have to deal
with things like this.
We cannot update in
place because disk
interface doesn't allow it.
Instead, we have to make a copy,
then we have to atomically
commit that copy.
We have to find ways of
doing that, and we
discussed this.
We discussed two primary
methods to do this.
The first one was shadowing,
and the second one was logging.
We didn't get to login,
so we only discussed shadowing.
A brief overview of shadowing.
If you recall, maintain two
copies of the data, right?
And we have a shadow
bit which is Boolean,
which basically
points to the version
of the data that's current
at any given moment in time.
So you have to be
careful with that.
When reading, we always
read the current copy.
When writing, we update
the shadow copy.
And then after the
writing has completed,
we flip the shadow bit, right?
And we discuss the beauty and
the elegance of the
shadow bit being binary,
being in one of only two states,
zero and non zero, and that
sort of gives us a way of
atomically updating it in
such a way that doesn't leave
it in an undefined state.
This undefined state is really
what we're trying to
preserve the system from.
Okay? So it's either
zero or it was
corrupted in some way that
makes it a non zero value,
in which case it simply
points to the shadow copy.
Okay, so this is
shadowing illustrated.
On the left hand side, you
have the current data.
On the right hand side,
you have shadow data.
You have some data that you
want to be able to update.
You perform a copy first, right?
Then you perform a mutation,
then you flip the bit.
This is overview, so I'm
not going to dwell
on this too much.
I just wanted to
refresh your memory
because it's been five
days and, you know,
five days in the life of
undergraduate students
at Georgia Tech
is can be very, very eventful.
Um, I want to get on a
tangent, but I won't.
Okay, maybe at the end of class.
So basically, then once
you've performed an update,
you flip your shadow bit to
point to the current data,
and so on the right hand side
is where your current data now,
the most freshly updated data.
We talked about what
happens if you actually do
the sequence of write
operations one after another,
and we actually looked at
the flush disk operation as
a way of imposing order,
and we reasoned about
why you don't need to
explicitly impose order on
the operations one and two,
why you do need to
explicitly impose
order between
operations one, two,
and three and why you also need
an additional order
3-4 and five.
And that's basically overview.
So the TLDR of this
is that we have to deal
with lots of rights.
We also have to have lots of
flushes in order to impose
these ordering constraints.
So at the end of previous class,
I sort of left things with
the following question,
you know, is there a better way?
Because we discussed some
of the disadvantages that
shadowing clearly has, right?
One of them is that you
basically need to
have twice the amount
of storage in order to
keep track of your data,
one for the current copy,
one for the shadow.
That's one of the
biggest disadvantages,
and the other one,
which is the performance
disadvantage
is the number of flushes
that you have to do in
order to ascertain and
ensure the atomicity and
ordering of invariance that
we're looking for in
this case, right?
So journaling is another
way of doing this,
and today we're going to be
talking about journaling.
I So how does the journal work?
At a very high level, instead
of writing directly
to disk, right?
We're going to write what we
want to the journal first.
And then we're going to
write a journal commit
in order to atomically
commit some section
of the log, okay?
So the log and journal
here are being used
interchangeably.
So let's instead keep a
log or a journal of data,
and then we're going to keep
a record of what the
new data should be,
and we're going to
put that in the log.
And then we're
going to atomically
commit the record in the log.
For any committed log record,
the log supersedes the
actual data block, okay?
So basically, there's
the supremacy clause
between the log
and the data on disk that
if there's a committed
entry in the log,
then it supersedes
the actual data block
or the metadata block in
the file system, okay?
So whatever's in the
log, if it's committed,
it supersedes whatever's in
the data or metadata
part of the file system.
Otherwise, if it's
not in the log,
we go to the data block or
the metadata block that's
actually in the file
system in order
to read from there, okay?
So here's what the
log looks like.
You have an entry, then
you place a commit.
The entries can be
of different types.
You know, it can be
a data block update,
it can be an ode update.
And then the second
field there is
basically the location of where
the data block or the
ode block is that
you're trying to perform
an update on, right?
And then the last
component of the entry is
essentially the payload
or the data that
you really want to go to
that location of
that type, okay?
Any questions so far?
Question. Awesome.
Yeah. Once you commit,
you still the entries.
Okay, so we're going
to get to that
because you cannot do
it infinitely, right?
I think where you're
going with this question
is that it seems that
if you keep doing this,
here's another entry, right?
Here's another commit,
here's another entry,
and so on and so forth.
So we can't really do
that ad infinitum.
So there has to be some sort
of mechanism to operate
within the fixed resources
available to you on a
particular computing system,
right? And we're
going to get to that.
So I'll get to that question.
So if an entry, however,
is uncommitted, right, then
it's considered invalid.
And it has very important
consequences as a result of
this that we will revisit
a few slides from now.
What's important, though,
is that as soon as you
find by sequential
scanning the log,
as soon as you find an
entry that was uncommitted,
everything else after that entry
is going to be invalidated.
We're not going to
consider anything
following the entry
that is uncommitted,
even if everything else in
the suffix of the log has a
commit that's valid, okay?
And that's an important
valid prefix property
of the log that will give us
the guarantees that we want.
Okay.
So just to make sure that
everybody understands the
supremacy clause, right?
So let's say that we're
reading block seven.
And in this particular case,
we have an entry, right?
We have an entry right here,
and it has a commit.
And the entry is of
the following type.
It's a data block.
It's located in location seven,
and it has a hello world, right?
And in the bottom
right hand side,
what we have is a set
of data blocks on disk.
And one of them is
a data block seven.
Which contains some data.
So now we have some data on
disk in the data block seven,
and we have some data in
the log in the first
entry in the log.
Okay? So the question is,
if I read block seven,
where do I get my data from?
Do I get it from the log or
do I get it from
the data blocks?
Yeah. Why?
Because of the commit, right?
Because the commit is valid.
And more importantly,
not only because
the commit is valid
for this entry,
because all the commits up to
and including this
entry are valid.
Okay? So that's a
trick question.
If I were to point you to
some entry for which the
commit is actually valid,
but there exists an entry in
the prefix of the log
that's not valid,
then you would be reading
from the data blocks.
Makes sense? Because of
this prefix property
that we're looking for.
Okay. And here's
another example,
which is also pretty
straightforward.
You have an entry in the log for
and you also have a data block
for block six. So
it's right here.
In this particular case, where
would you be reading
the data from?
You're trying to read block six.
An entry for it
exists in the log,
and an entry for it exists
as a data block on disk.
Where would you
read the data from?
You would read it from
data blocks, right?
disk. You would read
it from the data blocks
section of your disk.
Okay. That should be
pretty straightforward.
Is anyone confused yet?
Okay. Very good.
So, What's so special
about logging?
Why are we using this
particular structure?
So far, I've only been talking
about sort of the
mechanics of this, right,
how this works and
what the rules are
associated with using this
particular structure.
The reason we use
logging is because of
its append only semantics.
One thing I believe I
forgot to mention is
that we are only allowed
to append to the log.
And that is very important
because by design,
it actually gives us this
sequentiality, right?
It gives us this ordering
because we are only
appending to the log.
We're never writing
to the log in
arbitrary locations of the log.
Every entry, so every
write operation,
every mutation that we want to
do is going to be locked in
a professional the ordering
semantics that
we're looking for.
Okay.
And so that is how
you achieve ordering,
simply by nature of the fact
that a log is a pen only.
Now, does it give us
atomicity, right?
In addition to ordering,
we also want to have a mechanism
that gives us the ability to
enforce this happens before
relationship between
an entry and a commit.
And I want to make
absolutely sure
that you understand
what that means, okay?
A happens before relationship
is not just English.
It's a mathematical construct.
It's a relation, okay?
It's a relation that
creates a partial order
imposed on a set of
vertices in your universe.
In this particular case, a set
of vertices are
entries and commits.
And we're going to draw
some partial orders on
the whiteboard today,
which is a lot of fun.
Because it really clarifies and
crystallizes the
thinking that goes into
designing these various
different types
of journaled file systems.
Believe it or not,
there are actually
multiple different types
of journaled file systems.
And in order to understand
the differences between them,
in order to appreciate the
trade offs each of them is
inducing in the trade off
space that we
haven't yet defined,
you really have to
understand the nature
of the happens
before relationship.
What does it mean?
So if there is
a happens before relationship
between verdicts
A and verdict B,
right, that means that
if B has been written,
it implies that A has
also been written.
So A arrow B means that if
B has become visible
to the outside world,
it implies that A is also
visible to the outside world,
and that is what ensures
atomicity of A, okay?
That's the mechanism for us to
ensuring the atomicity of A.
Okay. So let's briefly
go through the we're
going to come back
to this in a second.
Let's briefly go through
the properties of
the log just to put
them on a slide, right?
So it gives us this implicit
ordering of operations.
And the reason for
this is because it has
this append only
semantics on right.
It's sequential order
reason recovery.
So we're going to get to
the recovery in a second.
But basically, in addition
to append only writes,
you also want to make sure
that when you recover,
you read it from the log
in a sequential fashion
as well, right?
And we'll discuss recovery in
a bit more detail later on.
So logs provide us with
ordering almost by design.
And specifically,
what that means
is that it gives us
the ability to have
this relationship
where entry sub
by happens before
entry sub by plus one.
Okay? So the ordering between
entry sub by and entry suba plus
one is ensured by the apparent
only semantics of the log.
Okay. Now, does it
give us atomicity?
As I mentioned, the answer
to that is no, not directly.
The log does not automatically
provide atomicity.
Aimsity is implemented by
this commit by committing
the records in the log.
And so let's see how this works.
But first of all, remember
from the previous lecture,
we also were curious whether or
not we need to perform
some sort of ordering
between the commit for
the previous entry and
the entry that follows.
So we definitely want
to make sure that to
ensure atomicity,
we need to establish this
happens before relationship
between entry suba
and commitab, right?
The entry Say plus one
and commitaylus one.
But the question is, and we
have mechanisms for this.
We discussed flush, right?
That's one mechanism.
But the question is, do we
want to also ensure that
the commits a by happens
before entry subi plus one?
Is there any reason
for us to ensure that?
In other words, can they
be written to this
at the same time?
Yes. The entries
after. I'm sorry?
No, that's not
exactly what I said.
I said is that when
you're reading through
the log, for instance,
either during recovery
or in order to find
whether a particular block
you're trying to
read is in the log,
as soon as you encounter
an invalidated entry,
you stop passing the log, right?
But the way the log is actually
populated is sort of
orthogonal from that.
And there are multiple different
ways of populating the log.
The first one is the
sequential that includes
the flushes to
ensure that happens
before relationship between
entry and commit, right?
And so you're kind
of appending entries and
commits one at a time.
But then if you recall,
you're doing these
writes, right?
But doing these writes
in isolation is
not sufficient to ensure
that happens before
relationship.
We need an additional
mechanism like
flush in order to
do that, right?
And so the question is
based basically whether
or not we need to have
a flush between a commitr
by an entry IP score, okay?
And so one way to maybe
draw that to make it a
little bit more clear is,
let's say you have entry one.
This is the log, by the way.
This is your log. And we have
entry one followed
by commit one,
and then we have entry E two,
followed by commit two.
This is two. And then
we have entry E three,
followed by commit three, okay?
And to ensure that
happens before
relationship between any IAB by
pair by the way to do that is
to put a flush in between.
Okay? And so a flush
imposes partial order.
So we know that if we put
a flush between E one and C one,
we're going to create the
following partial order,
E one in the set by itself,
and then this happens
before arrow, right?
And then we open a new set
that starts with C one, right?
We've imposed this partial
order with the flush.
And so the question is,
do we need I'm going to put
a dash line right here.
Do we need a separate flush
that imposes order
between C one and E two?
Do we want to make
sure that E two
is guaranteed to be sort
of written after C one?
Or do we care? Is there
anything bad that's going to
happen if C one and E
two are written simultaneously
or out of order to disk?
There was a yeah. E two
is written before C one,
then there could be a case
where something is
trying to read E
two and then you'll
go to the blocks
even though E two is the pile.
Yeah, it'll construct
everything after C one invalid,
whereas E two might
actually be valid still.
So I think you're trying
to prematurely optimize,
but all we were trying to
ensure is that we're
crash consistent, right?
So it is indeed possible
for E two to be
written before C one,
and then let's say
crash happens.
And in that particular case,
E one would not have
been committed, right?
E one would not
have a commit bit
actually written to disk.
And so what you would have in
the log is that you would have
E one invalid and E two invalid.
Is that a problem? With
respect to crash consistency,
it is actually not a problem.
Yes, you've lost some rights,
but that's not what
we're optimizing for.
We're optimizing for
crash consistency.
correctness in this particular.
We're ensuring correctness
with the set of
techniques and mechanisms that
we are discussing today, okay?
So writing E two out of water
with C one is actually not
a problem if crash consistency
is what we're trying
to ensure, okay?
In other words, it is
not necessary for us
to actually impose
a flush between consecutive IA
by Csa by pairs in the log.
And so we will ensure ordering
between IA by and Cis by with
a flush for each of
the pairs, right?
So what you have is essentially
your second set in
this partial order starting
with C one and E two.
And then there's this
particular happens
before relationship that
insured by the flush.
And then you have a
C two and E three in
the third set and C three
in the fourth step.
So that's how you actually get
a partial order out of this law.
So E one will happen
before everything else.
And then after
that, in any order,
you can write all of the
elements in this set,
then it happens before, then all
of these elements in the set
can be written in any order.
It doesn't matter.
That doesn't matter.
And then it happens before
and then C three. Yes.
Then we are enforcing that C
two happens before say C
one happens before C two.
Yeah, exactly. So notice
what we've done here.
What we've ensured,
just like you said,
but I'm going to correct
it a little bit.
This way is actually it is
sufficient for us to
have this flush between
I by to guarantee the
ordering as well, right?
You're actually guaranteeing
that ISA B is going to
be persistent before IA by plus
one for any I And you don't
need this additional flush in
between the pairs in
order to do that.
You can allow some reordering
of CA by and IA by plus one.
Makes sense?
And so I'm jumping
ahead of myself here,
but since we have this
on the whiteboard,
you can already see that
we're starting to save
some flushes here
compared to shadowing,
where shadowing
required three flushes
for us to perform
two writes, right?
Those two writes could have
corresponded to, let's say,
e1c1 and e2c2 with
only two flushes,
so we will have already
saved one flush.
In addition to not requiring
this memory or, I guess,
storage overhead
in order to keep
track of the current data
and the shadow data.
So we've already won,
even with this limited
rudimentary journaling approach.
And you should always
make sure that it
checks out on all of the
properties we're looking for.
Is it consistent with
the ordering of IABse?
It is consistent with
the ordering of IABis.
Does it guarantee atomicity?
It guarantees the atomicity
of every IABi, right? Because?
Why? What's the how do
you answer this question?
Because pick any seed,
let's say CSA Bi,
and then if CSA BI is
committed or written or visible
to the external universe,
then this implies
that Isabai is also
visible to the external universe
because of this partial order
that was imposed by Flush.
Any questions so far?
Okay, let's keep
going through this.
It will become a
little bit more clear.
So this is our commit
mechanism number one.
Basically, the
question is or part of
the discussion we need
to have is how to
ensure atomic
rights for commits.
And you could also be writing
basically single block
granularity, right?
Because we're
guaranteed atomicity
at single block granularity.
One block for the entry,
one block for commit,
one block for the entry,
and so on and so forth.
But this is clearly
suboptimal, right?
So instead, what we're
doing is what I have
just described.
You have a right for the entry,
and then you put a flush
and you have a right
for the commit.
And this gives us this
happens before relationship.
So again, E one,
followed by the flush,
followed by C one, right?
And then you have E two,
followed by the flush,
followed by C two,
and then you have E
three followed by the
flush, followed by C three.
So the flashes are
giving us this
happens before semantics
that we're looking for.
And yeah, and this is
just of what we discussed
with this particular log.
And this is how you would
instantiate the partial
order or direct
the graph out of
the vertices that are
participating in your log, right?
And we discussed how you
don't need an
additional flush here.
You can allow some out
of order operations
between CI and de capital for.
Okay. So this is commit
mechanism number one.
We can see that we've
arrived at a point in
the design space where
we're getting itemity,
we're getting ordering, and
we're doing better in terms
of performance, right?
So we're achieving
correctness and we're
improving on performance
relative to shadowing.
So we should be
very happy, right?
And there must have been a point
in the design space at
some point in time,
but we've moved on
from that point.
There are some better
ways of doing this,
and this is what I'm
referring to as commit
mechanism number two.
Let's motivate this commit
mechanism number two
with a question.
Somebody asked me the
following question, right?
And it was a really
good question,
and sort of I gave me pause.
So the question was, how
can we distinguish between
an erroneous commit and
an invalid commit, right?
What if we make a mistake
when writing an entry?
So let's say we've
written an entry and
then we've written a
commit and there's
a cosmic ray or a bit
flip that sort of
went unchecked in the
process of a write?
And do we have
any mechanism of actually
detecting that, right?
So at this moment in time,
we only use the commit write
as sort of a signal that
the entry corresponding to
it has been written to
disk, and that's it.
That's the only way
in which we're actually
leveraging a commit.
So here's an insight for you.
Since we're writing a commit to
serve that purpose
already anyway,
why not make it a checks?
We're already spending it right,
which is an
inexpensive operation.
We're already doing
that in order for us
to actually ensure and enact,
in fact, the ethnicity
of the entry that
it corresponds to.
Let's just overload it and
give it some semantic meaning.
Thank you to check some of
the entry that we're writing.
It seems pretty like a sort
of not quite a leap
of faith, right?
It seems pretty
thing for us to try.
So instead of just writing
some arbitrary data for CSA Bs,
make it a checks of ES one ESAB.
So how would that work?
To commit an entry,
what we're going to do is
we're going to compute
a check sum of that entry, okay?
And we are also
going to make it possible for
multiple entries on the same
this block to be written.
We can write all of them
in a single operation,
and we can compute
a single check sum.
So I believe in XB six,
this is called a
group commit, right?
So it is actually possible
to have a group commit with
a single check sum
that's calculated on
multiple writes in
a single operation.
And so why is that interesting?
Well, that's interesting because
checksum is now overloaded.
It still gives us this ability
to impose order and
ethnicity, right?
But it also gives
you the ability
to validate or
invalidate the entries.
So in other words, if you
check the checksum, sorry,
if you read CSA B and it doesn't
correspond to the
check sum of ISAI,
we will consider
that entry invalid.
Okay?
Everything else stays the same.
Everything else stays
the same. Mm hmm.
A very interesting question is,
what does that by us,
this additional thing, right?
Well, it buys us very,
very cool properties and
huge performance improvements
as it turns out.
Now, let's see what logging
with checks on
commit looks like.
Any questions? Oh,
sorry, I didn't notice.
Yeah. Entry. Would you what?
Would you recommit that entry
or Would you recommit
that I mean,
it depends on what
you're doing, right?
So for example, if
you're performing
a read operation
on block I, right?
And the first thing you're
going to do is you're
going to traverse
a log to see if that block
I is already in the log, right?
And so you'll be
traversing the log for as long
as the entries are valid.
Where valid is defined
as the check sum of
ISA B equals to CSA B.
Okay.
The termination
condition of this for
loop is essentially you're
encountering an entry for which
this equality no longer
holds true, okay?
So like your question
is a little bit vague.
It depends on what you're doing.
So if you're doing
this screen operation,
you wouldn't recommit anything.
You basically just stop. It will
be a termination
condition, right?
Okay.
I Does that answer
your question?
Okay. So what you
mean when you're
performing a write
and you're writing
into the log, right?
So when you write
into the log and the entry was
written and the
checks was written,
you know, presumably
there's there's
a way to check that that
write was actually has
gone through and the checks
corresponds to the commit.
Yeah. You would not would
not perform this operations.
Okay, let's see how
this is useful, though,
because it's actually when I
saw this for the first time,
it kind of really blew my mind.
So now we have the
same situation here.
You have a log and it has
a bunch of entries, right?
So what's really,
really interesting is
that these entries
can now be written to
the log in any order,
and that's mind blowing.
Now, sequentiality is
still guaranteed by
basically grabbing a position to
which you're going to
perform a write, okay?
So there's a specific log block
to which you're
going to be writing,
and that is given to
you in sequence, right?
So write operations are still
sequential and they are
ordered by virtue of
actually getting this
log block number
to which the write is
supposed to happen.
But you don't have to wait
for the write to complete.
All of these writes, both for
the entries and the check sums
can actually happen in any
order. And that's crazy.
Now, you no longer need
to have this flash
between the IAA and CAB if
you're using checksums.
I'm going to let you think
about this for a second,
because that has tons
of implications, right?
The way you should be thinking
through this is what happens if,
you know, E three and C
three gets written, right?
E one gets written
but not C one,
and then maybe C two gets
written but not E two.
And you should be thinking
about what happens
when we are performing
a read or when we're
performing a recovery over
a log like this in
situations like this. Yes.
I might have missed this, but
let's say you perform a write
on a block on
a location that's already
in the log, right?
So you perform a write
and you append it to
the end of the log.
And then when you perform a
read on that same data block,
how do you differentiate
between the first write
and the second write?
You don't. You don't have
to differentiate, right?
So if you perform two writes
to the same data block,
there will be two entries
sequentially ordered in the log.
So you don't stop when you
see the first location?
Why would you? Yeah. If
you're performing a write,
it's just a mutation
operation that you log.
When you read, you have to read
the entire log so that then you
apply the first write and
then you apply the second write,
assuming both of them are
actually valid rights.
And so what's interesting
is that you let's
say there are K rights
that were appended
to the log, right?
But only a small subset of them,
let's say the third right
for some reason was invalid.
It doesn't have a valid commit.
So upon reading the
log left to right,
you will only consider
the first two rights
and the rest are going
to be discarded.
So remember that it is
possible to miss rights,
right, because that's not
what we're optimizing for.
What we're optimizing for
crash consistency and
making sure that we
leave the system
in the same state.
Okay.
Can we can we flush
the log after a certain
amount of rights,
I guess, because, like,
it's we're guaranteed that
they're going to persist, it is.
Yeah, yeah. So basically,
I really like where this
question is going, right?
As a developer, you
have no guarantee
that the stuff you're writing
actually persists to disk.
There is a way to do that,
but it's very expensive.
And we're actually going to
get to how to do that both
from the application
perspective and
from a file system
perspective, okay?
And basically how expensive
the FSInc actually
is when you do try to
persist something to
disk because you really,
really want it to
be on the disk.
But yeah, that question really
stems from the right place
in your thinking that you
should understand by
now that when you're
performing a write clocking
write and it returns,
and it says it has successfully
written, it means nothing.
The data may not have
persisted to disk, okay?
It's still somewhere out there,
potentially in the log,
somewhere in memory.
And in order for you to
actually persist your data,
you really need to work quite
hard for it to be
persistent to disk.
But let's get back to this.
So the checksum is
really beautiful
because we really got rid
of all of the flushes.
Okay? And so you can
take advantage of
the vector processing
capabilities of your modern CPUs,
for instance, in
order to calculate
the check sums in the
SIMD fashion, right?
Single instruction,
multiple data.
You have multiple data
in this particular case,
multiple entries, which you
can write at the
same time, okay?
And you can calculate their
check sums at the same time,
and you can write the
commits also simultaneously.
And what's important is that
the order is still preserved
because you're writing to the
right location in the log,
but the actual act of
writing data can
happen in any order.
And that's really
beautiful. Okay.
Yeah, and what
happens is that if
you ever need to go through
the log for whatever reason,
either by reading the log or by
merging the log or by
recovering from the log, okay,
you will stop at the very
first entry for which
the check sum of
the entry does not
equal to the commit
written to disk, okay?
So this entry in this particular
case would be invalid.
And in order to preserve
this prefix property that
I mentioned previously,
as soon as we encounter an
invalid entry in the log,
it invalidates all of the
remaining entries in the log.
And the reason for this
is consider three rights.
Let's say the first was valid
and check some matching.
The third was valid, that
check some matching.
But the second one,
the one in the middle,
for some reason got corrupted
as it was written to disk.
So as you're replaying those
rights one after another,
you want to stop
at the second one
because it can
corrupt your file,
even though the third one was
correctly check
suped and validated.
Does that make sense?
So you never want to go
past the entry that is for
whatever reason, invalid.
It invalidates the
rest of the log.
The entire suffix of the
log is now invalid. Yes.
This log array that's
depicted here,
does it only pertain to
one single location or
one single isode or is
it for the entire disk?
Entries can be multi block.
And entries can also
be a combination
of data block updates and
iNte updates as well, okay?
Remember how we talked about
in the previous lecture,
I showed you some
examples where we
can result in interesting
situations where
you updated updated
the data blocks
but did not update
the iNs, right?
And so we pointed out
that there can be
some security violations if
you actually allow
for this to happen.
So the way for this
not to happen is to
enact some sort of
transactional semantics.
And the way you do that
is with commits, okay?
So entries can be
multi block and can also
be of different types.
Batched together. So you
can have a metadata entry,
followed by a data entry.
See the entries do have
their specific types.
So you would have,
let's say, two, three,
four, five, or however
many entries you want,
either metadata or data,
and then you can place
a commit to enact
this transactional semantics on
the entire group commit, okay?
Answers your question?
Perfect. All right.
Let's keep going.
So Now, let's talk
about these scenarios that
people have already started
wondering about, right?
We have a finite number of
resources in the system, okay?
So what happens when
the log gets full?
Remember that logs are basically
these blocks in a specific
location on your disk.
So there's only a
finite number of them.
It's not an infinite tape
in a turing machine, right?
So what do we do?
Well, we perform
a log merge operation.
What does that mean?
That means that we iterate over
all the committed
entries of the log.
And then for each entry,
we override the normal
version of the data
or metadata with the
version in the log.
Okay? So in other words,
we're performing this for
loop that I
previously mentioned.
You can literally write down
the pseudo code for this.
You know, for each
entry pair, you know,
if check sum of IA by
equals to CSA by, you know,
then perform a
write of IA B into
the corresponding location is
a by dash location, right?
Else continue.
Who is following
the pseudo code?
We want to break out of
the loop at some point.
What's the termination
condition for the loop?
If what?
Yeah. If the check sum of
IAB is not the same as IAB,
that's when you want to
break out of the loop.
No matter what you do,
break out of the
loop, you're done.
You're done with the
entrance in the log.
Okay? So that's how we're
performing the log merge.
And once the last committed
entry is processed,
we want to clear the log, okay?
So Whenever I tell you
something like this,
don't believe me,
don't believe me.
Start thinking critically.
What happens if we crash in
the middle of a log merge?
You know, are we
immune if we are
performing a log because those
are the edge cases, right?
We want to make sure
that the common case
works and looks like it does.
We've sort of convinced
ourselves that it does.
But in cases of
a log merge or
a recovery operation or
something like this,
you know, what happens if we
crash in the middle
of a log merge?
Are we immune to that?
And here's a teaching moment,
sort of a slide that I thought
of this morning, right?
I want to make it clear
why am I asking all
of these questions?
Because I want you to
think critically, okay?
You know, don't believe anything
you're told without
thinking critically.
So why am asking why am I
asking this specific question?
Well, because the log merge
consists of multiple disk
IO operations, okay?
So that means that
they are not atomic.
That means that a crash,
which is a single point in time,
it's a sort of a
catastrophic event,
which is an event on a timeline,
on which you have multiple
nonatomic DCIO operations.
It can happen, okay?
So visualize a timeline.
Visualize multiple
DCIO operations
happening on that timeline.
Visualize a crash somewhere
on that timeline that
interjects in the sequence of
nonatomic DCIO operations.
Are we immune to that?
What is the space
of possibilities?
Think about it mathematically.
Remember, I started giving
you these hints in terms
of how to approach this from
the boundary condition testing.
Can we get the full log merged?
That's one of the possibilities.
Can we get no log merged?
That's another possibility.
It is also possible to log
entry for the log entries to
be merged partially, right?
And so on and so forth.
Some blocks can be corrupted.
So what will happen
after the crash?
Well, All of the above,
these bullet points right here,
they're all perfectly
fine because if
the crash happens before we have
a chance to clear the log,
upon the subsequent recovery,
we're just going to
replay the log again,
and that is perfectly fine.
Okay? We will basically
go through the process
of recovery again.
We'll traverse the log again.
And of course, the assumption
here, which is critical,
is that the log entry
updates must be
idempotent. What does that mean?
You guys know what item means?
Okay, item also, whatever.
The item is where you can apply
the operation to the operand
multiple times and
achieve the same result.
So in other words,
an op X equals to the op of of
the composition of a bunch of
different ops applied on
top of the operand X.
So itemportance here ensures
easy at least one semantics,
and that's exactly what
you want from the log.
From the log recovery.
You want at least one semantics
when you've finished
recovering from
the log. What does that mean?
That means that every entry in
the log was actually written
to the data block or
the metadata block on disk
at least once in an
item important fashion.
Okay. So I mentioned
that at the very end
of the log merge,
we want to clear the log because
we want to sort of give back
those log disks
back to the system
so that we can
finally start writing
new log entries from the
very beginning, right?
So how can we make
log clearing atomic?
So do you have any ideas?
Maybe we can collectively
figure out a way to clear
the log because we
want to make sure
that it's atomic because
if it's not atomic,
it's not crash consistent.
Can somebody tell me how
we can clear the log?
So we're done merging,
we actually want
to clear the log.
Do we want to go
through the process of
actually invalidating every
single entry in the log?
If we do that, do we
start from the end?
Do we start from the beginning?
Do we do it in some
random fashion?
Any ideas? Yes.
Okay good idea?
Because it keeps in mind
ordering structure we had.
So let's say it did crash
in the middle of merging,
you're moving from
the end forward,
it'll still be ordered from
the front. That makes sense.
Any other ideas?
That's not atomic.
Yes. So could you speak up.
Yeah, so basically the way
to accomplish this is just
invalidate the very first
entry, and you're done.
And the reason for
this is because of
that prefix property that
we've been talking about, right?
Because anything that
deals with the log will
stop at the very first
invalid entry, right?
So all you have to do
is you want to invalidate
the first entry.
You don't have to touch the
rest of the log, right?
It's completely
unnecessary because
if we're reading from the log,
if we're recovering
from the log,
if we're merging the log,
we will stop at the
termination condition,
which is an invalid entry.
So all you got to do is a
single right atomically to
invalidate the very
first entry by
writing garbage into
your check sum command.
Let's say a set of zeros
with very high probability,
very, very high
probability you will
have invalidated it, okay?
So whenever we start up,
how do we recover, right?
Whenever we start up,
we merge the log.
So we've already discussed
what merging the log means.
We've already discussed what the
pseudo code for that
is going to be,
and we discussed
that we are going to
stop at the very first
uncommitted entry.
And this is going to guarantee
that old data is
the newest data.
And once you're
done with recovery,
similar to the merge operation,
we're going to clear the log
so that we don't have to
do it multiple times if
we don't have to, right?
In this particular case,
clearing the log can
also be accomplished
in an atomic fashion
by invalidating
the first entry with
a simple right to the first
commit with garbage data.
And now that you've
completed the recovery,
a file system is ready to go.
So we've covered what happens
if the log gets full.
It's just a log merge operation.
We've covered how
to clear the log,
returning the resources into
the operating system, right?
We've covered how to
recover from the log.
read from the log.
So you have everything
you need, right?
And all of these operations
are actually ensuring
crash consistency.
And that's really wonderful.
So let's maybe recap what
the logging advantages
are at a very,
very, very high level, right?
So what are the benefits?
Maybe can somebody tell
me what the benefits
of logging are,
especially compared to
shadowing, things like that.
That we discussed previously.
Why would you choose logging?
Yes. Fewer flushes
compared to shadowing,
so it's more efficient
to write data to this.
It's more efficient to write
data because of fewer flushes.
Yes, that's correct. Yes.
In what kind of overhead?
Shadowing, you had to have
a copy of the data
every single data blog.
Storage overhead, right?
There are different
kinds of overhead.
Precise. Anybody else?
Yeah, those are the
big ones, right?
Let's see what I have.
So this is the one
that's commonly missed.
Remember the rotating
spinning rust,
it really benefits from
sequential access.
So as it turns out,
performing sequential writes
is orders of magnitude.
I don't know.
One, maybe two orders of
magnitude faster when
you're dealing with regular HDGs
compared to random writes, okay?
And so the sequential
a really gives you
the benefits because
your log is append only.
It's very distinct,
especially for rights.
Uh We also established
that logging does indeed
ensure correctness.
It provides us a general
form of atomicity.
It also provides ordering by
the semantics of the
append only logging.
So the log entries are
committed in order
preserving intended order of
operations and performance.
There are very few sinks.
In some cases, we were able to
get rid of all of the
sinks completely.
It's a significant sink
reduction compared
to the alternatives that
we previously discussed.
Do we get all of this for free,
or do we have to pay
something for it?
I guess in the interest of time,
I'll just go through
this, right?
What are the costs
associated with logging?
Well, you do double the writes,
because you're writing to
the log first for
every single write.
And then once you've
written into the log
at some point in time,
there's going to be
a second write that
actually overrides
the data on this,
be that the data block or
the note update, right?
You also must periodically
merge log into actual data,
for instance, when it gets full.
And it is very
unfortunate because you
don't really have as a
user or as an application,
you don't really have that
much control over it.
And so if you are performing
something that's
mission critical,
something that is
soft real time,
something that is very
latency sensitive,
that log merch
operation can happen at
arbitrary can happen arbitrary
and you simply don't have any
control over this, right?
So one of the very
commonly overlooked, um,
disadvantages
associated with logging
is the actual predictability
of such a system. Yes.
Well, how do you re
evaluate the log?
Because you said you can only
append to the log, right?
And once you invalidate
the first entry,
and then you append to
the end of the log,
it doesn't really matter, right?
Well, so you append to a
logical log data structure.
Yeah. But basically, once
you've invalidated
the first entry,
there's sort of an additional
bookkeeping operation
that needs to happen that
returns the log blocks
to make them free.
To mark them as free.
Because remember, we have
a special type of block on
disk that actually keeps track
of a bitmap that figures
out which blocks are busier
and which blocks are free.
So you do that
booking operation.
Yeah. We do that during
a Mrs log operation.
So if you have a Mersa
log and your second right
was invalidated and then
your K write was appended,
that K write won't
be it won't matter until
you MRSA log again.
So why would the second
write have been invalidated?
Or it has been, it
wasn't vaalid right now.
P when you book.
Well, when we're,
we're sort of fixing that
with check sums, right?
So we're now making
sure that whenever you're
writing the entry,
you're calculating the
check sum and then
you're writing the check
sum as your commit.
That sort of takes
care of that issue.
That was an issue with the
commit mechanism, number one.
When we didn't use check sums,
it was actually possible to
end up in that situation.
Okay.
Okay. Yeah. So now we're
going to assume that
with check sums,
the entries that
were written and
successfully to the log,
we will trust that they
were written without
any corruption.
Okay. And this
predictability is my
favorite because I do work
on softwal time systems.
And if I were to ask you
a question that asks you
whether or not you
want to use logging in
a particular situation that is
latency sensitive, what
would your answer be?
What success metric
will this affect
if you allow the
log merge operation
to happen arbitrarily
in your system?
Like reliability or consistency?
Yeah, but success metric is
something that's
quantifiable and measurable.
It has units, almost
like in physics. Yeah?
Latency at the day.
Latency, right? Latency. So if
you have latency
sensitive operations,
it's a quantifiable metric
that you might want to optimize,
minimize, or maximize, right?
And it has units,
which is seconds.
And if you're
performing, let's say,
some let's say GI auto
regressive decode, right?
And you really care
about time between
token latency SLO and
all of a sudden your log
merge has kicked in.
And instead of 30 milliseconds,
you're getting 3 seconds time
between token latency SL.
You would probably not
want to use that system
because it's very sensitive
to this operation, okay?
So the distribution of your
latencies will change.
In particular, the tail of
the distribution
will be affected
by such unpredictable phenomena
as the log merge operation.
So always be very careful
if you're working
with RTOS or you're working on
those race cars
standing out there in
front of tech green that
are really, really cool.
And apparently have beaten
the national record on
two success metrics.
One of them is
fastest acceleration,
and the other one is
the amount of time it
takes you to do
the H shape thing.
I was very impressed by that.
Some people working on that
project are actually CSAC
threat undergrads who will
be taking this class.
Lots of very useful stuff that
can be done with this knowledge.
And so chances are they
would not be using
a journey file system
on that racecar, okay?
Because you have to operate with
the sensor data on a
critical path towards
actuating the brake pedal
and actually shifting
changing what you're doing
with your I'm not a MCI major,
sir, with your wheels
and stuff like that.
So you would not be
using anything that's
unpredictable in that
situation. Okay.
So modern operating system
file system options,
they have the following options.
You can completely
turn off logging,
which is usually a bad idea.
You can do metadata logging,
you can do full logging,
and you can do ordered logging.
And we're going to
discuss ordered
logging at the next time.
I just want to end this lecture,
which is 10 minutes over time,
with the following where is it?
I want to end this lecture
with the following slide.
Okay? There's a trade
off space here.
The trade off space is
spanned by these two axes,
the safety and performance.
Now, if we have first of all,
where do we want to be
in this trade off space?
Upright. That's the
dream condition, right?
And here's where
the bad design is.
You get low safety and
you get low performance.
Now, where would full
journaled file system
be in this trade off space?
That full journaled
file system means that
you're going to be journaling
both data and metadata rights.
Yes? Correct. Good job. Okay?
Now, what about the write back?
But basically, there's
nothing being journaled.
You're just writing
everything directly to disk.
Bottom right?
Bottom right. That's where
the writeback would be.
And now the ordered where
would the ordered be?
We haven't discussed
what that means.
What that means is that you're
actually journaling
metadata updates,
but you're making
sure that your data
writes precede your
metadata updates.
We'll have an example at
the start of the next
lecture on Thursday,
but where do you think
it's going to be?
Yes. Yeah, that's right.
It strikes the balance
between safety and
performance. Okay.
You give up a little bit of
performance because you are
writing metadata updates to
the journal, but
at the same time,
it actually recaps the majority
of the safety because you're
at the very least
making sure that
your metadata does
not corrupt, okay?
And so I want to leave you with
this journally designed
trade off space.
Every single point
on this trade off
space is no better or
worse than the others.
It creates a pareto frontier
of options that are
good for different scenarios
that you're working
with. Thank you.
Thank you.