Just a little this,
this, this, this, this, this.
I got you.
Okay, I
believe we are at time.
So let's go ahead
and get started.
How many of you
are excited about
finally finishing up
talking about file systems,
automity ordering, and
crash consistency?
Today?
Pretty much everyone, right?
Okay, how many of you are
excited about actually
attempting to find some time to
talk about distributed systems?
Also, today, Okay,
so this is one of
those brutal lectures
that is going to be
a workout because I'm
going to try to squeeze
both of them in in,
let's say, 60 minutes.
I'm not even going
to bother trying to
do it in 50 minutes anymore.
This is a lot of material, and
it's also very, very useful,
and you will understand
why all of it
matters and why all
of it is actually
something that I wanted to bring
to your attention
towards the end
of the class that everyone is
just trying to finish up, right?
And I'm going to assume
that the sparsity of
this classroom has to do with
the lab four actually
being due tomorrow, right?
This Friday on April 11th,
that's when the lab four
is going to be due.
But it is important
to still show up
and come back and review
these video recordings,
video lectures that I'm
putting out on Canvas because
your exam two is going
to be on April 16th,
six days from today, okay?
So, pretty much, how many of
you are down with lab four?
Is it the majority
of the room here?
Can you raise your hands higher?
Again, not actually
the majority.
And so I really want to
thank everyone who showed up
today despite the fact that
lab four is due tomorrow.
I understand that you
have conflicting demands
on your time as juniors and
seniors at Georgia Tech.
So a reminder about
exam two should be no
surprise at this point,
but the location is your
supervised lab location.
So wherever you guys go
to your supervised lab,
that's where you're
going to go for
your exam two, I should say.
And the time is
exactly the same as
your usual supervised
lap times, okay?
It's going to be joint across
both sections, unlike exam one.
So everyone is going to be
taking it at exactly
the same time,
and all the rules are going
to be exactly the same.
I don't really want to spend
my class time on this,
but if you do have
any questions,
make sure you reach out to me
for any clarification about
how your exam two is
going to be administered.
As a highest order bit reminder,
it's going to be closed Internet
completely disallowing
GI in any shape or form,
which stands for generative
artificial intelligence.
And I'm, of course,
allowing open notes,
open book, open lecture slides,
et cetera, et cetera.
You will find the exams
in this class being
primarily focused on
the conceptual understanding
of the material.
And so the reason
why it's open note
is because I really
expect you to sort of get
your fundamentals
down so that you have
the toolbox ready to
go so that when you
come to the exam,
you don't search
for which tool do
I apply in this
particular scenario.
You just pull out those
tools from your toolbox,
so you start thinking in
a very a mentally fluid,
agile fashion and resolving
the scenarios that you are
presented with at exam time.
So that's how you
should be spending
your exam time when you
take the exam, okay?
I'm going to give you a lot
more time than exam one.
So the timing is not going to be
restricted to the 50 minutes
that we have for this class.
So that's why we
actually put it into
the supervised lab time slot
and synchronized
across both sections.
Any questions so
far? No questions.
Excellent. So we stopped
our last lecture by talking
about logging, okay?
And logging was this really
interesting discussion,
and we really ended
the lecture by saying
that there are actually
different kinds of logging,
different approaches to
logging that you can
take with their own
advantages and disadvantages.
And we tried to
really categorize
what those advantages
and disadvantages are.
As a reminder, we can
do obviously a complete
absence of logging, right?
That's a thing. It's
usually a pretty bad idea.
Because with some
minimal overhead,
you can do at least
metadata logging, okay?
So the second option
is metadata logging.
And the idea here is that
your logging only
changes to the Ns,
to the metadata to the control
plane of your file system.
But you're not actually
logging the data,
and we'll get to that
in a few slides, okay?
There are really good
reasons for that.
A separate type of journaling
approach is called ordered.
And there's a nuanced
difference between
metadata only logging
and ordered logging.
So in ordered logging,
what you're doing is that
you still are not
logging the data.
So your data plane in
the file system is still
not being logged, okay?
But what we're ensuring
is that the right for
that data is sequenced
before the logging of
the metadata, okay?
And I'm being very careful
with the words that
I'm choosing here.
So we are writing the data
before we are logging
the metadata.
And we'll have examples
of this to clarify
what this means.
And this is actually
a Linux default
for most distros out there.
And one other option, of course,
is to do full logging,
which is actually when
everything is logged.
So any change to
the control plane,
any change to the data plane,
meaning data block changes,
Ode block changes, all of
that is going to be blocked.
But all of that is
going to be logged.
And this is, of course,
fairly expensive, okay?
So today I want to talk about
atomicity and how to achieve
atomicity at the file system
level with Pyx semantics.
So have you heard about Poss?
Yeah, so it's a
unix standard that
basically codifies a
set of system calls.
And it attempted to
do that, you know,
decades ago in the previous
millennium, previous century.
I think it's probably 1970s
when Unix was very, very
popular at the time.
And what it was trying to do is
attempt some sort of
a standard across
multiple increasingly
heterogeneous systems.
I and workstations, as they
were called at the time.
And so for that reason,
it necessarily had to cater to
the lowest common denominator
across those
heterogeneous systems.
And that is why PSIs almost
by design provides very
weak semantics, okay?
It doesn't really give you
very strong guarantees.
The system calls,
especially the system
calls that we will consider,
which are the ones
that are related to
file system operations.
So again, what happens on crash,
we discussed many bad things
can potentially happen.
You can get data corruption,
you can get metadata corruption,
you can get these out
of order situations,
and so things have already been
motivated sufficiently to
sort of worry about this.
And so the modern
file systems took
this approach to
say the following.
We need to at least
make sure that
our control plane is sane, okay?
What that means is
that we're going
to at least protect
our metadata.
And so in systems,
if you haven't encountered
these terms before,
there's usually
something that has to do
with a control plane and
something has to do with
data plane or moving
the bytes on the wire
or moving the bytes to
storage to and from
the different layers in the
memory hierarchy,
et cetera, right?
So that's the data plane.
And so what modern file
systems are trying
to ensure is that
we will at least
try to protect the metadata so
that our file system
doesn't completely crash.
Okay, so what does the XT
four provide by default?
Well, X four, for instance,
as an example of a somewhat
modern file system out there,
it always journals metadata
to ensure, as I mentioned,
that we are not running
the risk of corrupting
the file system, right?
But it does that
in a way that it
orders the data plane writes.
So the data writes are ordered
before the metadata
writes, okay?
But you can still get
poor behavior with this.
So, yes, the ordered file
systems that are employed
in modern file systems,
in modern operating systems,
they try to ensure this
happens before
relationship between
data rights and metadata rights
without actually logging data.
Okay. And so sort of
to illustrate this,
let's say you have three data
blocks that you want to write,
so you want to write them,
and as you're writing them,
you need to update your
free blocklist data
structure auto on disk,
and then you want to
persist your iNde changes.
And you want to do that
in that order, okay?
So you write the disk blocks,
then you update the
free blocklist,
and then you write the iNde to
the log part of
your disk as well.
Okay.
And we want to ensure that
there's this happens before
relationship between
the data rights
and the metadata rights.
And this goes back to the
scenarios that we discussed that
motivated this whole thing
about ethnicity and ordering.
Remember, when I was writing
on the whiteboard here,
I showed you that even if we
write the data correctly,
but you can, for example,
persist the note updates out
of order with data updates,
and you get a crash
in the middle, right?
Those two, if
they're not atomic,
what you can possibly get is
a metadata update without
the data persisted to disk.
So what you can get is your
direct pointers pointing to
somebody else's data
blocks that haven't
actually been
overwritten as part of
this write operation, okay?
And so if you do it in
this order, if you
write the data first,
and then essentially you
flip the pointers to
point to that data,
in some sense, we're
trying to prevent
this from happening.
We're trying to fix
that motivating example
that we started the
sequence of lectures with.
Okay. So as I mentioned,
food journaling is one
of the options, right?
So you can have data
entries with a commit.
You can have metadata
entries with a commit,
all of them intermixed
in the same log, okay?
It looks kind of like this.
What's really nice is
that you can enact
transactional semantics that we
also discussed you sometimes
want in the file system.
So you can actually coalesce
the data entries and
metadata entries
into one big group
commit and commit all
of that at once, okay?
And so remember that
atomicity here is going to be
guaranteed at the granularity
of the commits, okay?
So that means that this
whole thing will be
guaranteed to be crash
consistent in an all
or nothing fashion.
In other words, if the
whole thing is going to
be a valid commit,
then we get the entire state,
the union of all of
these entries exposed
to the universe.
And if we find that the
commit is actually invalid,
we want to make sure
that our universe
doesn't see any of these
entries at all, okay?
So this is the definition of
atomicity is ensuring all
or nothing semantics.
Okay, so what problems do we
immediately see here with food
journaling in particular?
Everything looks good.
What's the problem
with writing data to the log?
Let me ask a more
specific question.
Even more specifically,
if even that
doesn't trigger some
thought process,
the way to approach this
is think of an example.
One example could be,
you imagine something.
Use your creativity.
Let's say you have a two
gigabyte file that
is being written,
and then you only have
a 64 byte node update.
How many orders of
magnitude difference is
the two gigabyte file write
and a 64 byte node update?
You don't have to
count the orders of
magnitude in this
particular case, okay?
I'm not really testing
your arithmetic here,
but it's a lot of orders
of magnitude, right?
And so what is that
going to do to
the fraction of our
fixed log capacity?
As it's allocated to
the data rights versus
the metadata rights.
How much of that is going
to be essentially used
up on a regular basis
by the data entries?
Yes. Much more than.
Yeah, much more than
the metadata, right?
And then you also end up
in a situation where,
let's say you are writing
a very small metadata update for
a file, which is insignificant.
But then because of the
ordering of the log,
it can experience
head of line blocking
from some of the larger
data updates, okay?
And we'll see an
example of that.
We'll whiteboard it just
to make sure that
it's very clear.
So it's also doubling
the cost of every single
write because remember,
you're writing to
the log on disk,
and then you are going to
when you perform a log merge,
you're going to write that
thing again from the log on
disk to the data block on disk.
That's two writes for
every single data block.
So if you're logging data,
you are paying the
cost of two writes for
every single byte of
data written to disk.
Okay? And the log capacity,
as I previously
mentioned, is diminished.
So if you remember the
logs, what's a log?
It's not some sort of a concept.
It's a physical
location on disk,
which consists of a
bunch of log blocks,
and you have fixed capacity.
You have some finite number
N of the log blocks that
you have available,
okay, finite number of space,
even if you don't want to
talk about log blocks.
But it's isomorphic.
Anyway, so if you are writing
lots of data to your log,
you're going to encounter
a lot more frequent
log merge operations,
and the recovery is also
going to be a lot
more expensive.
And every time you
read, remember,
what's the first location
you're checking on
every single read in the
journaled file system?
Do you go directly to the
data block to read it?
Yes or no?
No. Where do you go?
Log, right? And what do
you do with the log?
What's the worst case
performance here
for you to actually
perform a read?
Yes. Log.
Yeah, basically the
worst case performance
here is that you
actually have to go
through the entire log
on every single read, right?
And the log is going to
be on average, right?
Probabilistically
speaking, the log is going
to be pretty large if you're
logging data updates.
You guys see that?
And so you can immediately see,
and I think it's pretty It's
pretty beautiful, right?
You can immediately see
the implications of these
design decisions as they
percolate through
these different kind
of operations that you want
to perform in your system.
You're making your
reads worse, right?
Because every read is
going to now traverse
a probabilistically
larger log file, right?
You're increasing the
probability of log merges,
and that The implication
of that is something
that I mentioned at
the end of the previous
lecture that increases
the unpredictability
of your system
because whenever you're
performing a write,
if there's no space in your
log to log that write,
you have to perform a
log merge operation.
So you're also making your
writes worse on average.
How do you quantify that?
You take the latency of your
write operations, okay?
And you construct that
cumulative distribution function
that we talked about, right?
If you look at the mean, median,
and tail latency performance
of that distribution,
and you will find
that in full logging,
the tail latency is going
to be significantly better.
Nobody's contesting
what I just said.
Is it going to be
significantly better?
No, what's going to happen to
the tail latency in this
particular case? Yes.
It's going to take a lot longer.
It's going to increase
the latency, right?
And so the tail behavior
of this kind of file
system is going to
be a lot worse, okay?
So you're paying with your
tail latency on reads,
you're paying with your
tail latency on rice, okay?
You're paying with
the unpredictability.
And so I can't use a system like
this for something that I
want to do in real time.
You know, that tough,
definitely not
something I want to do
in an embedded system or
a cyber physical system
or a UAV draw, okay?
That's why this
stuff matters, guys.
This is not like it
really matters. Okay.
So as I mentioned,
you also experience
this head of line blocking
for metadata updates.
So if you have a
very small metadata
update that's sort of
blocked by a very large
data entry in your log.
Because of the sequential
semantics that we
expect by design from
the logged file system,
we are going to block the
metadata updates
downstream, okay?
That's called head
of line blocking.
It's a very famous
phenomenon in systems.
It shows up in multiple places.
I encourage you
to remember that.
Um, So as a result of this,
we actually have the problem
of experiencing lack of
responsiveness of
metadata updates.
Now, what the hell
does that mean?
Okay? So think
about compilation.
There are some file system
operations that actually
perform the nature of
those file system operations
is primarily metadata updates.
A good example of that
is GCC compilation.
As a matter of fact,
GCC compilation,
let's say, on a
Linux kernel, okay,
on the Linux kernel
code base was quite
often used as a benchmark
for the performance
of file systems.
So anytime some new
upgraded sort of file system
feature was rolled out,
the first thing you
want to do is try to
run GCC compilation
on that file system.
The reason for that is
because it actually creates
a lot of very small files in
the process of compilation,
those that are so files in
the process of compilation.
There's going to be a lot
of what kind of updates?
What kind of updates would
you expect from compilation?
So you're creating files,
very small files, yes. Huh?
Metadata?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, metadata,
but what kind of
metadata updates?
Allocating your notes.
Allocating new notes.
Good. Any other
metadata updates?
So, see, this is like an exam
type of question, right?
I'm not telling you, these are
the metadata updates that
are going to happen
during compilation.
I'm not going to tell
you this. I'm going
to make you think
about it, okay?
So you're creating lots of
small files across a whole
bunch of directories.
What metadata updates
would you expect?
And you have to be able to give
me an answer to this, okay?
So one of them is creating
a whole bunch of Ns.
There's more, but we'll
move on from now.
I'll leave this as a
thought exercise for you.
So let's look at this ordered,
so because of all of
these problems that I talked
about with full logging,
people came up with
ordered logging, okay?
And so with ordered
logging, as I mentioned,
you're ordering the rights
for the data itself
before the rights to log
of the metadata entry.
Let's say that here, I
don't know if I should
be whiteboarding
or if this is sufficient.
Maybe this is
sufficient for now,
just so that we can go faster.
Let's say we have a file,
here the file is
denoted as data one,
and this is essentially
the data corresponding
to the file.
I should be pointing
here probably.
Okay, so this is the
file right here.
And these are the
data blocks that are
essentially on disk, okay?
And then what we want
to do is that we want
to perform a write on this file.
So here's what happens.
That's going to introduce
some metadata updates
inside the i node one.
So let's say previously it
pointed to these first
two data blocks,
and then you what's
going to happen after
the mutation to the i node is
going to point to these
two data blocks, okay?
So as I mentioned, you know,
we are trying to do
the data write first,
and then we're going to persist
the metadata update
to the log second.
So here's the first thing
that we want to do.
We want to perform a data write
directly to data blocks on disk,
not to the log to data
blocks on disk, okay?
It can be corrupt.
That's a problem,
but we're attempting
not to solve this problem
because it's too expensive,
as we've just talked about in
the fully journal file system.
And then we're also going to
persist or log the metadata
update to the journal.
And notice that I use
the number one in
both of these cases,
and we're going to talk
about that in a minute.
But in terms of issuing
the right operations,
the first write that will be
issued is the data right.
The second right that
will be issued is
the metadata log entry right.
Now, as you well know,
if they're not explicitly
sequenced, they can
be out of order.
But we're going to
get to that, okay?
We're going to get to that
to see if it's a problem.
And only after that as
operation number two as
operation number two
is actually issuing
a commit also to the log. Okay.
And then after that, let's
say you had a second file,
you can and it required
an node update for the
data file number two,
you could start issuing more
metadata updates to the log.
So does this solve the problem?
Oh, actually, let me so
please make sure that you
remember what we did here, okay?
What we did here is we tried
to perform a write
on a data file,
and the write of the
data was issued first.
This updated the data entries,
and then we logged a
metadata update to the log.
Then we pushed a commit, okay?
So let me advance to
the next slide so that we can
try to analyze what's
happening here.
Here's an ordered
mode breakdown.
And it's a little bit
conceptually non straightforward.
So let me please bear with
me on this slide, okay?
So this slide is important.
What's the intuition here?
The intuition here is to think
from the perspective of
externally visible state.
In other words, what
is externally visible?
And the goal is that at
any given moment in time,
when an i node update
that metadata one, okay,
when a metadata one
update is visible,
it must be true
that the corresponding data
has also been written.
And this is by the definition
of an ordered mode journaling.
And we need this to comply with
the consistency of the
externally visible state.
Now, how are we
accomplishing this goal?
What is the mechanism that we
use in order to
achieve this goal?
Conceptually, we want to
enforce a happens before
relationship between data
and metadata updates.
And practically, the way we
accomplish this
is by essentially
enforcing a flush between
a metadata update
and a commit, okay?
So in other words,
what you get so this was
a data file number one.
So this was data one.
And it was pointing to
some blocks right here,
one, two, three, four, okay?
So it's pointing to some well,
sorry, not the eye
node was pointing.
This is the file node,
node one, and it was pointing
to some data blocks.
This is the data block section
of your disk data blocks.
And this is your disk, okay?
This is your disk. Okay. And so
this is your log right
here. This is your log.
And what we did is we issued
a data right directly to
the data block section.
And that was our
operation number one.
And after that, we issued a
write for the metadata entry.
So this is the meta
data one entry.
And I'm just going to denote
it since this is
such a long word,
I'm just going to
denote it as one, okay?
So we have d one directly
written to disk.
So that's your D one right here.
And one is the metadata update
that corresponds to
the node mutation,
followed by a commit one.
And we will enforce the
ordering between as we
have always done with
the journal during
the previous lecture,
we will enforce this ordering
with the flush, okay?
And so what you will end up with
is essentially this
partial order.
You'll have a Data one and
metadata one essentially
in the same group
because there's nothing that
explicitly orders them
relative to each other.
And then a separate group,
there's going to
be a commit one,
and this will be enforced
with the flush, okay?
So that's the result of this
order journal file system.
And that's the partial
order that you will get.
Now to the last line of
the slide, and then
I'll take questions.
The last line of the slide says,
When the commit is visible
to the external world,
it must be true that the
metadata is also visible, okay?
And it is true
because of the flush.
And it must also be true that
the data has been written.
And it is true because of
this partial order that
is ordered by a flush.
So everything that
happened before a flash,
including the data right,
is going to happen before
we perform a write
on commit, okay?
And so that means that
if C one is visible,
This implies that one is
also visible and this also
implies that D one
is also visible
and thus we have achieved
this ordered semantics
that we were looking for.
Questions. There was a question.
Yes. Write the data
to disk and then,
does that have to happen before
the metadata or it can
happen at the same time?
Yeah, so we issue a write to
disk on data first, okay?
But it turns out
that because the disk can
reorder write operations,
when we also issue
a write of the entry from
metadata to the log,
they can be reordered.
And that's perfectly fine
because we're enforcing
the ordering with the commit bit
and a flash before that, okay?
And so by the time we're done,
By the time we're done,
we have this invariant where
if we see a valid commit,
by implication,
both the metadata
and the data have been written,
and we were able to achieve this
without logging the data itself.
Makes sense?
That's powerful construct here.
So we were able to
achieve ordering,
and we were able to achieve
the ordering of performing
a write on D one without
actually logging
it to the journal.
Okay.
So we have these
three options, right?
We can write back, which doesn't
have any ordering guarantees.
We just briefly talked
about ordering,
where the data is
written to disk
before the metadata is
written to the log, okay?
And I'm being very
precise with my words.
The data is written to disk
before the metadata is
written to the log.
And you have journal file
system which refers to
the fully journal
file system where you
commit to the journal
both the data and the
metadata updates,
and you ensure
atomicity that way.
And we discussed the advantages
and disadvantages of these.
So We had this at the end
of the previous lecture,
so I'm just going
to skip through
this very, very quickly.
So let's start putting
our design points on
this Preta frontier.
Where's the fully
journaled solution
in this trade off space?
Upper left, right?
Because it gives us
maximum safety, right?
But it sacrifices a
lot of performance,
and we discussed
precisely the ways
in which it sacrifices
performance.
Right back is going
to be bottom right,
sort of the opposite
of that, right?
It's going to be
very performance,
and if that's what we want,
if that's your
application wants,
you know, we have
that option for you.
That's why Linux can be
configured for you to actually
have no journaling whatsoever.
Sometimes it is necessary.
And order essentially
strikes this balance
between safety and performance
in this trade off space.
It gives up a little bit
of performance because you
are performing double rights
for your metadata updates,
but we do ensure
metadata sanity,
the control plane sanity in
your file system by logging
your metadata updates. Okay?
It's a very, very,
very quick overview of what we
already discussed at the end
of the previous lecture.
In the interest of time,
let's move on to the 0.6
file system interface.
So the question is,
if I'm a user, right?
I'm a user application.
I live above the kernel.
I'm no longer inside the kernel.
I'm no longer designing
a file system vertical
of the kernel itself.
What can I do, right?
Because it seems like there
are so many moving
parts to this,
and let's say that from an
application perspective,
I want to be able to
persist my file with
a I want to be able to persist
my file. How do I do this?
This is the P six file
system interface.
You have read write, make
door, create, and link.
Okay. You have mode and
you own, you have Stat.
You have some file
control system calls,
and of course, you have FSync,
which is the only persistency
Cisco that you have because
it syncs a file to disk.
It makes the changes to
a specified file descriptor
persistent, okay?
That's what you
have to work with.
Um, And as we know, basically,
when we perform an open and
when we perform a write,
at this point in
time, right here,
the write can be cached.
We have no guarantees that
it's actually persisting
to disk, right?
And it will not be guaranteed
to persist to disk until after
we've actually called an F
Sync on the file descriptor.
So the way to think
about this is
your F Sync is
essentially a memory barrier
for the file system.
And only after that,
it's a blocking call,
obviously, and only after
that the write is now
on disk and persisted.
So the question that you
might have is if
you call an F Sync,
how does this interact
with what we have just
discussed, right?
How does this interact
with the journal?
How does this interact with
the log and with the
kernel in general?
And how do our ordering
and atomicity mechanisms
actually interact with an FInc?
So we're going to go
through an example of this.
And the problem here is that
the F Inc essentially suffers
from this property of
the logging that we wanted
in the very beginning,
which is sequential logging.
And so to motivate this,
let me draw something
else on the whiteboard.
How do I get the
second whiteboard?
Okay, here we go. All right.
So here's what's happening.
We have two files.
Of course, there's
going to be a log.
So this is our log.
We're going to be doing
stuff with the log.
Huge surprise. Two files,
File one and file two.
This is file one, and
this is file two.
Okay. And let's say
there's some blocks of data that
these files actually
want to mutate.
We're going to color them.
Let's say the mutation
actually happens to
these particular
blocks of data for
file one and these particular
blocks of data to file two.
And this is our disk right here.
And these are the
data blocks on disk.
These are data
blocks, data blocks.
So this could be
pointing somewhere over
here and over here,
and these two block
mutations could
be pointing somewhere
over here and over here.
So here's a sequence
of operations
that is being done
on these two files.
A sequence of operations
is the following.
So these are the ops.
You perform a write and
another write on file one.
You then perform another write.
Oh, I'm running out of space
here and another
write on file two.
And then finally, you perform
an F sync because you
want to actually F
sync your file two.
This is a sequence of
operations that you perform.
And so all you want is to
persist the changes to
the file two that
you have just done.
And we are operating
with something that
we are going to take
for as a default,
we're operating in an
ordered logging modality.
So in an ordered
logging modality,
remember that what's
going to happen
is that in the log is that
you're going to have your
metadata one update,
then you're going to
have your checksum
and then metadata two update,
and two update, and
then you're going
to have your checksum
for metadata two.
Check some commit for
metadata two, okay?
And so I'm going to carry over
those ops to be at the bottom
right here for convenience.
These are exactly the same ops.
A write a write for F one,
another write and
write for F two,
and an F sync for file two.
Let's not worry about the
file descriptor, okay?
So what's going to
happen in order for us to
actually return out of Fsync,
what's going to
happen with the log?
How's it going to interact
with the log? Any ideas?
So FCN guarantees is that
your file two should
be persistent to disk.
So when it returns,
it tells you that file two
was persistent to disk.
Yeah. Um, so it
doesn't explicitly call
a log merge, right?
But you're absolutely correct
that the end result of calling
an F sync on file
two is actually
going to result in
this particular case,
what is essentially
a log merge, okay?
And there's a reason for this.
The reason for this, now I'm
going to use dashed lines and
maybe a different colored
marker so that you
can see why this is
happening, okay?
The Fync a file descriptor
two wants to make
sure it sort of takes
a dependency on this commit
to. Do you agree with me?
So it takes a dependency
on this commit two, right?
And then this commit
to takes actually
a flash dependency on
metadata two being
written to disk, right?
In addition to this,
the metadata two, and sorry.
And this commit is also
taking a dependency on
the commit one because
there's actually a
flush in between,
and this commit one is taking
a dependency on
metadata one update.
So if we were to write down
a partial autograph
for this situation,
we should be able to do that
using this example right here.
This was a small example,
but using this example,
we can actually write a
partial autograph update
a partial autograph
representation
of the situation, okay?
And what is it going to be?
At the very beginning,
you're going to have your Data
one and your metadata one right?
And then it's going
to be sequenced.
I think I'm going to
run out of space here.
Let me try to go a little
bit further to the back.
So you have a Data one and
a metadata one in the same set,
so they can be
written in any order,
and that doesn't
matter because it's
sequenced with commit one.
So this sequencing is
essentially carried out with
the flash operation in between.
Now, in addition to
this commit one,
remember we were
discussing that you don't
necessarily care about the order
in which your M sub by plus one
is sync to disk relative
to C sub by, okay?
It doesn't really
matter. So you can
put this two in the same set,
and you can also
put G two here in
the same set because
as we discussed,
the metadata sub and data subi
can be sync to disk out of
order because they
are going to be
sequenced by the
corresponding C two,
by the corresponding
commit checksum.
Okay, I see some heads nodding.
It's a bit too
much. It's probably
the most complicated example
you'll see in this class.
And this completes
our partial order.
So this example
right here you can
capture a partial graph a
partial autograph as follows.
And this makes it clear
that if your F sync takes
a dependency on C two,
it must be true that everything
else will have been
persistent to disk.
Yes. There are other
pending commits
in the log which maybe
belong to other files.
Wouldn't those also have to
go through when you call F?
I would say Fnc because,
like, all the commits have
to be in order? Yeah.
Yeah, exactly. That's
essentially the problem is that
FSync is going to trigger an
entire log merge operation,
as he pointed out, right?
Because of this ordering
that we have imposed.
And this is sort of
fundamentally connected
with um with the structure of
the log in the first place.
We wanted the log
to be sequential.
We wanted the log to actually
give us this ordering.
But there's a disadvantage
associated with that.
And the disadvantage
is that it gives
this essentially false ordering
across even independent files.
It imposes total order on
the operations that are going
to be persistent to disk.
And it does that for
crash consistency,
but it comes with
a disadvantage,
and disadvantage is
that if you want to
guarantee persistence
of some file to disk,
the entire prefix of
the log in front of
that specific file in
the log is going to be
persistent to disk.
So it's not exactly a
log merge operation,
but it's a prefix
merge operation, okay?
So that's a problem. Yeah. And I
already have this in the slides,
so you don't have to
take pictures of this.
It'll be included in the slides.
So this is the downside
of logging, right?
You combine all file
system data into one log.
It imposes a total
ordering on data,
and it doesn't even
matter if this data is
coming from file one or
file two or file three.
All of this operation is
essentially conducted within
the file system itself,
and the file system
cares about itself.
It cares about crash consistency
and control plane
sanity of itself,
okay, which is not
necessarily what the user
application may
want to care about.
So it makes these Fsync
operations extremely,
extremely expensive.
They're very expensive.
So the whole point
of what I've just
described is
essentially to tell you
how calling Enc from
a PS six interface
at the user slash application
level actually has
significant kind of
performance implications
if you're using
even an ordered journaled
file system as your default.
Ooh. Okay.
So let's assume we wanted to
modify a file in
a crash safe way.
How would we do this
via a P six interface?
So we're going to be now
switching from file
system view of things,
which is inside
the kernel, okay,
to a user level to the
user level perspective.
So if I'm a user
application and I
actually care about
persisting my file to disk,
how do I actually do that in
a crash consistent
fashion, okay?
So this is the highest level
in the stack, and
the question is,
how do we ensure atomicity at
the highest user level user
space level of the stack?
So what promises
does PoS guarantee?
Very weak semantics.
After an Fn, my data will
be persistent to disk.
That's all we know.
Before an F Sync,
there's no guarantees
about what's in the file.
It could potentially
be corrupt, okay?
So here's an example.
Let's assume we have
file F in directory bar.
The way we modify how do
we modify let's construct
essentially some pseudo
code that will modify it
atomically by only
using P six standards.
In other words, without relying
on a file system whatsoever.
Because let's say we don't
know what to expect
from a file system.
So in the interest of time,
normally I would ask for
some suggestions on how
do we accomplish this?
But it may come as a
surprise to many of you that
you can actually create
a log file in userspace.
Remember just how it
was somewhat surprising
that you can manage different
stacks in userspace.
So you can actually
have a userspace
threading library that actually
switches and controls which
the thread stack
gets to run, right?
And there's nothing
fundamentally preventing
us from doing that in userspace.
Same thing goes here.
You can actually create
a log file in userspace.
So let's create a
log filee, right?
And now We store
the updates in the log just
like we would inside
a file system.
Then we perform an update
on the actual file.
We're trying to
persist atomically to
disk using Post semantics only,
and then we're going
to delete the log.
So by the end of these
four operations,
we will have accomplished
atomic persistence of the
file of interest to disk,
using Post level only semantics.
Okay, let's build it up.
Let's create a log. Okay.
Now we're going to
write to the log,
add some offset size,
and we're going to
write the data that
we want to write
and the check sum.
So this will correspond to
essentially, well,
this is not here.
This will correspond
to a data entry, okay?
And this will correspond
to a check sum commit.
Now, of course, at some point,
we want to write the actual data
to the actual file, okay?
So there's a difference
between those two
because the first one is
writing to the log that we
have just created as
a mechanism for us to
ensure atomic update to the
file at 0.6 level, okay?
And this is the actual write
that we want to perform,
the actual write that we
want to persist, okay?
So remember that. Any
questions so far?
We we've created the log,
we've written to the log, and
now we're writing to the file.
No guarantees yet.
Nothing at this point in time
will have gone to disk yet,
which is really cool.
And then we want to get rid of
the log because who
cares about the log?
We are done with
writing the file.
So obviously, we want
to get rid of the log.
Is this sufficient for us
to ensure persistence?
That is not a trick question.
If I give you the pseudo code
on exam two and I ask you,
have you persisted the file?
What is the true,
false answer here?
You should be very, very
confident in the fact that
the answer here is no.
We talked about this
for three lectures.
How do we do this? We're going
to use an F sync on the file.
Now, is this sufficient?
Interestingly enough, it is
actually not sufficient.
What are we missing? Yes.
I'm just curious if someone has
any ideas because this
is non trivial now.
Now it gets to be non trivial.
Yes. Yes. That the data
you wrote matches the
check sum for corruption.
Okay. So basically, you want to
check if the check sum is
actually correct, right?
So the validity of
the entry, right?
Okay. So not quite
that advanced,
although I do like
this idea, right?
But at minimum,
we want to do something even
simpler than that, right?
We actually want to
make sure that we
persist the log to disk also.
Okay?
We want to persist the log.
And it turns out that that
in itself is not sufficient?
And then the hint here
is that we've created
something inside a directory.
And when you create something
inside a directory,
something happens as far
as the metadata
mutation is concerned.
What happens? The file
system two lecture.
There's something else
that changes when
you create a file
inside a directory.
Yeah. You add a Durant, right?
Where do you add a Durent?
Where does that go? Which
node does it mutate?
Yeah. The directory eye node.
Wow. You see how
careful you have to be when
you step through this code.
You need to also F sync your
current working directory.
And the reason for
this is because
you've created a log there,
which has inserted a Durant
into the directory node.
So you need to F
sync that as well.
Phew.
And finally, when
you unlink the log,
what have you done when
you unlink the log?
Yeah. Modify the directory.
You modified the
Durant again, right?
You're getting rid
of the Durant.
And so you're mutating
the directory,
the current working
directory, I know again.
So you need to F sync it again.
So how many F syncs
have we just done?
Four F syncs, right?
And this is just
scratching the surface.
Four F s four.
You probably thought that
only one is sufficient, okay?
But you need to have four
F syncs to actually make
sure that your file
atomically persisted to disk.
That is a lot, okay?
That is a lot. So why do
we need so many F Sycs?
What is the problem here?
And this has to do with the
semantics of the 0.6 calls.
Is it because I actually
want data to be
persistent every single
time I call F Sync?
Or is it because I actually
care about imposing order?
And F Sync is just the
only hammer that I have.
Yes? It's the what?
It's the first is the later.
The only hammer that we have,
the only mechanism
that we have to impose
order with Post
semantics is FSync.
And so we're just slapping
the FSync here and there,
not necessarily because
we want data persistence,
but because we actually
want to impose order.
And so let's see. In
this particular case,
what order do we
specifically talk about?
In this case, we want to
make sure that we
order a right to
a log before a right to a
file. That makes sense, right?
We do want to
impose the order of
a right to a log before
a right to a file.
There's one more order that we
want to impose,
and it's this one.
We want to make sure
that we write to
a file before we
actually unlink the log.
You don't want to get
rid of the log too soon.
You want to make sure
that the right to
a file actually happens,
I don't want to use
the word persists,
happens before your
log unlink happens.
I'm being very careful
with my words right now.
That's the second order
that we want to impose.
We're using F syncs
for that, yes.
Why is it different users
than in kernel space?
Why did the F sync
every single Well,
so because in userspace,
we have to deal with whatever
is available in
userspace, right?
And what's available in
userspace if you want to
be Post six compliant,
I'm not talking
about, let's say,
Windows or maybe some
non Post compliant
libraries out there
or Cisco interfaces.
Like, if you were to do this in
a Post six compliant fashion,
FSnc is the only
thing that you have
available in userspace, okay?
But in Cryospace have FSIC
and you In kernel space,
you have whatever we
talked about, you have.
You basically can issue
direct rights to disk,
and you can issue flashes.
So the atomicity and
ordering primitive
that you're using inside
the file system inside
the kernel is a flash.
Yeah. It's not an F sync.
F Sync is a higher
level construct
that we're using at the
users at the user space.
Okay, yeah, great question,
though, because, you know,
to put it all together, and
this is how I wanted to
finish this lecture.
So let me get to that
point a little bit later.
So the question is, do I
need all of these things?
The answer is no because
I actually want ordering.
And the only way to
accomplish ordering with
POSIX with this particular
interface is F sync, right?
So that's a problem.
There's actually
a research paper
that's fairly recent,
you know, as far as operating
systems are concerned,
a decade is fairly recent.
Okay? And the issue is quite
explicitly stated that we
conflate ordering
and persistence.
We often need ordering
for correctness.
Remember that ordering is
a correctness construct,
a correctness
mechanism, but we don't
actually need it for persistency
at this point in time, okay?
So FInc just slaps them both
together and gives it to us,
but we can disentangle it.
We can actually create two
different primitives
and OSINc and
desync where OSINc ensures
ordering and D sync
ensures durability.
That was the premise
of the paper.
So It splits F Sync
into two operations.
OSINc is an ordering primitive,
sync is a durability primitive.
So now, What we can
do is we can make
a much lighter version
of what I've just
described by calling
an Syn on the log.
So that ensures this
happens before relationship
between this right and this
right that we want it, okay?
And remember that we
also wanted to ensure
ordering between the right to
a file and unlinking of the log.
So we're slapping an Sync there.
So that ensured the order.
And we also want
to make sure that
the metadata changes to
the directory itself are,
of course, ordered before we
perform a write to a file.
And finally, we can F sync
the whole thing exactly once,
and that will persist
stuff to disk.
We have reduced the number
of very expensive F syncs,
and we talked about why
it's very expensive
using this example right
here, connecting the dots.
We use this example
right here to
motivate how expensive
F syncs are,
and now we reduce the number of
F syncs by a factor of four.
And this is huge.
Next lecture, we're
going to talk about
distributed systems and how I
eventually became a
systems researcher.
Thank you very much. Let's
take the questions offline.
Why do we lag? The user?
Why doesn't sorry. So basically,
flush is a different operation.
A flush the semantics of
flush is different from
the semantics of F Sync.
And it depends on what
semantics you want.
The flush the semantics
of flush, since you
asked the question,
is to make sure that
all the pending rights
that are currently pending
to the disk driver
are executed a before
you perform any additional
disk operation.
So if there's a bunch of
writes that are sort of up
somewhere in the system,
you know, they could
have been in cash,
they could have been in the log,
they could have been wherever.
If you issue a flash,
they're going to be
persistent to disk,
okay before anything else
is persistent to disk.
So this is an
ordering primitive.
And it is really important to
understand that this is
an ordering primitive at
the finer granularity at
the granularity of this
block writes, okay?
So you can impose
this ordering without concerning
yourself with file granularity.
Now, F Sync is a
primitive that gives you
durability and ordering
at the file granularity.
So it says that for this file,
I want to persist
this entire file.
And so it's a higher
level persistence
and durability primitive.
And so depending on what
you want, you know,
sometimes you just
want your rights
to be persistent, right?
And those rights
can be scattered
throughout a whole bunch
of different files, right?
And sometimes you want
just a single file
to be synced to disk,
and you would use
enough sync for that.
Okay?
All right. Okay, you want to
keep asking questions? Sure.
For the final.
Practice exam for the final.
I will think of some practice.
I mean, if you actually I
encourage you and I
want to make sure I
make it very clear,
starting from Lecture seven,
all of the lectures
have been recorded.
So have a binge watch party
to binge watch my lectures,
and they're scattered with
practice exam questions.
Right? So what I could
do is I could literally
refresh my memory and write
down all the questions.
I sort of stated, Oh,
this would be a good
exam question, right?
Just go through all of
them throughout all of
my lectures and think
through what the
solutions might be.
There was one today, right,
that we didn't fully answer.
For example, what happens
with GCC compilation?
So that could very easily
be a practice exam
question, right?
So I already gave you a lot of
practice exam questions
if you just, like,
carefully listen to
what I said during
the lecture because I'm
very careful with my words.
Any other questions?
Yes. Distributed system
instead of I cannot hear you.
Are we doing distributed
system instead of exam?
We will try to do both. Yeah.
So I'll try to split it
into two and we'll do
some prep and some
distributed systems as well.
Thank you.
Yeah. 1 second. I
stop the recording?