Yes.
Test one to three test, test.
I think
the
Okay.
Good afternoon, everybody.
Everyone is so busy
preparing for the
final that you are
continuing to do this now.
I'm certain of that.
So today, instead of
doing the distributed
systems lecture,
I've decided to go with the
overview in preparation for
the with the overview in
preparation for the exam two
that's going to take
place tomorrow, okay?
So it is taking place
tomorrow, April 16th.
You should show up to
your registered lab
section locations.
It should take place
between 6:30 and 9:00
P.M. Leave 15 minute buffer
time plus or minus TBD.
Please make sure you bring
your bus card and your laptop
and charger. What
else can we say?
Well, maybe 32 hours from now,
you can breathe easily
because you will be done
with the final exam,
and in fact, with all of the
deliverables in this class.
And after that, we're going
to have two more lectures of
fun that you don't have to
worry about studying for.
You don't have to worry about
any kind of deliverables.
You can just sit back and
enjoy two additional lectures.
One of them is going to be on
distributed systems
and the other one
is going to be on some research
that I've done in
the past that is
fairly highly cited and
has to do with scheduling.
Tuesday, April 22nd, is the
last day of office hours,
and, in fact, the last
day of instruction.
That's when we're going to
have Section C is going to
have its last lecture.
Then after that, you're
going to have a reading day.
And as far as this
class is concerned,
sort of this is when
the class ends, okay?
After exam two, there will be
no final exam after
exam two tomorrow.
So people have been
asking me about CIOS,
It's an interesting
topic for me because,
as always, there's
a trade off space.
But I do find CIOS
highly valuable across
both of the courses that
I've been teaching for
the past 5.5 years.
So even if you don't feel
like putting prose responses,
even if you don't feel
like giving me essays,
right, please fill
it out anyway.
All of this is
completely anonymous.
What that means is that when
I receive a CIOS response,
I don't know whom it came from.
So this is basically free form.
You can provide your
honest opinion.
But if you do want
to write prose,
And the form is
simply not able to
accommodate the extent to
which you want to tell me how
much you love this course.
Definitely do not hesitate
to email me and put CS
three to ten in the subject
because I always read
these emails that have to
do with the feedback
for this course.
We strive for excellence,
we strive for
student experience,
we strive for pareto
optimal points
in the trade off
space that we are
provided with.
Keep that in mind.
So in order to facilitate that,
since we all love a
little bonus, don't we?
I've decided that I'm going
to create the following
tier structure.
If the class as a whole
reaches 70% response rate,
you will get three
quarters of a percent
of BCIOS participation bonus.
Sounds like not too much, right?
This is three quarters of
a percent of the
final letter grade.
However, if the whole class
reaches 85% response rate,
there's going to be an
additional three quarters of
a percent that will be
added on top of that.
And so overall,
the bonus consists
of the achievable bonus
for this class is
going to be 1.5%.
So this is to help you guys
take your time to fill
out the CIOS surveys.
I'm probably going to
allocate some time during
the last lecture on
next Tuesday so that you
actually have some in
class time to be able
to do that. Okay.
All right. So topics covered on
Exam two are listed
on this slide.
They were also posted on Tiazza.
This is a copy paste,
with the exception
of some extension
that I did under the VMM.
So we're covering
isolation and protection,
kernel organization,
virtual memory management,
interrupt concurrency
and scheduling,
operating systems
and networking,
security file systems,
atomicity and ordering.
And note that distributed
systems is not on the list.
Just wanted to emphasize
that because I want you
to enjoy this topic.
I don't want you to
worry about, oh my God,
I'm going to have to study
for this for the exam.
I if I could,
I would just completely get
rid of all of the
grades so that I
could simply lecture and the
people who want to show
up show up and learn.
But of course, many
of you do need
some incentive structure to
actually be productive,
and so here we are.
This is a set of exam
two instructions.
It will be in person, in
class on your laptop.
Make sure you bring your
laptop and charger.
Aim for 2.5 hours
of laptop battery.
If you know a priori that this
is going to be a problem
for your laptop,
remember that neither
in this class nor in
supervised lab classes we
actually have any
built in outlets.
Unfortunately, there's not
much I can do about that.
Other than to encourage you to
bring a power cord,
an extension cord,
there are wall mounted
outlets that we
can hopefully share
if your laptop
doesn't actually
survive for 2.5 hours.
Try to make it survive.
There are good ways
of doing that.
Try to close everything that's
running on your laptop with
the exception of a
single browser tab
where you're taking the exam.
That'll help quite a bit.
As a matter of fact, every
single time I present,
I do that to make
sure that nothing bad
happens during the time that
I'm actually lecturing
in front of you.
So, there are many things
you can do in order
to make sure that your battery
persists for 2.5 hours.
The exam will be released
and will be visible to
you at 6:30 P.M.
Tomorrow on Canvas,
and the access
to the exam will end at
approximately 9:00 P.M.
So that's the 2.5 hours
that I'm referring to.
Make sure you bring
your bus card.
You have to bring
your photo ID, okay?
So if you have some
issues with the bus card,
we'll still require you to
show us some sort of photo ID.
We'll be taking attendance.
These things will be proctored.
Your physical presence
is going to be recorded.
You cannot take this exam
remotely. We will find out.
So you have to be
here in person,
and we'll validate
that you're here
and you are you. This
is very important.
Please answer all of
the questions to the
best of your ability.
Write down any reasonable
assumptions that
you had to make.
So in the not this
year, but in the past,
there were experiences
where, you know,
there were some implicit
assumptions made
because XV six did
things a certain way.
For example, where the
stack is located, right?
That was one of the things that
I remember from last year.
And so, you know, if you're
making these assumptions,
make sure you just
state that assumption.
Um. Or double check with the TA.
If the TA is inaccessible,
just go ahead and state
that assumption, okay?
Because if it's not stated,
we cannot sort of assume
that this is what
you had in mind.
Maybe this is a brilliant idea
that you actually came up
with after you've finished
your final exam, right?
There's no way for us to
distinguish between
those two situations.
I hope that makes sense.
We're coming from
a place of being
reasonable and being fair.
Closed Internet, not
allowed to use Internet
for anything except
accessing Exam two quiz.
This will also help
with your battery life.
This will be strictly enforced,
especially for exam two.
Um, you know, don't try to go
through lecture recordings.
This is simply
logistically complicated.
You know, I'm not religious
about that particular one,
but it could be disruptive
for people around you, right?
Stuff flittering on
your screen can be
distractive for some people
sitting right next to you.
So let's just try to
avoid these sort of
contentious situations
that are not
really necessary because as
you've seen from exam one,
you don't really
have a lot of time
to watch videos, okay?
In the 15 minutes that you were
provided, you barely
had time to think.
Thankfully, we're not going
to have that problem
with exam two.
Um, So also, if a question is
asking for an explanation,
we want to make sure that
we get some sort of
explanation from you.
It says, Please
explain. That means
that the answer in itself
is not sufficient.
Please provide that explanation.
Otherwise, the answer even
if the answer is correct,
it will only get partial
credit as a result.
It will not get full credit
without explanation.
Any questions about this so far?
Okay. No GNAI for
many, many reasons.
I want to just go
past this slide
because you already know
the drill for Exam one,
and we do have a lot
of material to cover.
So let's go ahead and get
through this real quick.
So let's start with
operating systems.
We have this entire course
almost behind us in
the spring of 2025.
What have we done?
Okay. What have
we accomplished as a class?
A lot of the lecture
focus was on design,
and there was a significant
project based component in
this class where
you actually worked
an actual X 86 Ring zero kernel,
which is a huge kind of hands
on component of this class.
It's sort of approximately
half of your grade.
But, you know,
over the course of
the lectures and exams
associated with that,
we also studied what
abstractions make
a good operating system
and why they are needed.
And that's why we have
these two exams that sort
of test the more
fundamental knowledge that
underpins all of the hands on
experience that you have
achieved through your labs.
So the next set of
topics I sort of put together
slightly out of order.
The order sort of depends
on the importance and
also trying to make sure that I
get to it before we
run out of time.
So let's start with waiting.
Do you remember this
piece of code that we
talked about when we discussed
waiting and ordering?
And concurrency.
What was the problem
with this code?
Is it correct? Yes.
Two threads at once,
then the end result could be
really combination of scenarios.
So either list one would be
like a persisted list or
list overrides the
original therapy.
Right. And which line
specifically would
create that problem?
What?
Right. So basically, line 15
is the one that's pretty
contentious, right?
Because, first of all,
when I ask questions like this,
you should identify what are
the shared resources that
are being accessed here or
the shared memory locations.
In this case, we
have the struct,
right on line six,
the struct list star list
that was sort of
defined over here.
And there's a possibility
for it to be accessed across
multiple different threads or
multiple different
processes, in fact, right?
And then each of these can
try to insert data at
exactly the same time.
So you basically have a situation
like this where you can
create a node L one on
the left hand side,
and L two on the
right hand side,
pretty much simultaneously,
and they can race with each
other for the next sequence
of instructions, right?
And the interleavings
are pretty broad.
So what I usually
like to ask is,
what is the space of
possibilities here, right?
And the set of interleavings
is quite broad.
So how do we reduce
the entropy in this
space of possibilities?
How do we impose some
sort of partial order,
in this particular case.
And so the way we impose
partial order in this
particular case is
by using the acquired release
around the critical section.
And the critical section here
is L one next equals to list,
and then list equals
to L one next, right?
We want those things to
actually happen atomically
relative to the other
execution threads.
Okay? And so what have we
accomplished if we think
about it in a more
principled fashion,
we have reduced the space
of possibilities,
and critically,
we have reduced the
possibilities, the options,
the orderings, the interleavings
that create a problem.
And what problem can we identify
here? What is it called?
If I were to ask you,
can you be precise about
the problem that existed
in the code before?
Would you be able to
give me that answer?
Yeah.
There is a database, and how
do we define a database?
At least one of
them being a right,
and we have this property here.
If we look at the piece of code,
try to go back to
the definitions
because there are other kind of
race conditions that
we can have that
are not necessarily data races.
Data race is just one type of
race condition that we
have been talking
about in this class.
So we use the acquired
release here around
the critical section in
order to enact basically
this atomicity for the block
of code so that it's
atomic relative to
any other thread of
execution that is trying to
insert an element at
exactly the same time.
Reduce the space
of possibilities,
made the code correct, okay?
All right. So we also
talked about how
the simplest possible way of
accomplishing this was
with what kind of log?
Yeah. Okay.
Mutex lock. Any other?
What did you have in mind?
The spin lock, right?
So that's simply
the easiest thing
that you can do is
just do a spin lock.
And what's the problem
with the spin lock?
Yeah. Wasting CPU cycle. Right.
And so the question was,
can we do better, right?
And we sort of came up
with a way to do better.
We simply want the
waiting process to go to
flip so that it doesn't waste
those expensive CPU cycles.
So we came up with this
conditional variable primitive.
And the canonical example that
we used in order to really
study this all aspects of
the conditional variable is
the producer consumer
queue, okay?
Where the producer adds
elements to the queue.
If the is full,
we want the producer to wait.
And if the queue was empty,
uh, before the wait,
we wake up the consumer.
And the consumer basically
removes the element
from the queue.
If the queue is
empty, importantly,
we want to make sure
that the consumer is not
busy waiting on an
empty queue because
it's quite possible that
our queue can be empty
for most of the time.
Okay. And we made
a huge deal about
the fact that we want to
use a while loop, right?
And this is essential because
of the race conditions.
And those race conditions
actually are not
necessarily data races.
There are other kinds
of race conditions
that we can have if
we don't use a while loop in
this particular case, okay?
So remember this when
we try to talk about
basically what happens in
the situation as follows,
where one of the threads is
the producer and you
have two consumers,
C one and C two on
the right hand side
that are attempting to pop
an element from the queue.
What types of
situations can happen?
And by the way, if
they attempt to pop
an element from an empty
queue, the panic happens.
We don't want this
to happen. So what's
the problem with what you
see on the screen so far?
You know, if you will, this
is a practice question.
If I give you this
code and I ask you,
what's the problem
with this code?
What kind of situations bad
situations can it end up with,
you should be able to
give me an answer. Yes.
If multiple threads
wake up on the signal,
only one of them will be able to
pop and the other one will.
Okay, so basically
in steady state,
especially if the
queue is mostly weight
is mostly empty, right?
What he is talking about is
that most of the consumer
threats, in fact,
all of the consumer
threats are going to be
in the CV weight.
You see that, right?
So let's say the queue
is mostly empty.
And let's talk about his point.
And so if the producer
actually signals,
remember that the way
weight operates is that it
acquires the lock before
it gets out of the
blocking weight.
And so how many
consumers will actually
get out of the blocking
weight with the lock acquire?
Only one. That's not necessarily
the problem. That's
the reason why.
Yes.
CV signal picks up one of
the threads and you're
in the CV weight thing.
Before you acquire a lock,
you contact the child
to another thread.
Oh, yeah, let me
get through this,
but is there a
simpler problem here.
Is it possible for any
consumer to wake up even
if producer doesn't signal? Yes.
You have a spurious wake up?
Yeah, the spurious wake
up can happen, right?
So that's one of the things
that can happen is it's
sort of this weird trick
that even if the
producer doesn't signal,
there's a possibility that
one of the consumers simply
gets out of the way,
grabs a lock grabs the
lock right here, okay?
What am I pointing
at? Yeah, basically
gets out of the CV weight,
grabs a lock on the
way out of weight,
and then performs a pop
and the queue is empty and
so we get a kernel panic.
Now what's interesting in
this particular example is that
even if there are
no spurious wakeus,
let's say somehow we
figured out the way to
not have spurious wakeus,
there's still a problem.
And this is quite interesting.
I think one of you has already
started to tell me
what the problem is,
and it motivates
the reason why we
want to replace this if
condition with a while loop.
Okay? In other words, when we
wake up and get out of
this blocking weight,
we want to make
sure that the queue
is still indeed empty, okay?
Spurious wakeup is still
indeed is non empty.
And so we can proceed
out of this while loop.
Now, here's what
can happen, okay?
Without spurious wake ups,
you can have a producer
signal and get out.
And so let's say C one was
actually blocking on the
CV eight right here.
That's where CV one was.
I think I have this animated.
Yes, that's where C one was.
And so after the signal,
let's say C one starts
going through the
wake up procedure.
And so it's on its
way to wake up,
but hasn't really grabbed
the lock yet, okay?
And C two was right above lock.
Right here. So C two comes
in and it can raise
to grab this lock,
checks if the queue is empty.
The answer is no, it's
not empty because
the producer has just deposited
a single element to the queue.
So the queue has exactly
one element at this
point in time,
proceeds to the pop
right here and gets out.
So now the queue is empty,
and we go back to C one,
for some reason, the schedule is
now scheduling C one, right?
And it gets out of the
way, grabs a lock,
the lock is free to get, right,
and performs a pop on an empty
queue and we get a panic.
So even with our
spurious wake ups,
we've demonstrated during class
that there is still a problem,
and so we really
want to make sure
that instead of an
if we put a while.
So this motivates the while.
This is how we fix it.
And this is now correct code.
Any questions? Yes.
Atomic If the weight was atomic,
if the weight was atomic,
I would say that you would
not need a while loop.
Yeah. Yeah interesting question.
But it's not atomic.
Yeah. Don't confuse
other people.
Weight is not atomic.
Okay. So this basically
gives us correct code.
So how does this fix
the situation if for
any reason whatsoever we get
out of the blocking weight,
be that spurious wake ups
or any other reasons that
we've just discussed,
we're going to double
check again on the
critical condition.
In this case, it's whether
or not the queue is empty,
and then we will
act accordingly.
Go back to sleep if it
is, in fact, empty.
So no harm done and no
signal wasted, okay?
Now, here's another bit that
I find really,
really interesting,
and this is basically
the placement of signal
relative to the push.
And in some ways,
this actually connects with
the journaling discussion
that we had recently,
and that's why I
want to go back to
this example really,
really quickly.
We looked at these three
different possibilities of
signal placement
and which one of
them will work and which
one of them will not work.
Here's another practice
exam question. Yes.
The only one that
doesn't work is
if you push after you signal.
If you push after you signal,
so basically this one
right here, right, right?
Now, what if you signal inside
the lock and then push
also inside the lock?
Yeah, that's an interesting
question, right?
But that's the correct answer
in this particular case.
You basically this works
because you signal
after the push.
This works because you
signal after the push,
and this will not work because
you signal before the push.
And let me explain why.
Here's what we're trying
to accomplish here.
There's a more fundamental kind
of underlying theory here.
What we're trying to enact
is a happens before
relationship between
the producer on
the left hand side
and a consumer on
the right hand side.
In other words, we want to
make sure that a pop sorry,
that a push happens
before the pop.
The producer happens
before the consumer, okay?
How do we accomplish this?
We actually take this
pair of primitives,
the signal and weight,
which are already
by design ordered.
In other words, you're going to
signal before your
weight completes, okay?
They're by design ordered.
And as we basically
pop after the weight,
We pop after the weight,
and as long as we also
push before the signal,
now by transitivity,
we will have
accomplished this happens before
relationship between
the push and the pop.
We will have established a path
in this directed acyclic graph
between the push and the pop,
which means that we will
have established and enacted
a happens before
relationship that we
wanted to begin with, okay?
Does that make sense? And so
we can take this a
little bit further
and think more deeply
around this, right?
So about this.
So what's interesting here
is that if you recall
from I'm going to
remind you that we
had this situation
with logging where we
had ordered journaling mode,
right, where we were
essentially making sure that
our data is written before
the metadata is logged.
And then there's going
to be an entry that's
also logged after the metadata.
And so remember that we didn't
really care in what
order this actually
persists to disk as long as
there is a flush
between the metadata
and the entry that's
logged to the log.
And so basically
this establishes
the partial order
between B and M and
E. Touch that the visibility
of E. So if E is visible,
This implies that the
metadata has persisted,
so metadata is also visible.
And this also implies that
the data has persisted,
which means that the
data is visible.
Okay? So I made a
huge deal about this
because otherwise we would have
had to establish
this total order.
D happens before M,
happens before E,
which is strictly
worse or strictly more
restrictive compared to
this partial order on
the left hand side.
Remember that? So we had
a discussion about
this because here,
there are two possible
orderings that can
actually happen.
D followed by M followed
by E or M followed by D,
followed by E. And so
you have more options.
And whenever you
have more options,
you're providing
more opportunity to
the disk to do its
optimization thing, okay?
And that will give the
disability the disk firmware,
the ability to be
more performance.
If you're imposing,
the more water
you impose in this
particular case,
unnecessarily the
less you restrict
the ability of disk firmware
to extract performance.
What does this have
to do with this?
Same situation here.
If you have a push, okay,
as long as it happened somewhat
around the same time
with signal, let's say,
inside the critical section
in any order, you know,
as long as we have this edge
between the signal and
the weight, right?
It also gives us
this partial order that
also gives us the happens
before relationship between
the push and the pop.
So in other words, push
signal, weight pop works.
Signal push weight pop works,
but they kind of have
to be simultaneous.
They have to be inside
the critical section.
So that's the connection
that I wanted to make with
this ordered login mode
that we discussed
much more recently.
I wanted to come back
to this example and
show that these things
are much more conceptual,
much more theoretical
that you might think.
Okay? All right.
In the interest of
time, I will move on.
So we also talked
about threading,
okay, user and kernel threading.
There are multiple choices here.
And, of course, there
are advantages and
disadvantages associated
with each of these choices.
The first and the easiest one
is what's called
kernel threading.
Whenever you have
one kernel context,
one kernel stack or
thread associated
with every single user
space thread, okay?
So the attributes is that you
get improved concurrency.
I'm not going to ask you
in the back and forth,
but just remember
that you get a lot
of you get true
concurrency this way.
You can run things
in parallel on
a multiprocessor, for instance,
But there's additional
overhead for us to create and
maintain these
kernel threads for
every single user threads, okay?
So these are the advantages and
disadvantages if I were to
ask you for them on the exam.
So we're going to swing to
the opposite side
of the continuum.
We're going to say, Oh,
this is too expensive,
this is too complicated, right?
This is too much overhead.
What else can we do in
our design space exploration
for user and kernel threading?
Well, here's what we can do.
We can just multiplex
a single kernel thread across
multiple user space threads.
We can map many user threads to
one single kernel
context, right?
It's simple and efficient.
However, the problem is
that what's the problem?
What's the single worst
issue with this
particular design?
Yes. Yeah, basically,
you're at the mercy
of the user threads,
basically doing some sort of
a blocking operation that
essentially stalls the kernel
thread for everybody else,
okay, for everybody else.
And there's nothing the
kernel can do about
it because from the
kernel's perspective,
all it sees is just this
one kernel thread
that it can schedule.
It cannot schedule it out and
schedule something
else in in order to
improve the performance of
the CPU. It can't do that.
Okay? And so that's the
single worst problem.
So only one thread can
access the kernel at
a time and no parallelism
on multiprocessors.
But what are the advantages
associated with this?
What's the single best advantage
that you can think of?
Yeah. Sorry? Low
kernel overhead?
Low kernel overhead.
Okay. But it turns out
that it's actually
you mean in terms of maintaining
the number of stacks that
you want to have, right?
Yeah, it turns out that
it's actually not
that big of a deal.
They're quite small, but
it is a correct answer.
Yes. Every time you get
the context will be out.
So minimizing context
switching, right? Okay. Yes.
Plus the TLB.
Yeah, this is associated
with fewer kernel
contacts, exactly.
Basically, you're
losing a lot of
locality, including
TLB locality,
cache locality, and
things like that
whenever you context switching.
So that's another
disadvantage, right?
Let's see if I have
a slide for that.
Yes. So basically, with
kernel space threading,
which is the one to one thing
that we talked about, right?
You have parallelism
or true parallelism.
You have the ability to preempt
something that got
blocked, right?
You can just kick
it out, you know,
go and sleep somewhere else.
I'm going to use the CPU for
another thread that actually
wants to run that's in
a runnable state, okay?
Preemption is possible
in this case.
More information is
available to the kernel.
What that means is that the
kernel has more visibility.
How many threads of
execution are actually
trying to execute and run
at the same time, right?
This gives the kernel
finer granularity control
over the resource consumption,
over the resource
utilization because you've
broken it down into
smaller units of control,
smaller schedulable units that
you are scheduling and
sending to the kernel, okay?
Final granularity control.
Is afforded by the
kernel space threading.
Okay, well, users
threading, however,
has these very salient
advantages that go for it.
One of them is that
if it's done in
the application context
where sort of the order
in which you execute
these threads actually
makes sense is meaningful
in some way, right?
You can perform semantically
aware scheduling.
So this is also referred to
as application awareness.
So let's say you have
a bunch of map reduced
threads, right?
So you would never schedule
a reduced thread before
all the map threads
have completed because
there's a data flow dependency
between them, right?
And so the application
understands that,
but the kernel is not
going to be able to
understand that.
So it could decide to enact
its own scheduling
policy in a way that
doesn't make sense from the
application perspective
because of this semantic gap.
Okay? So the user
space threading
kind of clears that gap.
It has this disadvantage.
It as you pointed out,
it minimizes context
with you overhead.
And it is much more
cash friendly,
including the TOB
flushes, right?
It avoids the TOB flushes
altogether, because
you're in the same.
Why does it avoid
TOB flushes, anyone?
So I'm not Yeah,
it's a simple question.
So that can come up.
Yeah.
Is it just the kernel stack
or is it more than that?
Yes. If you're preempting
a user thread that's
a one relationship
with its kernel thread,
scheduler never
actually rotates on
the same kn single
linkage context switch
which avoids the.
Okay. Yeah. Yeah, exactly.
Basically, this has to do
with the fact that
you're switching
the entire virtual
address space when
you switch between
the processes, right?
You're overwriting the
CR three register with
a different base address
to your page directory,
and that's going to
trigger TOB flash.
So anytime you switch
between processes,
the kernel context requires that
Kernel context switch
requires that,
you're going to encounter
a TOB flash, okay?
Let's hope we can
get to that as well.
So it's also lighterweight
than kernel threading.
You know, I had a
couple of slides on
how you can actually manage
user space threads
in user space,
and there's no fundamental
reason why you wouldn't.
We walked through assembly
that actually makes
that happen, right?
And we kind of line by line,
demonstrated that there's no
privilege instructions that
are involved in us switching
between user space threads.
Within the same
virtual address space.
We're not doing this across
virtual address spaces.
We're doing this
user space threading
within the same
virtual address space.
Otherwise, as someone
pointed out on Tiaza,
this can, of course,
lead to some security violations
and isolation
violations as well.
Okay. So since these
happen to be sort of on
the opposite sides
of the spectrum,
there are some design choices
that are in the middle of
the spectrum, in particular,
this hybrid threading,
when you have many to many
or N to N threading
opportunities, right?
And of course, if I were to ask
you how many user
threads there are,
how many kernel threads there
are relative to each other,
would you say that we'll
have more user threads than
kernel threads or the
other way around? Yeah.
Probably more user threads.
Yeah, it would make sense if
you have more user threads.
Just hypothetically speaking,
how many kernel threads
would it make sense to have?
It's a very open ended question,
but let's see if you get this.
Yeah. So of N. Square root of
N. You're not scaling it
too much. Oh, interesting.
Any other ideas? One per core.
One per core is a good
idea or a hyperthread.
Square root of N.
Yeah, you put my mind in
overdrive here for a second.
Okay. Okay, so there are
some advantages and disadvantages
associated with each.
User space threads
can run in parallel.
So basically, you do gain
some true parallelism
with the hybrid model.
You do reduce the number
of contacts switches,
right, compared to
the one to one model.
So all of this is
relative, right?
You have lightweight
user space threads
because you are doing some
threading in user space,
a And what are the
disadvantages?
Well, you still have
this possibility
where a kernel thread
stalls whenever
you're multiplexing
it across multiple
user threads, okay?
So if one of those handful of
user space threads is doing
some blocking
operation, of course,
you cannot make progress on
that particular
one kernel thread,
but that's okay because you have
other kernel threads that
can still make progress.
So the possibility of
the worst case scenario
where you have
essentially a livelock is
significantly reduced.
And this is still not a
cooperative use of the CPU, okay?
Um, Yeah,
and the reason for
this is because
what does that mean, right?
Just a few words about
what this means.
Cooperative uses of a CPU
is basically when
you're allowing
the kernel to make resource
management decisions
for you, right?
The kernel scheduler is the one
that's scheduling the
next kernel thread.
So you're giving up some
control whenever you go with
the hybrid model
because you rely on
the scheduler to enact
the order of execution.
That's what this means. A
few words on OSN networking.
We talked about
basically seven layers
according to the OSI standard.
Does everyone remember
what they are?
Do you remember the
mnemonic that I showed you?
Yeah, remember? So
it's something like
all people seem to
need data processing.
Okay? So this is
application layer.
This is presentation.
This is session.
This is transport.
This is network.
This is Data Link, and
this is the P, and
this is physical.
In networking classes or
slash networking
kernel literature,
these layers right here
are sort of also
referred to as L one,
L two, L three and L four.
So whenever you hear about
the discussion of routers and
switches and whether
or not they're L three
or L four capable,
that's what this means.
Okay? This is what
they're referring to,
whether or not
they're able to take
the L three or network
layer information
and do some routing based
on this information,
or if they actually
understand the GCP versus
UDP at the higher level
transport protocols and,
you know, make some
decisions, for example,
flow control, based on the
transport layer protocol.
So this is for the
purposes of this class,
I don't care about this, okay?
To me, this is just application.
So you can kind of
forget about all that
for now for CS 30 to ten.
And we primarily in
CS 30 to ten concern
ourselves with these
two layers right here,
the L three and L four,
the network layer and the
transport layer, okay?
So as we go up and
down the stack,
we're sort of growing and
shrinking the amount of
metadata that
surrounds the payload
we actually want to send.
So we start with a piece
of Datum here, right?
And then we're going to put
a Then we're going
to put some UDP header
on top of this, right?
If we're going through
the transport layer,
then the network
layer is going to put
some additional IP
header on top of this,
and then we can have
the Ethernet frame
header on top of this.
All of this kind of
carries information
that pertains to one of
these essentially
five or seven layers
of the protocol stack.
This is a huge success story in
the Cysnet or systems
and networking community
because they really came up with
tasteful abstractions that
stood the test of time.
Okay. So transport layer or L
four is of particular interest
to operating systems.
Why is that? This is where we
talk about TCP versus UDP.
What abstractions
are provided by TCP?
Well, so when I ask
this question, right,
the way to think about
this is as follows.
What do you see
above this layer?
So what do you see above
this layer and what do you
see below this layer, okay?
Um, and that sort of yields the
answer to the question of what
is provided by the layer?
You know, how does it
bridge this interface gap?
And so we're going to spend a
few words talking about this.
So the abstractions
provided by TCP,
it gives a stream interface.
Data comes as a stream instead
of as a sequence
of packets, okay?
The packets is what
the network layer is
going to deal with.
The transport layer gives us
the abstraction of a stream.
It also provides us with
some additional features
like reliability.
So basically, above
the transport layer
implemented with
the TCP protocol,
we can depend on
the reliable and in
order sequencing
of the data that
we send as part of our stream.
So, in other words, we don't
have to worry about
packets being lost.
We don't have to
worry about packets
being reordered,
and point to point.
So point to point is basically
the abstraction that
we get where we're talking
directly to the end device,
and we don't have to
concern ourselves
with what's happening on
the network in between.
So how do we make
packets look like streams
of arbitrary data?
We essentially do
some coalescing.
For example, if the writes
are very small or if
the write is very large,
we can break it down.
And this happens kind of
transparently to
the application.
The application doesn't
have to worry about it.
It serializes its protocol.
It basically pushes it
down the socket, right?
And then it's the protocol,
the TCP protocol
that takes care of
breaking it down into
individual packets.
We also get packets.
It is possible for us
to get packets out
of order. How do we
solve this problem?
Do we remember? So the slide
says sequencing number, but
is this the only thing?
Is it necessary and
sufficient condition for us
to enact or for us to solve
the out of water problem?
It's certainly necessary.
I don't know how you can do
it without sequence numbers,
but is it sufficient?
Yeah. But no,
because you need to know what
the next packet would be.
So you need the next
packet number as well.
You need what? The
next packet number.
You need the next packet number.
Okay. Can you be a
little bit more precise?
If you have. Don't need. Yeah.
No, you don't need
to check them.
At least not for this purpose.
You may need it for
another purpose.
Yeah.
Yeah. Exactly.
Yeah. Thanks for that answer.
Because remember, the sequencing
is only solving a
part of the problem.
So if you have, let's
say, node one here,
so that's your node
one and node two here,
that's your node two, and
it's sequenced its
packets, right?
So it has a transmit buffer.
And this guy has
the receive buffer,
and you sequence them as one,
two, three, four, five,
and let's say you send
one, two, three over,
so because they're sequence,
the receive buffer knows
how to order them,
right, how to queue
them in order.
And let's say you've
only received one,
you're missing two, and
you received three.
So the two has been dropped.
So this is your
packet number two,
and for some reason, it
has been dropped, okay?
We took care of
ordering by using the
sequence numbers, right?
But now all of a sudden
we are missing two.
And so we know
we're missing two,
and the way we're acknowledging,
essentially the absence
of two and the fact that
it needs to be
retransmitted is by going
back to the sender and saying
that number two is
the next sequence number
that I'm expecting.
Okay? And so this information,
so it's called the
acknowledgment mechanism
is sufficient for the
sender to realize,
Oh, so that means that I
need to send two again.
So, in other words,
the receiver is
acknowledging up
until the very last.
So it's acknowledging
the in order prefix
in the receive buffer.
So if we have one,
two, three, four,
five, then something missing,
which is a six, right?
And seven is going to
acknowledge one through five,
and it's going to communicate
back to the sender
that six is missing.
Okay. So both of those
things are needed.
You need sequence numbers
and the acknowledgment
mechanism,
and that's how we handle
packets being dropped
is with retransmission.
Now, there's this
big sort of trade
off space between
TCP and UDP, right?
TCP provides us with
data reliability.
It gives us byte
stream interface,
sort of ensures no errors,
no duplicates, no drops.
UDP is an alternative,
but it only gives us
check sums. Question.
So you're saying the receiver
will send if it's
missing a packet.
I thought it will just
send what it's received,
and then the transmitter
will use the timeout.
And if it doesn't receive
an app for a packet,
then Well, in this
particular case,
those two things are
the same, right?
It can say that I've
received up to five or it
can say that I'm expecting
six next, right?
Those things are
exactly the same.
Okay. But you still
need the timeout.
You do need the timeout
on the sender side.
I didn't get to that.
That's a good point, right?
You also need a timeout
in this particular
case because if
this whole situation of
sending and acknowledging
is taking too long,
you need yet another
mechanism in order to
retransmit the packets that
have not been
acknowledged anyway.
So the receiving sign says
I need packet six next.
The transmitting side will
just immediately packet six.
It will wait until the time out.
And it still haven't received
an app six, then
it will resend it.
Are you saying that it
will resend it right away?
Well, it's acknowledging
things right away.
Yeah, because
there's going to be
an act for everything
that it has received.
We need the
retransmission timeout
in case this act is delayed.
If the act itself is delayed and
it took longer than
a timeout window,
we're going to basically
retransmit it again
from the sender.
All right, let's move forward.
I wanted to basically get
to the TCP versus UDP.
There are some
situations for which you
really need the abstractions and
the guarantees that are
provided by TCP and
some situations where UDP is
a much better alternative.
And the reason for
this is because
it's going to give you
higher performance,
because it has lower
overheads, okay?
So that's important. All right.
File systems, we covered
fairly recently.
So We're already at 2:51.
So very briefly,
file systems is an
abstraction that bridges
the low level interfaces
and provides a much more
sane higher level interface
that gives us atomicity,
crash consistency, and ordering.
So basically, this is
the disk layout that
was presented in class.
XV six does something
slightly different.
It puts a log right
after Super block.
If we ask any questions,
we're going to specify
which ones we're using.
Yeah, by the way, this is
what the XV six looks like.
So you will notice
that the log here
follows the super block
right away, okay?
And so we have these
node structures
to keep track of metadata.
The on disk format for
this consists of the type,
and link, the size,
and 12 direct pointers,
and one indirect pointer.
The reason we need
an indirect pointer
is because we want to
provide support for
larger files because what is
the largest file that you can
support with 12 direct pointer?
Yeah, I'm hearing
the right answer.
Yeah. 12 times Yes,
12 times block size,
which is 12 times half a kilo,
which is 6 kilobytes, right?
And this is what I notte in
XV six looks like, okay?
You have your 12 direct
pointers, you have one indirect,
and the indirect
block simply consists
of 128 direct pointers.
And basically with
this kind of structure
or any kind of structure
that I invent,
okay, you should
be able to give me
the largest possible file
size that it can support.
Does that make sense?
That you basically count
how many data blocks
can you address with
direct pointers and how
many direct pointers
can you possibly have?
Even if you have sort of mixture
of doubly indirect,
trip, indirect,
quadruple indirect pointers,
you should be able to
figure out what is
the largest file size
that you can support.
And this is just the
simplest example here.
What's the largest file size
that this particular
structure can support?
Yeah. 70 kilobytes
or 140 times size.
70 kilobytes.
And the way we get
this is that we have
128 here times half a kilo
is 64 and 12 here times
half a kilo is six,
64 plus six is 70 kilobytes.
Okay. There was some Piazza
discussion about this.
I clarified on Piazza
Please refer to Piazza.
All of the counting
here starts from zero.
The math is correct.
Okay, let's move on.
Directory contents.
Basically, they kind
of look like this.
So directory is
just like a file,
but you can't really directly
write to the directory.
You have sort of API
in order to do this,
like the make Dur directory
and mod and things
like this, okay?
And also create file,
which modifies indirectly the
contents of the directory.
The Durant consists
of the number,
the file name, and
the Durant is free if
your number is zero.
So basically, your
directory data block
looks like this as a
whole bunch of Durens.
I And especially during
our last lecture on files
on atomicity and ordering,
we talked about how there's
this interesting thought process
that goes into trying to
figure out what you
need to persist.
So if you're creating a file,
you have to keep in
mind that not only are
you writing some data
blocks for the file,
you're also modifying
the node for the file,
and you're modifying the dur
associated with the file inside
the directory data block.
So keep that in mind. Yeah.
So the directory
data block is like
to put the first direct
pointer points to, right?
De? No. So the eye node that
corresponds to a file will
only its pointers will point
to just the data block
associated with that file.
Okay. Yes. Okay. So you
have a directory eye
node as well, right?
Yes. You do have a
directory eye node. Yeah.
What do the address pointers
in that ide point to?
Is it the data block.
Yeah. Basically,
they will point to
this they will point to
this directory data blocks.
Yeah. The question is,
we have two different
kinds of i nodes now.
One of them is a file node,
the other one is
a directory node.
The question is about, what is
the directory eye
node pointing to?
It points to these
directory data blocks.
The contents of the
directory data blocks
are different from the
contents of the file.
In the file, you just have data.
For directory data blocks,
you have a bunch of Durens,
and we sort of discuss
what the Durens are.
You have one Durent for
every single file
inside the directory.
Including the subdirectories
of that directory as well.
So you can see how
you can make that
recursive, okay? Good question.
And so we won't have
time to go through this,
but you should be able to
walk through this example.
So let's say you have
an absolute path.
It's called an
absolute file path
that starts with
a forward slash,
and you basically
are trying to open
a file named as follows, right?
And the question could be
asking you what i nodes will
the file system be looking
at in the process of
opening this file.
Okay. And you may be
given kind of a table
that looks like this.
The number zero corresponds to
the forward slash,
the root directory.
I number one corresponds
to directory BS.
I number two may correspond
to the file itself.
I number three
corresponds to bar,
I number four
corresponds to foo,
and so on and so forth, right?
So going through this,
you should be providing me with
an order in which
every single one of
these five nodes is
going to be accessed
in order for us to
open this file, okay?
Okay.
We spent three lectures talking
about ordering ethnicity,
so probably won't be able
to get through this now.
But I do encourage
you to go back to
those lectures because they
have a lot of very
important stuff.
And this is probably
conceptually
the most complicated
topic of this class.
And the reason for this is
to be able to understand
the ethomicity and ordering
from the first principles.
You should also be able
to understand that
we're dealing with three
different layers in the stack.
Okay? And I mentioned this in
the Q&A at the end
of the last lecture.
I want to make sure that
everyone sees this.
So we have three different
layers in our stack.
The bottom most
layer essentially
interacts with the
disk directly, okay?
And the only thing it can do
is perform a block write,
a block read, and a flush.
So this is basically
an interaction with
the disk firmware or
disk driver directly.
On top of this, there's
a separate layer
that is your kernel,
and this is the kernel
user space divide
right here that this
is your file system,
and the file system can do
some logging, for example.
So this is where the
logging is implemented.
It's implemented
inside the kernel
as part of your file system.
You can have different
options here,
for example, no logging, right?
Or you can have ordered,
or you can have metadata,
or you can have
full logging Okay,
et cetera, et cetera.
All of this is
inside file systems,
the file system
component of the kernel.
And then there's a
third part that we
talked about during
the last lecture,
which is what's happening
at the PIX level,
kind of what control
you have when you write
the PoSx application as
far as data persistency
is concerned.
And it has its own separate
interface like a open file,
make directory, an F sync.
And the important one
is the F sync, right?
And so the question we
were asking ourselves is,
how do we bridge this
very, very unreliable,
low level interface that
interacts directly
with the disk using
this very limited interface that
provides us with no
guarantees whatsoever, right?
How do we build an
operating system and
a file system on top of that
that provides us with
crash consistency,
eomicity and ordering
primitives that we require?
So it's really important
to understand that we
were talking about
these three different
layers of the stack.
The last lecture was all about
the higher level,
the highest level,
the third level of the stack,
which doesn't make
any assumptions
about what's
happening underneath.
Because underneath,
you could have
a file system that performs
no logging at all,
or this is the same thing
as write back, by the way.
Or it could be doing ordered or
metadata or full logging.
It doesn't matter.
You can still ensure
consistency by using
the Post six interface.
It's extremely expensive,
but you can do it.
You can make it
correct. Okay? We also
discussed about
shadowing and logging.
Do we want to go through
shadowing again?
No. I see no.
Okay. Cool.
There was an important
bit right here that you
do need this flush to
order operation three
with operation four.
And as a result of this,
you sort of arrive at something
that has a lot of overhead.
So the cost of shadowing
are sort of extreme.
You need at least twice the
amount of space, right?
And you also need
to require right to
a shadow bit on every
version update.
So there are at least two discs,
a copy and update and a shadow.
And as we also
discussed on Tiaza,
you know, I encourage you to
refer to that discussion.
Shadow must be a separate bit,
which means that you cannot
coalesce them into
the same block.
Because otherwise, those
updates would not be atomic.
You want to make sure
that shadow bit updates
are atomic by themselves.
And one way to ensure
correctness with
the shadow bit
update is to write
this to a disk block by itself.
This ensures that
the contents of
the disk block can be
found in one of two
possible states.
Either it's a whole bunch of
zeros or it's anything
other than that.
And the interpretation
of that gives
us this Boolean semantics
associated with
the shadow bit that allows us to
reason about it in an
atomic fashion. Okay? Yes.
Sorry? The active bit.
Sure. Yeah. So again,
this is a semantic
interpretation.
Zero could mean
looking left, right?
Anything other than
zero could mean
looking right where basically,
when we flip it, we
flip it to point into
the opposite direction.
Yeah. But the flush
3-4 and five is not
necessary for any or it would
have to be the same way?
Well, it's not necessary
if you're writing to
different blocks,
but you don't know what
you're writing to.
And so that's why you need
to inject a flush in there.
There's a possibility that
you could be writing to
exactly the same block and
to make sure that the
subsequent op four,
which is a copy, reads
the file from the most
up to date state,
you need to put a flush in there
in order to order
those two operations.
They're writing to
different blocks,
couldn't that lead to out
of order entries though,
so that if you were
writing to the metadata
and the data and the data
got the shot of it flipped,
within the data did
an imminent crash,
then you would have.
I'm sort of half
hearing you right now.
So I think you might be
the person who asked this
question on Piazza, right?
So why don't you stop by
after class and we'll
talk about this?
Because let's make sure
we resolve that
confusion offline.
I Okay, so basically
logging works like this.
You put logs into the entry,
entries into the log,
you put commit, and then
another entry, another commit.
And for any entry
that's uncommitted,
you basically don't
consider it during
a log merge or recovery.
The entry consists of a type
and location and payload,
basically what you're
attempting to write.
I And we really
care about this prefix
property of the log, okay?
The prefix property of
the log makes sure that
every entry is considered
valid up until this
termination condition.
Determination condition is when
you've reached an entry
that's not valid.
Everything after that is
not going to be valid,
even if it does have a commit.
Okay. And so then the way we
access data is we
check the log first.
And we went through a couple
of examples during class.
So in this particular case,
if I read block six,
where are we going
to read it from?
So our entry is right here.
It corresponds to right here.
It corresponds to block six,
and we have a data
block associated
with block six in the data
block section of the disk.
Where where would we be
reading the data from?
Yeah. You read from
the actual dislocation because
the entry hasn't been committed.
Right, exactly. In
this particular case,
the entry hasn't been committed,
so we would actually go
to the data block, okay?
We made a huge deal about
how introducing check sums
actually gives us the same
eomicity property we love.
But in addition to this,
it also allows us to
checksum the entry we're
writing to the log, okay?
And so this makes
it possible for us
to write them all at
the same time without
any flushes in between,
as long as they're written
to the correct location,
to the correct seek on the disk,
to the correct log block.
So this really unlocks a lot
of performance as a result.
Okay, so there are lots of
advantages and disadvantages.
Sequential access is
one of the advantages
because we know that sequential
access is very efficient.
We also get ordering from
logging just by design.
The log entries are
committed in order.
They're recovered in order.
They're sort of read in
order whenever you're trying
to figure out where
to read from.
So this whole left to right
ordering that's provided by
the log is actually
highly beneficial.
It's sort of a very,
very clever and simple
design that a lot of us are
taking for granted
at this point.
It does come with its
own set of costs, right?
We are doubling the rights
because at some point,
we're going to write to the log,
and then the log will
need to be written to
the actual data block
section of the disk.
So you are paying for
two rights for any
given right, right?
And so there's a certain set
of corollaries
associated with that.
First is, we probably
don't want to have
full logging because especially
with large file updates.
Uh, because full logging
will essentially
log the data rights as well as
the data rights all
within the same log.
We'll run out of the
logs fairly quickly,
and it also is much
significantly more costly than
ordered logging that
we talked about.
So what do modern
file systems do?
Well, they provide options.
You can turn it off.
It's usually a better idea.
Or you can do metadata
only, but, you know,
it's problematic because, um,
some bad things can
happen to data.
And what's worse is
that you can still
arrive at the situation where
you've written the
metadata, but not the data.
So you could be pointing
at somebody else's data,
which is a security violation.
So that's problematic, right?
Ordered logging kind
of addresses this.
We still don't log the data,
but we are writing data to disk
before we are writing
metadata to the log,
and it's usually
considered pretty safe.
Full logging, we
already discussed,
is sort of really expensive
because you're logging
everything and
you get head of line blocking
for your small
updates as a result.
Huge issue, especially
when you're trying to F
sync something to the
disk, as we discussed.
Okay, so I'm going to stop here
because I also want to
leave some time for
you to come up and ask me
questions after class.
Thank you so much and
good luck tomorrow.
It's going to be a fun exam.
You