Everyone. Good afternoon.
Good afternoon.
Hey, good to see you too.
Okay, so today we're
going to start, I guess,
the last important and large
ish module in this class,
which is file systems.
And it's going to take
us four lectures total.
Two of those lectures we're
going to talk about
file systems,
and two additional lectures
we'll be talking about
ordering atomicity and
concurrency in file systems,
which is a really,
really exciting
topic that remains to be
actually a topic of
active area of research.
And as a matter of fact, it
is so important In fact,
the file systems as a whole
is so important band.
For example, at Carnegie Mellon,
which is where I
got my PhD from,
there's a dedicated class
just talking about file systems.
And here we are going
to discuss this in
a couple of lectures in
a 3,000 level class.
So there's definitely a
lot to talk about, right?
So let's go ahead
and get started.
I we all know lab three is
due this Friday due today.
And Friday is tomorrow.
Great news item, right?
This is probably the best lab.
If you do have any late
days remaining, I mean,
just probabilistically thinking,
I would encourage you to
actually spend those late days
on lab three, if you
need to, of course.
Like, if you feel like, oh, my
God, I'm running out of time,
don't count on it because
if you count on it,
you will spend them, right?
Do try to meet the deadline.
But at the same time, if
you think about lab three,
we're spending them on lab
three versus spending
them on lab four.
Lab three is 20% of
the final grade,
Lab four is 10% of
the final grade.
So it just makes sense
to sort of spend them on lab
three instead of lab four.
And lab four is
relatively speaking,
going to be a breeze
compared to Lab three.
I don't want to set the
expectations too low.
All of this is
relatively speaking,
all of this is probabilistic
and everyone is different.
But that is just sort of
the general guideline
that I wanted to share with
you in case this is useful.
Speaking of Lab four,
which is going to be
all about file systems,
it's going to be released
tomorrow, Friday,
March 28, The time does fly.
You know, it really feels weird
that we are almost at the
end of the semester, right?
You'll be done
before you know it.
And as a matter of
fact, exam two,
it sort of really was a
surprise for me personally.
I mean, it's a
statement of fact,
so it shouldn't be a surprise.
So we knew that from the
start of the semester,
but it's a surprise how
fast the time flies.
We will be holding an
exam two on Wednesday,
April 16, which is only
20 days from today.
Only 20 days from today.
And in this period of time,
you have to get your lab three,
and you have to get your lab
four done and submit it.
And then since the
lab four is going to
be due the Friday
before that Wednesday,
you will have
approximately five days
of doing nothing but focusing on
the preparation for the
comprehensive final exam
for CS 30 to ten,
which has become your
most favorite class ever.
Yay.
The new material that will be
added to your plate
for preparation
to exam two is going to be
file systems, ordering
and atomicity.
This is pretty
complex stuff, okay?
And it's very
conceptually novel.
It's going to be
to a lot of you.
In addition to this, we'll have
some discussion over
distributed systems.
I'll try to squeeze in as
much as I can in 15 minutes.
Distributed systems is a
whole area of research.
I actually happened
to take a theory of
distributed systems
class that was
zero coding, 100% math.
And I spent this
whole semester doing
that when I was doing
my masters, actually.
And so each of those areas,
they are meant to really
give you a flavor for
how much depth there is in every
single one of these
cis ark threads, okay?
So cis ark thread is a
thread in its own right,
obviously, from
your perspective,
but it's actually
sub threaded into
the specializations and
area specializations,
each of which warrants
its own area of study.
So that's pretty cool. Yeah, and
we're going to have the
Exam two prep lecture
on Tuesday 415,
which is one day
before the exam two.
Exam two will be joint.
It will take place wherever
you are doing your
supervised labs right now.
So it will be different from
exam one in that respect,
and you will have more
than 50 minutes to do it.
So I cannot share with
you the exact time limit that
we're going to decide upon.
I would like to reserve
that until later when we
actually have made progress
on putting together that exam,
but I can guarantee you that
it will be more than 1 hour.
You will be given more than
1 hour to complete it for sure.
As an estimate, a rule of thumb,
think about it as
a two hour exam.
Okay, so let's start
talking about file systems.
You know, it seems like such
an obvious topic because
you're pretty much
using a file system
every single time you touch
your computer, right?
And so you must have some
preconceived notions
about what a file system
really is, right?
So let's talk about it.
What is a file system?
And what is a file system
when we mention that name?
You know, can anyone
venture a guess?
What does it mean
to you? How would
you define a file system?
What does it do? Why do we
need it? Do we need it?
Yes. Storing retrieving memory
from the disk to external
memory on your system.
Like the packet can do that.
So let's not use the word memory
because that sort of
by association kind of
leads us to think about
virtual memory and
physical memory and
the DRM slots and things
like that, right?
So maybe instead of memory,
you meant something else, right?
What do you want to
store and retrieve?
Yes. Or state, over a long
period of time. Okay.
Okay, so store some state
that you want to be
able to come back to,
right, over a long
period of time.
So it's something right there,
if you actually start thinking
about it from the perspective
of what are the properties
associated with
what he just said,
We want persistency, right?
We want crash recovery, right?
We want some properties.
We want isolation,
we want protection.
We want some properties
that will guarantee
durability of the data that we
have stored on that
medium, right?
And every single word
actually by implication,
carries more and more
things that we're going to
sort of try to uncover
in this class, right?
And here's a question for you,
that's sort of a follow up
to this thread of thought.
Does a file system have
to relate to disk?
Because you mentioned
storing, right?
Storing for a long
period of time.
There's some state, let's
call it data, okay?
Just as a very general
term, let's call it data.
We want to store some data
over a long period of time.
We want to have the
ability to retrieve it.
ability to access it.
Do you have to have
a disk in order for
us to have a meaningful
conversation about file systems?
Oh, nice. I see some
correct answers
that have not been
verbalized yet.
Yes. But not necessarily.
You can have virtual outs,
which are not really
tied to a disk.
Okay. What's a virtual file?
A resource for an
external computer or
a cloud system, which
you can retrieve.
I mean, you're given the
illusion that it's native to
your machines file system,
but it's really not.
Yeah, so file seems to be
an abstraction, right?
It's actually not
a physical thing.
It actually turns out that it's
an abstraction that may or may
not necessarily have
some persistent storage
behind it, right?
So that's pretty cool.
And then in that case,
where would you store,
actually the metadata
associated with that file?
So if it's not backed
by secondary storage,
what could it possibly
be backed by?
Because at the end of the day,
I think we agreed
on one thing so far
that we want file
system to manage data.
So where would you
store that data
if you don't have
secondary storage?
No idea? Oh, yes, sorry.
I was myopally focused
in the back. Yeah.
Have any of you heard
about Tempo FS?
Have you tried
building a tempo Fs
on the Linux system, right?
So empoFs is basically
a temporary file system
that can actually be
stored in memory.
A RAM disk is a file system
that can be stored in memory.
So you don't actually have
to have disk in order to
talk about or have a file
system in the first place.
Of course, it changes the
properties that are given to
you by this file system
because if you press
the power button,
what's going to
happen to a RM disk?
It'll basically become
ephemeral, right?
It has ephemeral properties,
not persistent properties.
So yeah, basically, does
a file system need any
secondary storage?
I think we've established that
the answer to that is no, right?
A very good example of that,
as we've established is RMFS.
There are some other examples
that basically include booting,
for example, an
operating system from an
A file system that was
mounted over the network.
So basically, you have this
notion of thin clients.
It used to be pretty
popular, I don't know,
maybe a couple of
two decades ago,
especially in the EDU,
in the academic environment,
where you had a single sort
of supersrver I
think it was called,
and then it had a bunch
of thin clients that
didn't even have any
local secondary storage,
but they were able to
boot file systems,
to boot operating
system over the network
by sort of mounting
over the network from
the super server.
Okay. So as we talk
about file systems,
I know it sort of
becomes evident that
we're really talking
about some way
to organize data, right?
And as I was sort of trying
to conceptualize this,
it's really important
to conceptualize
very concrete things that you
may possibly be
taking for granted.
So here's a relevant
analogy that I would like
to share with you very briefly.
So there was a first attempt
at organizing Internet data.
Do you remember what was the
first attempt at organizing
Internet data and what it
looked like? It wasn't Google.
There was something
before Google.
There was life before Google.
So that first attempt
actually looked just like
cataloguing the websites into
a specific hierarchical
structure.
So Yahoo was a very
good example of that.
I think Alta Vista was
another good example.
You may not have even heard
of these names now, right?
Because it's such an outdated
way of organizing data,
but it was the first approach to
organize Internet data, right?
And it was it sort of came
to be because that's how
we used to organize data,
let's say in the
library, because
the library before Internet,
used to be the to go to
place to go for knowledge,
to go for data, right?
And the way to organize this
was the library catalog system.
Okay? So I'm giving
you a bit of like
a historical walkthrough of
data organization
and data management,
but it's important to understand
that basically things
have evolved over time,
and there are reasons why
they have evolved over time.
When they tried to organize
Internet data using
the cataloging system,
they made a fundamental
assumption,
and that fundamental
assumption was
that it held true
for the libraries,
which actually held
physical books,
physical objects that
you needed to organize.
And because they were
physical, they were finite.
You couldn't scale them in
an exponential fashion.
And therefore, the
cataloging system
was actually
perfectly reasonable.
But as soon as you try to
organize data that
is cyber data,
scalability properties of
cyber data are actually
significantly
different compared to
the scalability properties
of physical data,
and therefore, the
same mechanisms of
data organization
will no longer apply.
So you needed something else,
you needed some sort of
semantic search, right?
You need a page rank.
You needed something, some
mechanism that could scale with
data with exactly the
same superlinear
exponential fashion.
And cataloging the
hierarchy that they
tried to impose in
the 1998, 1999,
right before the y2k,
it simply did not
scale as well as
the underlying data that
they tried to organize.
Same thing happened
with the file system.
So it's a bit of a diversion,
but I think it's important.
So there's a lot of thought that
people put in into
managing the user data,
including in the operating
system file systems
in the OS file systems.
Now, what else can file
system do for us, right?
What if we have multiple users
using the data on
the disk, right?
Is there something
that we want to
do about that as an
operating system?
Should we just allow them
to read and write to
arbitrary locations
in the file system?
The answer to that is no, right?
Because bad things would happen.
So we need to provide
mechanisms and
policies of multiplexing
those storage resources.
We need to provide them
with a notion of isolation.
Again, the same concept,
the same abstraction that we've
become dependent on
in the context of
operating systems
is that when I am
using the set of resources
that are given to me,
I would like to
believe that I'm the
only one interacting
with the system.
You know, there should be no
interference if there are
other users in the
system at the same time.
There should be no
interference when
I'm trying to access
those resources,
when I'm trying to when
I'm trying to use
those resources.
The resource in question
is the thing that
changes across multiple
modules in this class.
Right? We've covered memory.
We talked about isolation and
how to achieve isolation, right.
What else did we cover
where isolation was
really important?
All right? It will
come back to you.
File systems is
another good example
where isolation is
really important.
And as an OS,
we want to make OS developer,
we want to make sure we provide
that isolation guarantee
to the users using
storage resources, right?
We want to provide
protection mechanisms.
So we talked about
protection mechanisms
again across different
modules in the system.
So I'm trying to kind of
thread things together.
They are not
independent entities.
They are high level
conceptual things
and abstractions that actually
permeate the different
verticals of the kernel,
different verticals of
the operating system.
And, of course, data
management as well.
And so overall, let's
go ahead and sort of
replace every single instance
of the word storage.
Since we've established
that secondary
storage is necessary,
we can go ahead and
replace that with
the word data because
it's all about data.
It's all about that content.
It's all about state,
to your point, right?
That we want to be able to
persist, manage, access,
isolate, protect, and retrieve.
Any other verbs? Come on,
wake up, people. All right.
So I guess to summarize,
the operating system
services that are
provided by file
systems are isolation.
It's a very important one.
We heard this name so many
times in this class, right?
And please do remember or
go back to the
question that I asked,
Where does isolation show up
and what are the mechanisms
that we use in order
to enact isolation
across the different verticals
of the kernel, right?
I could ask you about
the specific examples
where isolation is important.
Protection, multiplexing,
and multiplexing is so
yeah, what about
protection, right?
Protection is a mechanism
by which access to
data is protected at
some granularity, right?
So granularity here
is, for example,
files on the resource side
and on the user side,
it's the users that
are trying to consume
the data from the file.
Multiplexing. In this case,
it's worth defining
or characterizing
that there are two fundamental
types of multiplexing.
There's space multiplexing,
which means that
the ability to multiplex
access to the same file,
for instance, right,
and time multiplexing,
which means ordering access to
a particular resource
across time.
So there's a spatial dimension.
For example, if the file
is a multi gigabyte file,
you might be able to
provide direct access to
this file to two
simultaneous users
at precisely the
same time, right?
And that could be allowed,
for instance, depending on
the application properties.
Or you are thinking about
time multiplexing where you
really do want to sort of take
a lock on the file, right,
update the contents
of the file or
of the Nde and
then unlock that before
somebody else is allowed
to get into that
critical section.
So that would be
time multiplexing.
So those are the two
different ways of
sort of multiplexing
access to the file.
And by the way, they are
analogous for this
in networking,
and this distinction
is fundamental.
Okay. Another thing
that sort of rarely
comes up in the discussion
of file systems,
which is naming, right?
We talked about
these four things
actually in the
context of networking,
and naming was one
of them, right?
Because the network protocol
stack actually gives us
the ability to name things at
the highest level of
abstraction, right?
And that's a very intuitive,
well defined interface,
user friendly interface that we
would like to get on top of
something that just sends
electrical signals
on the wire, right?
So naming is in the file
systems is critical, right?
Of course, one
example of naming is
files, but more generally,
it refers to high level
abstractions that create
a user friendly interface
in order to access data.
So in other questions,
in other words,
the way to think about it
is what is my interface
to data that resides
on this medium, right?
Am I going to access it at
the granularity of blocks?
Does anybody want
to access your data
at the granularity of blocks?
Like, say, Hey, I need
this block number 537 and
this block number 1032
and somehow manage
the state in the user space
associated with which
blocks correspond to which
application specific data
structures, for instance.
Does anybody want to do that?
No, right? You really want
an operating system
to do that for you.
And so, by the way,
the answer to my earlier
question about isolation,
networking was another one
that really had that property.
And networking was
another module
in this class where we really
explored all of
these four different
operating system services,
and naming was one of them.
Okay, so what is a file system?
Wikipedia definition,
at some point, right?
It's a multi version system,
so who knows what it says
right now, but at some point,
it said that a file system
controls how data is stored
or retrieved, right?
So what we've established
is that file system
in general is an abstraction
to manage data, right?
And just like with everything
else else in this class,
it's sort of not set in stone.
It's not necessarily fixed.
We can actually play around
with the abstraction.
We can play around with
the interfaces that it
exposes to the user,
exposes to the application
depending on the underlying
set of assumptions,
which may be explicit and
may sometimes be implicit,
just like that
example that I told
you about Internet
data management.
You know, one of the
assumptions they
made is held true
for the libraries,
did not hold true
for cyber data.
We've established
that file systems
do not have to be tied
to persistent data.
We have FS controls to access
the data that is also
exposed by file systems.
It exposes the ability to name
and organize data, right?
It exposes the
ability to share data
between multiple users
and multiple processes.
And data, in fact,
can be completely read only.
It doesn't have to be mutable.
Let's see.
And it exposes the properties
that we've come to depend
on for operating systems,
including naming
protection, and isolation.
As a matter of fact, the
file system interface,
you know, it was sort
of invented probably,
I don't know, four, maybe
five decades ago in
the context of Unix,
and it sort of really
stood the test of time.
It sort of really became
a useful mechanism
for being appropriated
in other contexts,
like, for example,
accessing devices, right?
So, you know, how many of
you have interacted with
serial bus drivers in
Linux, for instance? Right.
How many of you have
interacted with the camera?
And where do you find those
things being mounted?
They're mounted actually
in the file system
on slash dev, at least in Linux.
And so what that means
is that there are
some specific peripheral
devices that you
can actually interact
with using the file IO,
and this has nothing to do
with data management and
nothing to do with
data durability
or anything of that nature.
You're sort of accessing them
in a reader only fashion.
And it just so happens that
the file system interface
and the file system abstractions
have been so tastefully and so
elegantly designed
that it became Um,
it transcended the
use cases that were
originally meant to be covered
by file systems, right?
So, as a matter of fact,
the interface that is broadly
generalizes to a variety
of data IO scenarios.
So how many of you have
interacted with ProcfS?
Yeah.
So ProcfS is a very
interesting example
of using file systems, right,
for something that has
nothing to do with
files and has nothing to do
with kind of content in your
common and typical sense.
Um, It gives you actually,
I think I might have a
separate slide on all
of the things that it
can enable you to do.
But generally
speaking, it gives you
sort of this file
IO interface to
a lot of the control plane data
that is exposed by the
Linux kernel itself.
So you can actually
read a lot of
useful state in a read only
fashion, and in some cases,
you can also mutate some of
the configuration
options through
ProkofS using file o, right?
Okay.
So the bottom line is that
file systems is an abstraction
to manage data in general.
It is used to export or make
accessible the data
to user space, right?
It does that in a very narrow
was interface fashion, right?
You can recall this
is Sparta analogy,
where in the narrow was fashion
actually gives you
a lot of strength.
And the file system is
adopted for managing the
Linux control plane.
We talked about Proc AFS.
So, as a matter of fact,
when I was a PhD student,
one of the pet projects we
did was to sort of hack
the Linux port to
Tyler Til Pro 64,
which was supposed to work on
a mesh network
ownership interconnect
with an eight by eight
grid, of course, right?
And we wanted to sort of
make scheduling decisions.
We were trying to
hack on a scheduler
that guest for Linux port.
And what we wanted to do is we
wanted to change
or rather change
the placement of an
application thread
closer to the memory controller,
which is being used the most.
And there were four memory
controllers on the peripheral.
Um, one in each of the
four corners, right?
And so in order for us to
make these control decisions,
we needed to collect the data.
Basically, where are all
the memory accesses going?
Which of the four
memory controllers.
So we would maintain a vector,
a four element vector to
maintain that count, right?
And we decided to expose that
through ProkofS as well.
So you can actually overload
Proofs for a bunch of
these interesting things.
And then the user
space application
would do its own
scheduling decisions of
the threads based on
this four element vector
that it would extract
from ProkofS.
So that's one
concrete way of using
file systems for something
that is not a file.
Okay, so we talked
about file systems.
We tried to motivate
file systems,
why they are important,
why they are useful,
what they cover, sort of,
what is the scope
and the generality
of file systems in general,
the fact that they are very
elegant and very important.
We'll also go and
talk a bit about API,
so the design choices that were
made to interact with
the file system,
the disk layout, buffer cache,
and if we get to it XV six code.
So, okay. I'm not sure
why this slide is here.
Oh, yeah, there are
some new things here.
So the abstractions that disk
based file systems provide,
now we're talking about disk
based file systems a little bit
more specifically than
just file systems
in general, right?
So what do they provide?
They provide naming,
They provide byte
level interfaces.
So remember that
we really want to
bridge the gap between hard to
use resources at the
very bottom, right?
And the user and application
level expectations
of convenience and
simplicity and ease of use.
Okay? So at the very bottom,
you have these hard to use
things like, for example,
blocks and sectors on
a secondary storage,
and at the very top,
you have applications that
really don't want to concern
themselves about the location
of those blocks and sectors.
They just want to read
a particular piece
of data from a
secondary storage.
They want to be able to
persist a piece of data to
secondary storage without really
getting into the details
of how that's done.
So the purpose of the operating
system FS stack, right,
is to actually hide
the complexity
of everything that goes
into making that happen,
of everything that bridges
this semantic gap that enables
the simplicity and ease of
use from the application
perspective.
And what do they want? They
want byte level interfaces,
right? What do they want?
They want isolation,
protection and
mechanisms to make sure that
the state is not corrupt,
to make sure that there's no
basically leakage of state,
and there's no unauthorized
access to state, right?
Other things that are
being enabled here by
the disk based file
system is locking.
So we basically have
the ability to lock,
take a lock on a file while
we're updating the
contents of the file,
and then release
that lock when we're
done updating or
reading from the file.
Right? And another thing
here is multiplexing.
We touched upon
this a few times.
In this particular
case, you can think of
a resource as a single
disk with many files,
and multiplexing sort of
takes care of coordinating
the simultaneous access from
users and applications to
the multiple locations
on this scarce resource,
which is, in this
particular case, a disk.
Any questions so far?
In some cases, we want to be
able to share data, right?
So let's say we created a file,
Alice created a file,
and she wants to share
it with Bob, right?
We want to rely on the operating
system file system, FS,
to actually give us the
capability, just very,
very abstractly, give
us the capability
to sort of share content
between the different users.
So from one perspective,
we do want to ensure isolation,
but we also don't want
to completely prevent
the sharing from happening
in the cases where
it does make sense.
Okay.
Yeah, I sort of I did a lot
of the thinking for you.
Normally, I would ask as
a question, you know,
which you would find
more intuitive,
reading the sectors or reading
blocks or reading bytes.
And we've already covered that
the byte level
interface is what we
really want because
it allows us to read,
seek, and write a stream of
bytes that byte granularity.
So you can see how
these abstractions
actually help us create
useful interfaces
for the consumers
of some systems functionality.
The file systems enable
protection and isolation.
It's very important
because it's required for
systems that are a
priori multi tenant,
and it's a primary operating
system function
that we discussed.
We enable synchronizing
potentially conflicting
accesses to the same file.
And in terms of
multiplexing here,
as I mentioned, we
have one disk and
many distinct files on
this shared device.
And here, it's, again,
important to talk
about granularity.
And also, as we
provide isolation,
we want to make sure that we
enable data sharing to happen.
And one example of using file
systems is actually pipes,
right, for interprocess
communication.
So I believe you've used
pipes in the context
of Lab three,
and it's also a very
important kind of
property or interface
that the file system
enables that can be
used for something
other than storing
things on disk.
In this particular
case, it allows
processes to share
data between them.
And sockets is another
kind of interface.
Where you provide the same
file access interface
as in cases.
The byte level
interface is a facade.
It's a translation of
low level denative to
process native interfaces.
It helps us hide complexity.
It also hides various things
that we really don't
want to think about,
which is heterogeneity of
storage devices and device
drivers for that matter.
We also want to
depend on this for
device availability and
failure in general.
It gives us the option
of hiding the topology.
For example, you don't
necessarily have to
worry about whether or not
something is local or remote.
And as a matter of
fact, some file systems
can be intermittently
unavailable, right?
So network mounted file
systems, for instance,
there's a possibility that
depending on the
granularity of time,
you know, there's
a possibility that
the remote file system
is not available, right?
And so if you do nothing,
if you don't have any
sort of painure recovery
or unavailability handling
mechanisms in your OSFS,
then your access to
files is going to be
extremely brittle.
It will fail all the time. So it
file systems also have
some mechanisms for
us to deal with this.
In other words, when
dealing with file systems,
we really want to get the
look and feel of memory.
You know, just like
you're reading and
writing to and from
memory, right,
you want to be able
to interact with
the content in the file system
in the same kind
of easy fashion.
Okay.
We discussed this, right?
This is just a reminder slide.
And the reason why this
works is because, you know,
FSIO interface sort of
became a time tested
intuitive interface for a
general set of use cases.
Okay. Here's another set
of things that you
can sort of extract
using the file system interface.
There's information
about pumsomes,
information about PCI devices,
which can be useful, right?
You can actually
control things like,
for example, huge page allocation
in an operating system.
You can get information
about open file descriptors.
For instance, LSOF is
a command line
interface command line,
So, it's a command that
you can run that will
give you access to
the information about
open file descriptors
for a specified process.
So the takeaway is
that file system
is a lot more than just
persistent storage.
Okay. And so let's take
a look at this, right?
Let's take a look at
the storage trends,
which are quite interesting.
So on this graph,
horizontally, you have cost.
So going left to right,
you have increase in the
dollars per gigabyte,
and going top to bottom, you
have increase in
throughput, right?
You have increase in throughput.
And so tape is known
to be extremely cheap,
in terms of dollars
per gigabyte.
And this is why we
still use tape,
even though we have
much better technology.
There are reasons for every
single one of these points.
And we already talked
about why, for example,
some other point in this trade
off space cannot be said
to be better or worse
than this point in this
trade off space, right?
And we're going to get
to that. We're going to
conceptualize this on
the subsequent slide.
But what I want to draw
your attention to on
this slide is that you have
tape and hard disk drives here,
right, which are
relatively low cost,
but also low throughput.
And then there's a jump, right?
And you have DRAM,
which is very expensive,
but, of course, gives you
much higher throughput
in megabytes per second.
And then you have
CPU SRAM cache,
which is even more expensive,
and it does provide you with
much higher throughput.
So where do you want to be
in this trade off space?
Yes. If you draw a linear
line across the points,
do you want to be on
the upper side of
that line where the
throughput is high,
but the cost is relatively low.
Right. E you get
into the habit of thinking
about everything in systems
as a trade off
because if I were to
ask you on the exam,
which is better?
It's a trick question,
so I probably won't ask, right?
But which is better? DirMo tape?
Yes.
It depends, right?
You cannot say
that one is strictly
better than the other.
Yes. Like, where
does SSD, fall this?
There. So because of
this increasing gap,
that's a great question,
and thank you for that.
Because of this is
how you actually come
up with new stuff
in the industry.
You start looking at trends
and the way that they sort
of map in a particular trade off
space of interest
to your customers.
What do customers care about?
They care about throughput
as a success metric,
they care about, you know,
out of pocket cost, right?
And so you start
seeing these kind of
increasing separation
between some
of the points that you provide,
let's say, as a
manufacturer, right?
And if there's an increasing
gap, this is an opportunity.
And rest assured that
your competitors will also
be thinking about
that opportunity.
And so you start thinking
about how do you develop
a product that will
actually fit into that gap.
And so somebody did that, right?
And they came up
with NVMs, right?
And we're going to
get to that in a bit.
So here's a conceptualization
of the trade off spaces,
and this is just a reminder
that we did talk about
it in the past in the context
of security, for
instance, right?
Because different kind of
security design choices,
they also span this trade
off space where one of
the axes is how usable or
easy to use the thing is,
and the other, the Y axis
here is how much
safety it provides.
And we want maximum usability
and maximum safety,
so we actually want to be in
the top right hand
corner, right?
In this particular case,
the trade off space
is different.
On the x axis, you have cost,
on the Y axis you
have throughput,
and I already asked you
this question, right?
Where do you want to be?
So yeah, where do
you want to be?
It's a very simple
question. Yeah.
Like the feasible frontier line
that represents the
best you can get.
Now, let's say I
give you an option
of just drawing one point.
Where do you want
to draw that point?
Yeah. Top left, right? This
is where you want to be.
Everyone agrees with me?
Yeah, maximum throughput,
minimum cost.
And I'll take that
a step further,
at the expense of, you know,
spending some lecture
time on this.
The best research in
systems collapses this
trade off spaces.
Like, if you can come up with
a mechanism that basically gives
you maximum Y axis
with zero x axis,
you have collapsed the
entire trade off space.
You wipe out all of
your competition.
You have solved the problem,
you have closed the chapter.
You can publish this. Okay?
So this is how it's done.
And this is a way to sort of
conceptualize how
research is done in
systems from the perspective of
looking at various
kind of options and
various state of the art
solutions to a problem
from the perspective of
rate of space they induce.
And this is, of course,
bad design, right?
And the reality is usually
somewhere in the middle.
And generally speaking,
you will come up
with a whole bunch of points
in this trade off space,
and what you care about is
a parato frontier, right?
A pata frontier is such
that you get maximum Y,
even an X constraint.
So maximum throughput
given some cost budget.
And conversely, you can try
to minimize cost given some
throughput constraints.
So if a customer comes
to you and says,
I need my application to
be whatever at such
and such throughput.
This is my threshold.
You want to figure
out the point in
the straight off
space that gives
you the minimum cost
solution to that.
So the combination of
those two constraints
will actually give
you a pareto frontier
that spans the
straight off space.
And this is what
this looks like.
Okay? Um, okay.
So somebody asked about SSDs.
Do SSDs solve the
problem, right?
So, here are some useful
benchmarks that someone ran
at some point in time
that was comparing
SSDs to basically
RM disk, right?
And in some cases, it depends.
In some cases, the
applications are such
that it can easily
match the performance,
so it's very close in
matching the performance.
But in most of the cases,
like, for example,
for a sequential 256 kilobyte
write or even random
256 kilobyte write,
it doesn't match the performance
of a RM disk, right?
So but there are some
specific scenarios,
like, for example, a
random four K write.
So it's much better at writing
finer granularity data where
there's no benefit from
a sequential and
temporal locality.
So high speed storage in
NVM is approaching RAM,
but it is very expensive, right?
So high performance
data recorders
can approach RAM speeds.
For example, you know,
there are options out
there that will give you
2.5 gigabytes/second.
They are, however, far
more expensive than DRAM.
And so you end up
with something that
approaches DRAM in throughput,
right, but it's far
more expensive in DRAM.
And so, okay, you
go back to here,
and you ask yourself, do I
really want that
solution, right?
Because this is your DRAM,
which gives you high cost
and high throughput,
and you get something that
is equal throughput and
even higher cost from
something right here,
same throughput and
even higher cost.
So it's not strictly better,
it's not strictly worse.
It just depends on
what the application
cares about, right?
So for example, in applications
where reliable persistent
storage is required,
such as real time sensors or
radar technology or imagery,
data recording, right?
This is where you would see
non volatile storage
actually being useful.
So what makes file
system interesting,
the challenges we're going to be
collectively thinking
about is crash recovery,
which is a very, very
interesting kind of from
the theoretical
standpoint question that
we'll sort of uncover over
the next three
lectures, performance.
And in order to
achieve performance,
there are various tricks
that we can easily do.
A lot of low hanging fruit like
separation of control
and data plane.
API design for sharing,
security, basically,
when you have multi process
access to file system,
multi user access to
file systems, right?
How do you enable that?
What are the
mechanisms for this?
And I believe some of that
is actually going to be
part of your lab four.
You know, to implement security
of file system access.
And also the
abstractions are useful,
like pipes. It's an abstraction.
We've come to take
that for granted,
right? But somebody
created that.
So invented that. Devices,
PcofeS and Andro file system.
And I don't have time
to talk about how
cool the Andro file system is,
but this is one example
where someone sat down and
said that The state of
the art file systems
are taking a very
important assumption
that the disk or
the medium with which
we're interacting is
always available.
What if this is not true, right?
How would we design
a file system,
assuming that this is
actually not true?
And that's how Andrew
File system was born.
And Andrew file system
was actually a precursor
for some very important kind of
mobile file systems
where you're dealing
with mobile devices which
are not guaranteed to
be accessible and,
in fact, are accessible,
I don't know, 20,
30% of the time.
In other words, they're
intermittently accessible,
and Andrew file system
was the first that
constructed the set of
abstractions and interfaces that
could handle that transparently.
Okay. So let me
try to get to the stuff that's
actually more important
to your lab four.
We could talk about
the separation of what
a file is versus what
a file descriptor is.
So very briefly, when
you open a file,
you get a file
descriptor, right?
But a file descriptor
does not equal to a file.
And the reason for
this is because
we can have multiple links,
for example, to the same file.
The file can be linked
from multiple directories.
So the information about
a file cannot actually be
stored in any given directory.
It has to be stored
somewhere that
is outside of any directory,
right, in some other place.
So this sort of builds
up motivation for
needing things like things
that are called i notes.
That's why you need notes
because i notes is where
you're going to
store the metadata
associated with the file.
And they're going to maintain
the link count that
basically tells us
how many people or
how many entities elsewhere
or how many directories,
for instance, are
linking to this file.
And this also tells us,
basically, this is a
rough count, right?
This also tells when
can we actually
release and when is it safe
to free a particular iNote?
INte must have a count of
open file descriptors,
and i know the
allocation is deferred
until the last link or file
descriptor is removed.
Okay. So there's actually
a bunch of software
layers and file systems.
The process, then you
have an FS interface,
then you have the
file system interface
that actually deals with blocks,
iOS director and
path resolution.
There's a lower level
that handles the log,
and then you have buffer cache,
and this driver at the
at the lowest level,
you have this firmware, right?
And so basically, um
The block interface
and the Nde handling and
directory and path resolution
are basically handled
by VFS and FS.
And so you will see those in
the code when you
start looking at
XV six and working
on your lab four.
And this is what the on
disk layout looks like.
So at the very beginning,
you have a boot sector,
and we already talked
about the boot sector
at the very beginning
of the class, right?
This is a 512 byte record
that actually stores
the bootloader.
After that, you have
another sector that actually
keep track of the superblock.
It and the superblock
is the first block
of its partition.
So this is when we start
getting into partitions
of the disk.
So superblock is always the
first block of a partition.
And it maintains the metadata
for the entire file system,
which means that this
is where you find
the information about the
location for all the Ns.
This is where you
find the information
about the location of the log.
How big is the log,
which is important for
crash recovery and
things like that.
And more generally,
the superblock is
where you will find metadata
information for the file system.
And these are the files,
the Fs dot H and Fs
dot C and makefs
dot C. This is where you would
find the information
about super block.
The nodes follow, right?
And the very first node
that you will store is
an node associated with
the root directory.
After that, you have the
yellow block bitmap,
and this is where you basically
keep track of on the disk,
you keep track of which
blocks are used or free.
And after that,
you have a set of
data blocks which contain
the actual data that
you want to store.
And at the very end,
you have the log.
Now, what's interesting is that
the XV six file system
has these things
slightly reversed.
So notice that after
the super block,
you have the log, okay?
So boot block is in block zero,
and super block is in block one,
and starting with block two,
this is where you have
the log for some reason.
I'm not exactly sure why.
So here, the log is
at the very end,
but in XV six,
the log actually follows
the super block.
Then after that,
you'll get the notes,
then you'll get the bitmap and
the data all the
way until the end.
Okay.
So Yeah, there's some discussion
that can be had here,
but I'm just going
to condense it by
saying that in most
operating systems,
we use a block actually
consists of multiple sectors.
For example, typically,
a block is actually four
kilobyte sized in a typical,
let's say, Linux
operating system,
which corresponds to
eight sectors, right?
Eight, 512 byte sized sectors.
Now, why would you want
to have this it's not
a coincidence that data a
block is foca sized, right?
It actually matches
the typical size
of a page in a virtual
memory system.
And the reason for
this is because can
somebody tell me why we want
to match those two things?
Yeah, exactly,
because of swapping.
Because when you actually swap
your physical frames using
that clock algorithm
that we talked about,
to disk, you actually
want that to
be the same size as
the block itself.
Okay? And so basically,
that means that the
information about
what was swapped
to disk can be at
the granularity of one
to one mapping between
a physical frame or a
PFN and the block ID.
Just one block holds
the page, right,
instead of having to worry about
how many sectors and
where those sectors are.
So the next bullet
actually summarizes this.
It's to reduce the
bookkeeping and
seek overheads in
order for you to
actually recover the
physical frames that you
swapped out to the disk
because it's going
to be in a set of consecutive
eight sectors instead of
random eight sectors everywhere
on the secondary
storage device. Yes.
What's a log?
Oh, yeah. What's a log?
Do you know what a log is?
Does anybody know what a log is?
So we actually have two
lectures dedicated to this.
So you will come to Lo log.
It's super important for crash
consistency and recovery.
Yes. Doesn't it all
the changes to the
file system in case
you do end up crashing
and end up with
corrupted stuff so that
you can recover yourself?
Yes. So it basically
allows you to
make to record the changes
that you have made
to the file system.
That's correct. Yeah. But it
doesn't keep them indefinitely.
And so there are basically
implications of
this that have to
do with crash consistency.
And we're going to spend
two lectures talking
about ethnicity ordering
and file systems,
and the mechanism for this
is the login file system.
And we'll actually
try to implement
a login file system in
two different ways.
So it's going to be a very
interesting discussion.
Stay tuned a week from today.
So next Thursday is
when we're going to
talk about log FS, okay?
So XV six makes things
easy, makes things simple.
It just uses single
sector blocks.
So in the context of XV six,
a sector is essentially
equivalent to a block.
It's the same 512
byte size, okay?
And what's a metadata
and what metadata
do we want to keep?
Basically, it's
everything on a disk
other than the actual
file content, right?
And it includes the super
blocks, as I mentioned,
because they hold the metadata
for the entire file system,
the location of i nodes,
the location for
bitmap and the logs.
Bitmap is also metadata
because what's a bitmap again?
It's essentially a
data structure, right,
where you set a bit
for zero or one,
depending on whether or
not the corresponding data block
is actually being
used or not used.
And by the way, have
any of you attempted
a defragmentation in your
operating system, a defrag?
So it used to be
a big thing 2005,
I would spend time actually
defragging my disk pretty often.
And the reason for
this is because
the disks at the time were
much smaller than
they are today.
Right now, you get 1 terabyte
and you think it's
common case, you know,
back in the day, you know, you
get I don't even remember,
much, much, much smaller disks.
And so constantly,
it would fill up.
It would fill up
quite easily, right?
And as you reach the
capacity of the disk,
allocating and
deallocating files creates
holes in your data
block structures
like in Swiss cheese, right?
And so in some cases,
you may actually have space
on the disk to store a file,
but you cannot create a file.
The creation of the
file would fail.
But if you diffract that because
it expects consecutive sectors.
But if you defract that,
it would actually
make it possible
for the file to be created.
So And the way we would do that
is by referencing
the bitmap of which
blocks are actually allocated
and which blocks are free.
And Drac would basically update
the location of the blocks
on the secondary storage and
correspondingly
update the bitmap
to reflect the relocation
of the data blocks.
Makes sense? Okay.
So stay tuned for a
Drac test question.
This is recorded, so
you can go back and
listen to it again
if I spoke too fast.
All right. And directories
are basically just
special files,
and I think we're going to
cover directories on Tuesday.
So what is an i node?
I know this is very special, and
you will become intimately
familiar with an i node by
the time you're
finished with lab four.
It has a very specific on
disk data structure, right?
It contains the type because
you need to figure out
if this is this an
iNde that's just free?
So unallocated i node,
it's a thing. It exists, right?
Or is it a file,
or is it pointing
to a directory,
or is it pointing to a device?
Because depending
on these types,
so it's basically like an
overloaded class, right?
Depending on the types of things
you want to be able to
support the metadata for,
you have to type the Nde.
Then you have the
number of links
to this specific i node,
the size and this data structure
that consists of 12
elements plus one,
which is the indirection
or the pointers to the
actual data blocks.
And there's a reason
why it's a 12 plus one.
You have 12 direct pointers
to data blocks and
one indirect pointer that
looks kind of like this.
So the direct block pointers
are basically pointing to block
ID zero through nine or
pointing to data blocks.
And the indirect actually
gives us the ability to
expand the size of the file
that we are able to support.
Okay? So here's what the XB
six ode content looks like.
So again, type, major, minor,
number of links, size,
addresses one through
12 and one indirect.
Okay, so if each address
is actually pointing
to a data block,
which is size 512 bytes,
what is the largest
file size you can
support if you don't
use the indirect?
Yes. Which is 6,108.
It's half a times 12, right?
Half a times 12, so that's six.
Yeah. Very good, very good.
That's pretty small. What
if you want larger files?
This is kind of to motivate,
you know, here's the
thing. It exists.
It's a statement of
fact, but I'm trying
to tell you that there's a
reason behind it, right?
Why do we need this indirect?
Because without an indirect,
you would only be able to
support six size files. Yes.
We guarantee anything about
the contiguity of
any of these logs?
The contiguity of what?
It go like direct,
indirect. That's the thing.
That's why you're using inode
as a layer of
indirection, right?
Because if we did that,
the internal fragmentation
would kill you.
Let's say you want to
allocate a file and if I
were to construct a
question just like
question one on
the midterm exam,
I could give you a
microS question,
where you only have
a limited amount
of space to put the blocks in,
and I would give you, let's say
this type of inode structure,
and I would say that
the requirement is
that the data blocks
have to be contiguous.
You can easily construct
scenarios where you cannot
fit a new file just because
of the contiguity requirements.
So you don't want that just
like you don't want
that in memory.
So the analogue of
an ode in memory is
the virtual memory of VM, right?
The analog of that here is
an node that gives you
a layer of indirection
so that you're not required to
allocate contiguous data
blocks to your file.
Excellent question. Yes.
12 indirect blocks.
What's the point of having
a static 12 blocks of data?
Yeah, so the um Okay,
so this is another very
interesting question, right?
Because just like in
the virtual memory,
the number of times
you have to sort of
indirect by the time
you actually get to
the data is going to cost
you some overhead, right?
So you want to be able to
get to the data as
fast as possible.
So you want as few hops as
possible to get to
the actual content
you're trying to access, right?
And so that's why it sort of
tries to find the balance
of in the distribution of
the file sizes that I have
to deal with in this
particular system,
let's say, 80% of the files are
actually less than or equal
to six kiloabyte size, right?
And then for this
kind of system,
it is sufficient for me to
just use addresses
one through 12.
The remaining 20% of the files
can be supported by
actually taking advantage
of the indirect and paying
the overhead cost of performing
a double pointer indirection
in order to get to
the content for those
larger files, right?
So that's the way to
think about this.
But if, let's say,
on a test, right,
if I told you that a system is
such that it only
has large files,
then maybe you would actually
change the structure of
the ode to reflect the properties
of that system, right?
Because if I tell you
that you will never have
files that are less
than 6 kilobytes,
right, then maybe it doesn't
even make sense to have
those direct address
pointers. Makes sense?
Everything here is quite dynamic
and depends on the properties
of the application.
The answer to the question
that I posed earlier,
the indirect number of entries
multiplied by B size or
block size is going to
give you the 6 kilobytes
of content that you're able to
address directly from an i node.
The last entry is a
pointed to an indirect
and here you basically
have 128 elements.
A one through 128 and this
is specific to XB six.
This is not a general thing.
Specific to XV six,
you have an indirect block
that just consists of
128 direct address pointers.
And so the question is,
what is the largest file size
that you're able to
support in XV six?
Yes. Because six
plus 64 indirect.
That's correct. Kilobytes direct
plus 64 kilobytes indirect.
And the way you get
64 kilos, right,
is you multiply 128
by half a kilo,
which is the size
of a block, right?
Did everyone get that?
Okay. Those are kind of
warm up questions. Warm up.
Okay. Another
interesting thing is
that everything is
highly predictable
and this is good for
forensic analysis.
Anyone that actually goes into
cyber or School of
cybersecurity and privacy,
let's say you recover a
device, a storage device,
then there's actually
quite a bit of
forensic analysis
and information you
can extract from
that storage device.
So let's say, how do you
find the file by 8,000?
Well, given the structure
that I've just given you,
the way you would do it
is you divide 8,000 by
the block size to figure out
which here's my pointer,
8,000 by the block size
to figure out which
block number it is.
In this case, it's 15 and take
the floor of that, right?
So we're dealing with
a logical block 15.
And this corresponds
to a third entry in
the indirect block because
15 is greater than 12,
so we know that it's
not going to be one
of the first two
direct pointers.
So we're overflowing
into indirect,
and it's going to
be the third block
of the indirect, okay?
The node structure
contains the number.
It's easy to turn the
number into an node.
The eye nodes are 64 bytes long
and the byte address on the
disk is five times 512.
Can somebody tell
me why that is?
Five times 512, we're
skipping over what?
Two of something,
which is 512 sized.
Yeah.
No, no, no. We're skipping
over the boot sector
and super block, right?
Yeah, we're skipping over
the boot sector and super block.
Okay. And after that,
we are skipping over Sorry.
After that, we're adding 64,
which is the size of
the node multiplied by
the number of the node
in order to get to
the node itself.
So, for example,
accessing the root
the node associated with
the root directory, right?
Since I mentioned it's
the very first node
that you're storing in
a file system is going to be
two times 512 plus 64
times the number of zero,
which corresponds to the root.
And this is going to be
at 1024 byte offset.
So whenever you extract
a device and you
need to perform a
forensic analysis on it,
look at 1024 byte,
and this is where you'll
find information.
For the root partition,
for the root node, okay?
And this is where we're going to
stop. We're at three oh seven.
Thank you very much.
So