I was like,
one to three.
All right. Good
afternoon, everybody.
We're going to be doing
some whiteboarding today.
So last week, We started
a very important topic,
which is related to your
lab four on file systems.
And this week, what
we're going to
do is we're actually going
to take what we've started with,
the toolbox that
you've built up,
kind of the mechanisms
that you've learned about,
the data layout, right,
the abstractions that are
enabled by file systems,
and we're going to
sort of take that
through a conceptual
furnace, right?
Because we didn't really
get to talk about yet,
what are the interesting
systems challenges
here with file systems, right?
Why should we care about
file systems other than just
knowing how they work and how
they implemented in
an operating system?
In addition to that, we
really want to figure out
what is interesting from
sort of an intellectual
perspective, right?
What is interesting from
a conceptual perspective?
And the way this lecture
and actually over the course
of the next two lectures,
the way we're going to structure
this is we're going
to sort of go through
the motivation and what's
hard with the interface
that's provided to us,
the low level
interfaces that are
provided to us by
the disk, right,
and the application semantics
that would be expected
by the users.
And one of those
things is basically
crash consistency because in
the absence of any support,
anything can happen
with the system,
especially if you simply press
the power button or
something fails.
You rely on secondary storage
and your file system in general,
your data management system
for one critical thing,
which is persistence and
not only persistence,
but persistence in a
way that makes sense,
in a way that doesn't actually
corrupt your data on disk.
Okay? And so that's what we're
going to talk about today.
We're going to build up to it.
I'm going to skip over
administrative Via
because we have so much stuff to
cover that I'm worried
we're going to
spill over into the
distributed systems lecture.
So I'll just jump right
into it unless somebody
else has any questions
about administrative via.
And we can also do that
at the very end as well.
So with respect to
the file systems,
here's a question that I would
like to start with, right?
What happens when
my machine crashes,
shuts down, or in any
way stops unexpectedly?
What do you think
is going to happen?
Specifically, what's going
to happen to your data,
which is the topic of, you know,
these two weeks that we're in.
Oh, wow. Lots of ideas. Yeah.
Sorry?
Okay, so basically you
expect it to be corrupt
in some way, right?
Any other ideas?
Is it just a matter of
corruption or can we
expect something else?
Yeah. Everything.
Yeah, that is true. And that
is to be expected, right?
So throughout these
two lectures,
which are going to
be conceptually
difficult for many people, okay?
Throughout these two lectures,
keep one thing in mind.
You have two different
types of state.
What he said in memory
data structures, right,
that you're going to keep in
memory while the
operating system is
operating normally and
the on disk state, okay?
And we want to make those
two in some way
consistent, right?
We're going to
develop mechanisms
and policies with which we
will be actually persisting
in memory state to
the on disk state.
And we want to be able to
do that in such a way that
guarantees consistency of
our data on recovery. Okay?
It doesn't mean that
we'll be able to recover
everything that was
in memory, right?
And that's not the purpose
of these lectures.
The purpose is for
us to guarantee
consistency of the data
that is recovered,
okay? And that's very important.
Do not expect everything
in memory to actually
end up on disk.
Do we expect whatever ended
up on disk to be consistent,
okay, to not be corrupt.
So that's very important.
Let's walk through a couple
of scenarios, right?
To really motivate this,
it really helps to go through
a couple of examples.
So I'm going to start
drawing timelines here,
which is very common in systems
and in distributed systems.
So you may want to get used
to kind of this way of
thinking about the operation
of systems in general.
So here is one
here's one timeline.
Right. If only this
worked, right?
Okay. I do have a
bunch that work.
So Here's one timeline.
So you're writing the disk.
So there's a right here.
And then there's a crash.
And then after a crash,
you recover, and then
you perform a read
on the same file.
Kind of what is the
expectation here?
What are you expecting to
read in this time sequence?
And time goes down.
This is your time,
wall clock time
or time from a system
perspective to be more precise.
So what do you expect
to get on a read?
What are the when I
ask this question,
you know, don't think
of concrete cases.
Think about the space of
possibilities, right?
What is the and even
better than that,
when I ask these questions,
think about what is the
best case scenario?
What is the worst case scenario?
Are there any situations
in between, right?
So this is called the
boundary condition
reasoning from mathematics.
So that sort of
helps you approach
these questions
whenever they're being
asked in any kind
of test situation.
So, what is the best
case scenario here? Yes.
Unable to read what I
previously wrote in
the right operation.
What?
Unable to read everything
that I wrote in the.
Yes, that's right.
That's the best case.
What's the worst case scenario?
Yeah. The right never even
persisted to disk, right?
And it's actually
not the worst case.
It depends on from the
perspective of what.
But from the perspective of
state transitioning from the
logical in memory data structure
to a physical on
disk layout, sure.
We can say that it's
either all or nothing.
Those could potentially be
reasoned as the best
and the worst cases.
Any other situations
that are possible, yes.
Like halfway completed, and then
now you have complete
garbage data.
Yeah, exactly. And this is
just like grading exams, right?
So the easiest
questions to grade
are either you get it
completely right or you
get it completely wrong.
And whenever there's some
kind of partial state,
so it's sort of partially
persisted and partially didn't,
you know, that really creates
a lot of complications.
And so when you read,
you can actually get
garbage data if you do
nothing at all, right?
So that's one example.
Here's another example.
So let's say you have two files,
file A and D, A and B,
and the two file
descriptors associated with
them are Fg one and Fg two.
So there is a right to
a file descriptor one,
and there's another right And
it may sound similar to
what we've just discussed,
but there's a slight nuance
that I want to emphasize.
And then there's a crash.
Okay? And let's just, you know,
logically you have
file A and file B,
and file descriptor one
corresponds to file A.
File descriptor two
corresponds to file B.
So what is the space of
possibilities after this crash?
Again, best case scenario,
obviously, everything
persisted, right?
And so after the crash,
you may actually expect
the contents you wrote to
file descriptor one and two
to be there on the disk.
Okay, what are some
other possibilities?
So that could be like a
freebie on the exam, right?
What are some other
possibilities?
Yeah. Sorry?
Okay. Mid right, like what?
In between the rights or
mid the first right I mean,
the crash happened after
you've actually called
right and the right
returned just to make
it very clear, okay?
So it doesn't really
happen mid right.
These are cys calls, right?
And these cscals were blocking
cys calls and they have
returned just to make
that very clear.
And then the crash happened.
What do you expect to see?
Let's say in the
worst case, right,
that we discussed
here, you may actually
expect to see nothing, right?
There may be absolutely nothing,
no updates that
were persistent to
file descriptor
one and two, okay?
But that is actually, again,
a really good case, which
we'll figure out why
that is the case.
Now, what are some of
the other options?
Can we have a written but not B?
Yes. Can we have B
written but not A?
So pay attention to this,
can we have B written but not A?
Let's say yes because
we can't we're not
blocking those rights.
So there's no
sequentiality guarantee.
So probably B goes first and
then A goes second and
then B rights any of us.
Yeah. So the
important thing here,
as he pointed out, right,
is that you're not
guaranteed the sequentiality
of those you're not
guaranteed the sequentiality.
Of those two rights being
persisted to disk if you
do nothing at all, okay?
And so that's very important
because now all of
a sudden, again,
as a system programmer,
you might be thinking, Oh,
I code right on FD
one write on FD two.
So therefore, in the
case of consistency,
the space of possibilities is
such that I will have seen
more rights in FD one or all
rights in FD one before I
see any rights in FD two,
and that is not the case, okay?
So you can actually have
some arbitrary order of
data blocks being
persistent across
FD one and FD two.
Anything is possible.
Any possibility of
mutated blocks for
FG one and mutated data
blocks for FG two,
kind of any subset
of the union of
those data blocks or data
block sets can be persistent.
That's insane, right? If I were
to ask you to define the
space of possibilities,
that's the space
of possibilities.
A set of all subsets from
the union of data
blocks mutated on
FG one right and FG two right.
And that includes the empty set
that includes the full set as
the boundary conditions
that we've just
talked about. With me?
Awesome. Awesome. Thank you.
Okay. Now, this one
is slightly more
interesting than this?
That seemed like a
trivial question
compared to that because
now we're messing
around with your
mental understanding
of what it means to order
things in a file system,
right? Here's another example.
We are writing to a
file descriptor, Fg.
We're writing something, let's
say it's just a string A.
Then there's a crash, and
then we're performing a read
from a file descriptor.
And then the question is,
what is it outputting, right?
So basically, this seems
like a version of what
we already discussed
on the left hand side,
but there's a possibility
here to actually corrupt
the metadata of the file
corresponding to a file
descriptor one, right?
So for instance, what might
happen is that let's start going
and digging into the
toolbox that was
built up over the course of
the last two lectures, right?
What does it mean to
write to a file, okay?
What is a file? What's
a representation
of a file in a file system?
How do we represent a file?
Let's break this down.
Take one step lower.
Yeah, go ahead. File metadata
that we want as programmers,
and then lines that the file.
Location of that.
Yeah. So at a high level,
we have two things, right?
We have metadata and real data.
So that's the next level down in
terms of our level of detail
that we're going to cover.
We have metadata
and we have data.
So what data structure
do we use for metadata?
We use an node, right?
So let's say that this is
our node for file A, okay?
And on the right hand side,
we're going to have a
set of data blocks.
So these are data blocks.
And remember that there's
a physical location on disk that
corresponds to the locations
of the data blocks for real,
as well as a separate
physical location for i
nodes where we actually store
the metadata associated
with the files.
And those are two separate
update operations.
So whenever we mutate the file,
we can potentially be
mutating the metadata because
what's in the metadata, right?
We have the NAM, right?
We have the size
somewhere, right?
And we have the 12
direct pointers,
where the direct pointers,
I'm going to put a dot,
dot, dot here, direct
pointers are pointing to
some data blocks that
are on disk, okay?
So let's say we had two direct
pointers pointing here,
and this write is
actually trying to
sever this connection
and point them somewhere else
and perform this update.
So this is an illustration
of what would
happen if we're trying to
perform a write on a file.
Right? What could
happen is that you
might be mutating the
data in these two blocks,
and, of course, mutation
is not allowed in place.
So what you have to do
is you perform a copy,
right, and then you
mutate it over here.
And in order to do this,
you have to perform the
actual copy and mutation,
and you have to update
the pointers to point to
the new data blocks, right?
You see how we've broken it down
into finer granularity
operations,
which all of a sudden
makes it clear
that unless they're atomic,
there's something bad
that can potentially
happen in the process of
us performing this
operation. Yes.
Right in the second,
like, middle case, right,
want to writes atomic
you said there, right?
It's like right FD one returns,
and then right FTU runs.
Why is that not atomic?
Like why can FD two be
written but not FD Because
a right cisco does not
guarantee that the data
was persisted to disk.
So, let's say you send an
IO request to the disk,
that doesn't finish
processing before you
return in your OS or
the right cysco is
allowed to return
before the data is
persisted to disk. Okay.
So how many of you
find this as new?
Yeah, see, that's
very important.
That's why we're having
this conversation,
and I'm spending time on
motivating this thing.
So you might have thought
that when you
perform a write and
the write is a
blocking call that
performs a cis call
into your kernel,
comes back, you hope
that the data is on
this, but it's not.
It's in some write
buffer somewhere.
And it may not even
be persistent to this
for some extended non
trivial amount of time.
If you actually
wanted this kind of
interface that
guarantees persistency,
and we're going to
cover that hopefully
by the end of the next lecture.
If you actually want that kind
of persistency and guarantee,
your rise would actually
be insanely slow.
And so for performance reasons,
what they've decided is
they decided to come
back from a Cisco
and basically say,
all good, the operating
system and the files,
the lower levels of
the file system are
going to take care
of persistent disk at
some point in time.
Yes.
In terms of atomicity of
each right instruction?
Yes. So the right is not
guaranteed to be atomic disk.
Don't use the word atomic.
It's not guaranteed to
persist to disk. Yes. Yes.
Just so I'm clear on it, we
have a situation where let's
say the first right
goes halfway.
Sure. The second also goes up.
Yes. You can have
that situation.
Yeah, and that's
what I meant when
I was talking about the
space of possibilities here.
Again, I can very
easily envision myself
asking this question,
describe mathematically a
space of possibilities if
we reason about the individual
data block updates.
Because there's a
set of data blocks
that's going to be mutated
by the first right.
There's a set of data blocks
you want to mutate
on the second right.
Then the question is, what is
the space of possibilities?
Describe it as a set
over the subsets of those
data blocks, right?
And I said that any
subset is possible.
It's basically a power set
of the union of those two.
Yes.
Separate rights are done
by two separate processes.
No, it's the same process.
How come it's that
sometimes like
FD two might occur before
in the middle of FD one?
If it's in the same
process, isn't that?
So remember, I'm describing
I'm not describing a file system
that already has
something in place to
take care of ordering atomicity.
I'm describing a situation
if we don't have
the primitives for
ordering atomicity.
Okay. Yeah, that's a very good
question because you would
expect the correct behavior
because you use the
same operating system
that's already
taken care of that.
But we're sort of building
up to this to really
motivate the mechanisms that
you need in order for
this to happen. Yeah.
So it's not guaranteed
that I persist the disk.
Yeah. Let's say you
a little bit crash.
You just write and you read.
When you read, is it
guaranteed that what you
wrote is in the file or
the The read after write
has the same semantics.
Yeah. And we're going to
explain how that's enabled,
even if you don't persist
what you wrote the disk,
because you'll be reading
from some other location
where that data will have
been persistent, okay?
And back to your question, like,
even in the sane
operating system,
what I said earlier
is true, the write
does not guarantee persistence.
It just guarantee just
guarantees crash consistency,
which is what's important.
Okay? All right.
Any other questions
about these scenarios?
It's easy to spend it like
the rest of the lecture
talking about this.
For instance, for
instance, okay?
We just covered security,
and, you know, buffer overflows,
you had an awesome supervised
lab that the core staff
has delivered with
passion yesterday, right?
Now, can you envision
some security implications
with partial file updates?
If we do nothing,
if we don't have
atomicity or
ordering guarantees.
What can possibly happen
here if, for example,
in the process of
updating the metadata
for the Nde for A, you know,
we crashed, and we didn't really
update the actual blocks
with the content we
wanted to write.
What can happen from a
security perspective?
Yeah. A file can gain access
to a block that belonged to
a different file
and then read data
from something that it shouldn't
have had access to
in the first place.
Yeah, exactly. This could
have been somebody
else's private SSH key.
They're just data blocks.
They stored some content.
What abstraction that should be
guaranteed by an operating
system does this violate?
Yes. Isolation. So see
how we've sort of
started from the very,
very low level view of
what's happening on
a file mutation and
percolated all the
way up to the top and sort
of motivated the fact
that something bad can happen
even from a very high
level perspective.
The isolation here would be
broken if we don't have the
mechanisms to fix this.
If we don't have the mechanisms
for crash consistency,
if we don't have atomicity
and ordering guarantees.
Okay. Because in this
particular case,
we will have updated the
direct pointers to point to
data blocks that may actually
have somebody else's data,
regardless of what that data is,
we really do not
want this to happen.
Okay, I have other examples,
but I think I
think I'm just going to
move on to a different
example here, okay?
So basically, how do we know
if my data persisted to disk?
We talked about that. You don't.
How do I ensure that
the file system metadata
wasn't corrupted? We're
going to discuss this.
Basically, the
mechanisms for this
are that you need some
primitives of ordering,
and you need some
primitives for ethnicity.
Ordering basically
refers to imposing
some partial order on
the file updates, okay?
And we do have a
mechanism for this that
is generously provided to
us by the low level system,
and that's called
the flush, okay?
And atomicity is basically
the ability for us to
perform updates in an
all or nothing fashion.
In other words, when you are
trying to do
something atomically,
you want to make sure
that either everything in
this atomicity block is done or
rather the way in
which it mutates
the universe is visible all
at once or not at all, okay?
And no partial updates,
no partial state mutations
are actually possible.
When you impose ethnicity.
Okay. Here's another example.
And in this particular example,
what we're doing is quite
simple on the surface.
What we're doing is we're
creating a directory, right?
And then we're performing
to a file creation
inside this directory.
So what are some
of the questions are
sort of being asked,
what happens if Mad is actually
sync to disk after they open?
So with Elton during
the previous lecture,
did you cover the directories
and the durance structure?
Oh, yeah, you touched
upon that, right?
So you know that the
directory basically has
its own directory block
with durance, right?
And durance corresponds to
the individual files that
the directory is
linking to, right?
And so think about this
from this perspective.
You're you're creating X,
which is your directory,
then you're creating
a file inside X,
which is your file.
And as I mentioned,
you do not necessarily
you're not
necessarily guaranteed the
ordering of those operations.
So what if you sync the
metadata corresponding to Y
before you sync the creation
of the directory X?
Yes. You can't read
from disk because what you
want isn't actually in disk.
So maybe you have a memory
representation permitting.
Okay. So maybe you could have
a system where you're in
memory storage has almost
like a dirty bit, right?
Where it if it's dirty,
then it signifies that
it hasn't been san yet.
It's dirty. Then it is.
So before you go
to every location is the
information I report.
If it isn't it,
if it's not, then I'm
going to just get it.
Okay. Yes, I think you're
going in the right direction,
but we just need to sort of
concretize what you said
a little bit, right?
We need to give it
very concrete and precise shape
because I really like precision.
So let's try to make
it more precise.
So here's our directory block.
I'm going to try to write it
on this board and
then maybe I'll
switch around to try
to preserve state.
So here's our directory block.
This is directory block D block.
Inside this directory block,
and this is d block
for X, by the way.
Inside this directory
block, we have Dur ends.
This is our Dr end.
N, okay?
And what does dur consist of?
It consists of the file num,
a 14 byte file num, in
this particular case,
Y, and the node number
corresponding to this
file num, all right?
And so the conceptual
representation
here is that clearly this num is
sort of a pointer to the
node for file Y, right?
Because NOM defines the location
on disk where you should be
able to find the eye node
for the file Y, okay?
So you have this eye node,
and we know what's
inside the eye node.
We have the number, right?
We have size, and we
have our favorite what?
What?
How do we keep track of
data from an eye node?
Yeah.
Yeah, the pointers to
direct blocks, right?
These are our ADDRs
that give us the pointers
to direct blocks.
And now, finally, we
have a third thing here,
which is a set of data blocks,
which is yet another
location on disk,
right, to which these
pointers are pointing to.
Okay? And so In order
for you to ask these questions
that you currently see
on the overhead, right?
What happens if Mader is
synced for disk after open?
You should really draw
the conceptual diagram of
what's involved in the process
of calling a Madir and calling
an open that creates a
file Y inside directory X.
And this is what happens.
You have to create a
directory block for X.
That's what Mad is going
to take care of, right?
And then within that
directory block for X,
you will create a
Durant for file Y
on the open Sysco when you're
creating file Y, okay?
So basically, this is one,
the creation of the dead block,
and this is two, this
and this right here,
the mutation of the mutation
of the data blocks.
And so the question is asking,
what happens if you are going to
sync if you're going to sync
the Mad to disk after open?
So open will have
created the ide, right,
and it will have set up
the metadata for
the Wi file i node,
and Mad will have
created the DR block
and updated the DR entry
for the file, right?
So what will happen if
these are out of order?
Anything bad? What
concretely would happen now?
Well, you will have
created this node,
right, in the system,
but nothing is pointing to it.
If there is a crash,
there is no way to interact
into the i node, right?
There's no way to actually
operate on this file.
So in some sense, you
will have this state
that corresponds to the file
to which nobody is pointing.
And so that will actually lead
to the i node leakage, right?
You just like you can
potentially leak memory by
allocating memory
and then shifting
the pointer away from the
memory you're allocating.
This is the same
situation where you've
allocated the metadata
for the file Y,
but then nobody
is pointing to it
because you haven't
persisted to disk.
Okay? So in this
particular case,
the out of order updates for
the metadata for file note and
the DR block for directory
X is a huge problem, okay?
And there's some
additional things
to consider. Let's see.
What happens if metadata
is corrupted for Y?
And so we sort of already
talked about that, right?
And what happens if X D entry
is written before's I Note data?
And that's basically what
I have just described.
Any question about this?
No questions.
Okay. Okay, and this
is a refresher for
directory representation.
Basically, you have,
as we discussed,
you have a Duren which consists
of the NM and a file number,
and the Durent is
free if iNM is zero.
So basically that's how
we are able to reuse
the Durant inside
the directory block.
And the Durant itself
has the two important
fields that we care about.
One of them is the NM itself,
and the second one is
the name of the file.
Okay. So by now,
what we should really appreciate
is that the interface that
is given to us by the
disk is very low level.
All you get is the
ability to read a block,
the ability to write a block,
and you don't have
any guarantees
over the order in which
this happens, right?
Because the low
level disk drivers
are actually allowed
to reorder data,
buffer data, and perform
these things in a
nonatomic fashion.
And Thank goodness there is
one operation like flush
that actually gives
us some sense of control over
the order of operations.
Because flush, what does it do?
It gives us the
ability to wait in
a blocking fashion until
all pending reason writes.
And by reason writes here,
I mean the low level read and
write operations to disk,
okay, are actually synced to
disk before flush returns.
And so that's what we
have to work with.
So basically, it gives us
some operations or
some primitives
with which we can actually
construct a partial order.
So here's a way to
appreciate the level of
control that you get
with the flush, right?
So let's say that you've
issued over the course
of a couple of writes,
let's say, right to file disk,
right to FD one.
Let's say issue the
right block 47.
So you write block 47,
that's your operation
number one.
Then the second one
is right block two.
Right block two.
And the third one is right
block 48, block 48, right?
And then you issued
a right block 49.
So in what order would you
expect these operations
to actually happen?
Give me a really good guess.
Given what we know about
spinning disks and what
we discussed last year, reset.
Okay, so you expect
something here to impose
the order because
the first batch of
write operations and the
second batch of operations.
Not yet. That's what we
want to happen, right?
But not yet. So yes.
Yeah, something
like this, right?
You would actually
expect the underlying
the underlying the underlying
low level system software
to actually order
them as follows,
47, 48 followed by 49,
and then two maybe before
because then it's monotonically
increasing, right?
Or it may be after, you know,
both possibilities are
kind of very likely.
So that's what could
potentially happen, right?
And so you can see that you
can easily achieve
the interleaving of
the block writes across
the two actually file
descriptor updates.
Now, if you actually
want the first batch of
rights to complete before
the second batch of rights,
we do have an operation
that gives us this ability,
and that's the flush operation.
Conceptually, what
happens is that
the flush operation
essentially imposes
a partial order over a set
of 47 48 sorry, 472 and 48.
With a set that consists
of block number 49, okay?
So it imposes a happens before
relationship between this
subset and this subset.
So we know that if we
impose a flash right here,
that it gives us a happens
before relationship
that we wanted.
Yeah. There's no ordering.
There's no ordering within
that set. That's correct.
Yeah. Does everybody understand
this conceptualization?
Would you be given this,
would you be able to enumerate
all possible orders in
which the riots can actually
happen on a physical disk?
How many possible
orders are there?
Can somebody give me a
mathematical description of
how many possible
orders are there given
this partial directed le graph?
Yeah. Oh, for the flush,
so there's three,
there's three rights in
the first, block, I guess.
And so there's six different
orderings of those.
Yeah. So you have to consider
all permutations of that.
And there's only one
possible possibility
for the second right block
because it has to write 49.
But just six times 16.
Yeah, exactly. It's
three factorial.
Does everybody see that, right?
Because in general, if
you have some set A with
N elements and a
partial order with
a set B with K elements,
it's going to be what?
N factorial multiplied
by a factorial.
That's the number
of possibilities of
the orders that you
are going to achieve,
which is much better
than just N plus
K factorial that you
could otherwise have without
this ordering operation.
But that's a side note.
Okay? I just want you to make
sure that these are very
powerful primitives.
It's not just for the sake
of coming up with notation.
It actually has something
very concrete meanings.
Okay, so as operating
system developers
as file system developers,
kind of the job that
we have is how do we
turn this partial disk
or write interface with
flashes into the atomic
multi block and note update
that our file system
actually needs?
Oh, by the way, you
can actually not
update in place because
the disk interface
doesn't allow it.
Right? If you want to
mutate if you actually
want to mutate a
particular block
in your data block
section of the disk,
you have to perform a copy.
And only then you can
override that copy
before you can actually
mutate that content, right?
And so there are two primary
methods that we're going to
discuss this week and next week,
and they're called
shadowing and logging.
Have you heard you must have
heard of logging before,
but has anyone
heard of shadowing?
You've heard of
shadowing? Okay, perfect.
Has anyone else
heard of shadowing?
No. Was there a question?
Yes. Question.
Why did they make it so that
you can't update in place?
Because doesn't that mean
that you always have to
have an extra iNde or just
replace an existing iNde and
wouldn't that be a waste
of data or storage?
Yeah, a lot of these
decisions were made by
the disk manufacturers in order
because they know the
physics of the disk.
They know what behaves
optimally from the perspective
of interacting with the disk.
And oftentimes they made this
very weird kind of well,
from our perspective, from a
system software perspective,
very weird and clumsy interfaces
that are very hard to work
with because they sort
of know what works really
well for the disk.
And so I can't really answer
that question because
I don't know.
But more generally, even
in the case of SSDs,
they make really
kind of strange,
uh operations that are even more
difficult to explain compared
to the rotating disks.
And all we have to do is
given this interface,
we're trying to make
it into something
that is actually
crash consistent.
So one way to make it crash
consistent is shadowing.
So we're going to start
talking about shadowing here.
In the next sort of 10 minutes,
let's try to cover shadowing,
at least the high
level conceptual
understanding of shadowing.
The idea here is to try to
make the actual update of
my data an operation that
must be done atomically.
And we're going to perform that
achieve that with a
single Boolean bit flip.
So how are we going
to accomplish this?
I'm going to have a
diagram in a second.
So the first thing we're
going to do is we're going
to make a copy of the data,
and at any given point in time,
we'll essentially be operating
on two copies of the data.
One of them is active and
the other one is shadow.
And then we create a
separate shadow bit
that actually flips
between them in
order to signify
which version at
any given point in time is
going to be active. Yes.
About flushing. So what's
the harms in flushing
after every write?
Because it's very expensive.
Yeah, the flush is a very
expensive operation.
So while it will be correct
to flush after every write.
So going back to the question
that he asked in the very
beginning of the lecture, right,
you could actually do that,
but it's going to you will
basically be seeing a huge
performance overhead
associated with that.
Yeah, you could do that.
And so, over the
course of kind of
the discussion of
shadowing and logging,
what I'm going to
be focusing on is,
how do we actually continue
to make it correct, right?
How do we ensure
optimistity and ordering?
So correctness here
is discussed and
evaluated from the perspective
of optimity and ordering,
while at the same time trying to
improve the performance
of our operations.
Where the performance,
the proxy for
improving performance
is how many read and
write operations
we have to do and
how many flashes we have to do
as the most expensive
operation. Yes.
So do you make this a copy
of the data disk America?
Disk.
Well, if it's a disk,
I'm assuming you alternate
between editing the data.
Then what if in between
you edit the data,
there's a crash, but you
haven't finished your
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah. So let's walk through it.
I'll answer the question
on the next slide, okay?
You'll see what's going to
happen. And we'll
think through this.
That's but by the way,
I don't want to dismiss
his question because it's
a very good question.
And these are the kinds of
questions you want to
ask as you flip through
these slides as you rewatch
this video one more time, right?
You know, what happens if a
crash happens at
this point in time?
Do I still get
crash consistency?
Remember, that's the
thing we're after, okay?
Do I still get
crash consistency?
And so the insight here is,
can I actually proxy
large data block updates with
a single atomic bit
flip operation?
So let's look at some pictures.
Here's shadowing illustrated.
On the left hand side,
you have a current
data block, right?
And you want to mutate
the current data block.
I believe you're trying to
update the value for why.
You cannot do that in place.
So you copy data.
Now you copy it to
a completely different
data block, okay?
Now there's two data blocks,
one active, one shadow.
At this moment in time,
the active data block
is the one to which the
shadow bit is pointing.
Shadow bit will only have
two states, zero or one,
which corresponds to
either the left hand side
or the right hand side,
conceptually, okay.
After you've performed
the copy, you want
to update the data.
So now you can actually perform
the update on the copy.
And when you're done updating,
now you want to flip
the shadow bit,
okay, and watch the flip.
The shadow bit after it flips,
it points to the
current version or to
the most updated version
of the data that you
want to operate on.
Have you seen or do you recall,
did you live long enough to
actually experience the effects?
First of all, does anybody know
about double buffering in GPU?
So, for those of you doing
gaming, for instance, right,
the double buffering in GPU
is what enables a smooth.
Yeah, you know about
double buffering, right?
Okay, good. What is it?
The pixels to one buffer
before you display it so
that you don't get to it.
Yeah, there are two
display buffers,
literally two display buffers,
and you write out the
entire you render
and rasterize the entire
frame into the buffer before
you actually flip
the bit in order to
point in order to display
that entire buffer at once.
What happens if
you don't do that?
Has anyone seen I did,
what happens if you don't
have double buffering? Yeah.
Like hearing because
only half of
the buffer has been masterize
so far, screen searing.
And, you know, going back
to the end of 90s, right?
You could actually
because there was
no double buffering
at the end of 90s,
you could literally see
the screen searing
kind of like this,
rendering one line at a
time on your CRT monitor,
cathode ray tube monitor.
And so the idea here
is quite similar.
So we're trying to perform
an update to the data,
and then we flip the bit
in an atomic fashion so
that it gives us this sense of
all or nothing semantics, right?
And hopefully that
answers your question.
You were wondering,
what if we crash in
the middle of a
copy? Do we care?
We don't care, right?
If we crash in the
middle of a copy,
our shadow bit is still
pointing to the current data,
and so on recovery,
we still have consistent data.
What happens if we
crash on an update?
Do we care? Because we
haven't updated the
shadow bit yet, right?
And so who cares if there's
a partial update to show,
to shadow on the right
hand side, right?
Now, here's a tricky question.
What happens if we
actually crash on the
shadow bit update?
Now, that's why the
shadow bit update
is actually a Boolean flip
because a Boolean flip
is either zero or
anything other than zero.
Okay? And so there's really
no way to crash in such a way
that you get an
intermediate state
between zero and something
other than zero.
It's either zero or
it's not zero, okay?
So no matter how you crash,
you will leave the flip bit
in one of those two states,
a zero or not zero,
which is really elegant.
It's an elegant way of ensuring
crash consistency for a
shadow bit update, okay?
And so we actually get
atomicity by using
a Boolean variable for
a shadow bit update.
Does that make sense?
Okay, very good.
And so, yeah,
basically, now that
we've flipped the shadow bit,
we're pointing to
the current data,
and the other block is
becoming the shadow data.
And so for what that means,
by implication, we're
going to get to
that hopefully in a
couple of minutes, right?
By implication, what
that means is you're
essentially doubling
the amount of space
you need to have for all of
your data in order to actually
do something like this.
So the overhead of ensuring
crash consistency with
this particular baseline is
huge, and it's just space.
We haven't even touched
the performance yet. Okay?
So let's talk about performance.
We discussed that the copy
doesn't have to be atomic.
It can result in a partial copy.
We don't care. We discussed
about the possibility of
creating a partial update.
We don't care. We haven't
flipped the bit yet, right?
And the bit flip we already
discussed is binary.
So that's the beautiful kind of
enabling technique for us
to ensuring atomicity.
Now, Um, I wanted to
talk about basically
in what order do
we need to perform
these operations?
Because there are
three operations.
You perform a copy,
we perform an update,
and you perform a bit flip.
Now, can we perform
a copy and an update without
a flaush in between?
Can we sort of send them to
the disk at the
same time without
an ordering primitive
in between?
Yeah. Because if let's
say you do the update
or you copied over,
it's going to get overwritten.
So you need the copy
to happen first.
Right. So basically, here,
one thing to remember is that
the disk interface does give
us one additional
useful feature.
If there are two rights
to the same data block,
it will make sure that right
after right consistency
is not violated.
Okay. So remember
that because of this,
we actually get this additional
ordering primitive in our favor,
but only if there's
a sequence of writes to
the same data block,
you are actually given the
right after right consistency.
Otherwise, you would be
in a very bad shape.
And so you don't actually need
a flaush between a
copy and an update.
You can essentially issue
a copy an issue update,
and don't impose a
flush in between
because that disk interface
is going to take
care of that, okay?
So you can actually perform
a copy and an update,
um I'm going to call
it simultaneously.
So without an ordering
primitive in between.
That's the precise definition
of simultaneously here, okay?
So I'm putting them into
the same vertex right here.
So one and two can
happen simultaneously.
And there's a precise
definition for this.
No ordering primitive 1-2.
That's what
simultaneously means.
Okay. Now, what about
the bit flip three?
Can the bit flip happen
at the same time
simultaneously with
one and or two?
I'm being very mathematically
precise because that kind of
precision is required
in order for us
to reason about the
correctness of systems.
Yes. Why not? Precisely?
The binary operation of
the template is supposed
to have been when both
copy and the update is
finished in the order
that we initially
intended to include.
If you don't execute
the copy and
then the right and then ensure
both of those are finished,
you cannot you cannot
flip the shadow.
Therefore, you can't put the
shadow simultaneously with
either of these operations
before or during the res.
Yeah, that's correct.
Because the semantics
of flipping the bit is
that the operations prior to
that bit flip have finished.
How do we ensure
that the copy and
an update has finished
prior to the bit flip?
We perform a flash, okay?
So we actually do need
to insert a flash
here in order to ensure
the ordering 1-2,
which can happen
simultaneously, and three.
Phew. So we've just discussed
a single block update.
What does it
require? It requires
basically two
copies, two writes,
a write for one and two,
and an additional
write for three,
and it requires a flush from
the performance perspective.
Here's a right, here's a right,
and we insert a
flush in between.
This gives us a correct sequence
of operations and
a partial order
that ensures that correctness.
Two writes and a
flush. All right.
Now, what if we actually want to
perform two writes
back to back, okay?
And so I basically copied
the structure at the very
bottom of this slide,
and you would expect a lot
of things to be
symmetric, right?
You still need to
perform a copy.
That's your operation
number four,
right, from the
current to the shadow.
You still need to perform
an update on the shadow,
and then you have a
separate shadow bit
for every single data block.
And so you need to you
need to flip that
shadow bit, right?
And that's your
operation number six.
So we've already established
the partial order for the
first update operation.
We have a vertex
for one and two.
We have a vertex for three.
We impose a partial order with a
flush 1-2 and three, okay?
And symmetrically, since
we're doing the same thing,
right, you have a vertex for
operations four and five.
You have a vertex
six corresponding
to the flipping the
shadow bit operation,
which is a mutation
operation, right?
And we have a partial
order in between.
Did you follow that? Yes.
Does this mean every data block
has a data block
associated with it?
Yes, exactly. This means that
in order for us to actually
enact this mechanism of
ensuring crash consistency,
the overhead
associated with that
is to have a shadow block
for every single data block.
You increase this
is a huge overhead.
It's two X overhead. Yes.
This probably isn't like what's
implemented like actual system.
Huh? This isn't what's
implement actual It is not.
But the reason we're
talking about this is
because we want to
appreciate that what's
implemented in the real system,
including XV six, is
a lot more performance while
ensuring crash
consistency, right?
And so if I just jump
to that straight,
you would not appreciate
that difference.
And so the question here is,
do you need a flash in between
the vertex three and a
vertex four and five?
In other words, should
we allow, right?
What does that mean? What
does this question mean?
It means that should we allow
simultaneously simultaneously
of operation three and 45?
Can 45 happen before three? Yes.
I'm inclined to say
no just because
the shadows like flipping
the shadow bit ensures that
you're pointing to
your current frame,
and then without
having done that,
four would be copying the
older version, right?
Yeah, exactly, exactly, right?
It usually takes people
longer to figure this out.
And so the trick here is that if
you're operating on
different data blocks,
you could get away
without a flash, right?
But you cannot ensure that
you're operating on
different data blocks.
So in the situations in
the corner cases where
a subsequent update
is actually to
the same data blocks that
was just previously mutated,
you actually need to
perform this flash
because otherwise you would
be copying the older
version of the data.
Do you see that? Does
everybody see that? Okay.
Question. Hold on a second.
Does that make sense to bundle
the one to flush
the operation with an additional
flush after the degree,
just to ensure that in the
event that you are going to be
writing or reading from
the new data once again,
you are always going to
have the correct
shadowing of the screen?
Yeah, basically,
yes. That's right.
Yeah. So, this
means that we need
a flush operation and
a flush operation between
every single one of
these bubbles, right?
And the flush operation across
the individual
mutations to the file.
Okay, so that seems
very, very expensive.
Now, what have we achieved?
Like, remember, let's go
back to the high level.
What did we want? We want
ethnicity and ordering, right?
Because otherwise things looked
dire without ethnicity
and ordering primitives,
right here, as we've established
in the beginning
of this lecture.
Have we achieved ethnicity?
Have we achieved ordering?
Right? So this seems like
a sane solution because
it achieved correctness,
right? We've achieved eeity.
Precisely how have we achieved
eeicity by virtue of using
a Boolean shadow bit,
which only has the ability to
switch between the two
versions zero and non zero.
So the bit flip is
crash consistent.
So if I were to
ask you precisely
how is showing
achieving atomicity,
you should be able to
give me this answer.
It achieves eomicity by
virtue of using a
Boolean shadow bit flip,
which only exists in
one of two states.
There is no partial
state possible.
And therefore, this mechanism
is crash consistent.
Okay? And what are the
costs of shadowing?
Well, as someone has
already pointed out,
it's a two space,
very bad, plus the
shadow bit block.
It also requires a right to
a shadow bit on every
version update, right?
And so it's at least
two disk writes
a copy and an update
as one right,
which could be coalesced,
right, and a shadow
as another right.
The shadow must be
a separate bit,
so it must exist somewhere
else on the disk, right?
And often this results in
large amounts of wasted
space. Can we do better?
Does it make sense for
us to use shadowing?
I think people have
started asking,
no, this seems really odd.
Why would I ever use that? Yeah.
About the flushing.
So I know you said that
we ensure right after
right consistency.
Do we ensure read after
write consistency?
Yes, I believe so. I actually
got the same
question a year ago,
and I'm going to go with
a yes on that, okay?
I believe that's true. Yeah.
Let go back to the previous
slide for a second.
If we insure read after
write consistency,
don't we not have
to flush between
three and then 45
because wouldn't the 45
have to refer to
reading the shadow it and
we're trying to write
to it before it anyway?
Well, in this particular case,
you're making a copy, right?
And so, let's take
this offline because it's
already a three oh two.
I can discuss this
with you afterwards.
But basically, there
are some corner cases
there that require flush.
I'm going to try to
get to the punch line
here that what we really
want to use is logging,
which is also called journaling.
And this is also what's
implemented in this XV six.
And we're going to pick up
on logging in the next lecture.
So logging is a very
interesting data structure,
and it's the data
structure that is enjoying
even a lot of active research in
the scientific
community for systems.
And so we'll give it
full treatment over the
course of the next lecture.
So have a good weekend and
I'll see you on Tuesday.
Thank you.
Okay.